./transcriptions/m54-3.xml:63:          <l>for coins. When he was walking in <del>his</del> the <rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch" key="Archbishop of Canterbury">
./transcriptions/m54-3.xml:68:          <l><rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch">Canterburys</rs> garden, <quote source="#" rend="inline">" the poor come 
./transcriptions/m54.xml:433:          <l>for coins. When he was walking in xxx the <rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch">
./transcriptions/m54.xml:438:          <l><rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch">Canterburys</rs> garden, <quote source="#" rend="inline">" the poor come 
./transcriptions/m54.xml:2356:          <l>and <rs type="place" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#pla-carl">Carlisle</rs> and <rs type="place" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#pla-stal">St Albans</rs>; there is the <rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch">Archbishop of</rs></l>
./transcriptions/m54.xml:2357:          <l><rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch">Canterbury</rs> and <rs>St Pauls</rs>. But the roads lead past London to</l>
./transcriptions/m51.xml:737:          <l><rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch" key="Archbishop of Canterbury">Archbishop of Canterbury</rs> and <rs type="place" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#pla-stpa" key="St Paul's Cathedral">St 
./transcriptions/m53.xml:810:          <l>the <rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch" key="Archbishop of Canterbury">Archbishop of Canterburys</rs> garden there 
./transcriptions/m1-8-1.xml:389:          <l>There is <rs type="place" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#pla-lond" key="London">London</rs>, there is the <rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch" key="Archbishop of Canterbury">Archbishop of Canterbury</rs>. <del>But at</del></l>
./transcriptions/m1-8-2.xml:335:          <l><rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch" key="Archbishop of Canterbury">
./transcriptions/m54-9.xml:142:          <l>and <rs type="place" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#pla-carl" key="Carlisle">Carlisle</rs> and <rs type="place" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#pla-stal" key="St Albans">St Albans</rs>; there is the <rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch">Archbishop of</rs></l>
./transcriptions/m54-9.xml:143:          <l><rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-arch" key="Archbishop of Canterbury">Canterbury</rs> and <rs type="place" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#pla-stpa" key="St Paul's Cathedral">St Pauls</rs>. But the roads lead past London to</l>
