<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title></title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability> <!-- ask SoA for copyright statement --> </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
          <handNote  xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
            <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
          </handNote>
        </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m50</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
        <physDesc>
          <p>M50. Anon. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 9p. Paginated 1-9.</p>
        </physDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in <sic></sic> / <corr></corr> tags, wrapped in a <choice></choice> element.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Where appropriate, spelling and punctuation have been modernised using <orig></orig> / <reg></reg> tags, wrapped in a <choice></choice> element.</p>
        </normalization>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in <rs></rs> tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <div xml:id="m50.1">
        <p>
          <l>1</l>
          <l>ANON.</l>
        </p>
        <p>
          <l><quote source="">"For many centuries <choice>
            <sic>afte</sic>
            <corr>after</corr></choice> Britain became an island"</quote> the</l>
          <l><rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-whar">historian</rs> says ""<quote source="">the untamed forest was king. Its moist</quote></l>
          <l><quote source="">and mossy floor was hidden from Heavens eye by a close drawn</quote></l>
          <l><quote source="">curtain woven of innumerable tree tops."</quote> On those matted</l>
          <l>boughs innumerable birds sang; but their song was only heard</l>
          <l>by a few skin clad hunters in the <choice>
            <sic>lcearings</sic>
            <corr>clearings</corr>
          </choice>. Did the desire</l>
          <l>to sing come to one of those huntsmen because he heard the</l>
          <l>birds sing, and so rested his axe against the tree for a</l>
          <l>moment? But the tree had to be felled; and a hut made</l>
          <l>from its branches before the human voice sang too.</l>
        </p>
        <p><quote source="">
          <l>By a bank as I lay</l>
          <l>Musing myself alone, hey ho!</l>
          <l>A birdes voice</l>
          <l>Did me rejoice,</l>
          <l>Singing before the day</l>
          <l>And me thought in her lay</l>
          <l>She said, winter was past, hey ho!</l>
        </quote></p>
        <p>
          <l>The voice that broke the <choice>
            <sic>sielnce</sic>
            <corr>silence</corr>
          </choice> of the forests was</l>
          <l>the voice of <rs type="person" ref="../resources/annotations.xml#psn-anon">Anon</rs>. Some one heard the song and <choice>
           <sic>re embered</sic>
           <corr>remembered</corr>
          </choice> it</l>
         <l>for it was later <choice>
            <sic>wrteen  </sic>
            <corr>written</corr>
          </choice> down, beautifully on parchment.</l>
          <l>Thus the singer had his audience, but the audience was so</l>
          <l>little interested in his name that he never thought to give</l>
          <l>it. For the audience was itself the singer;   Terly terlow"</l>
          <l>they sand; and "By, by lullay" filling in the pauses,</l>
          <l>helping <add hand="ms" place="above">out</add> with a chorus. Every body shared in the emotion</l>
          <l>of Anons song, and supplied the story. Anon sang because</l>
          <l>spring has come; or winter is gone; because he loves; because</l>
          <l>he is hungry, or lustful; or merry. or because he adores</l>
          <l>some God. Anon is sometimes man; sometimes woman. He is the</l>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="m50.2">
        <p><l>2</l></p>
        <p>
          <l>common voice singing out of doors, He has no house. He <choice>
            <sic>l ves</sic>
            <corr>lives</corr>
          </choice></l>
          <l>a <choice>
            <sic>r ming</sic>
            <corr>roaming</corr>
          </choice> life crossing the fields, mounting the hills,</l>
          <l>lying under the hawthown to listen to the <choice>
            <sic>nightigale</sic>
            <corr>nightingale</corr>
          </choice>.</l>
        </p>
        <p>
          <l>By shutting out a chimney or a factory we can still</l>
          <l>see what Anon saw-- the bird haunted reed whispering fen,</l>
          <l>the down and the green scar never quite <add hand="ms" place="above">not yet</add> healed along which</l>
          <l>he came when he made his journeys. He was a simple singer,</l>
          <l>lifting a song or a story from other peoples lips and <choice>
            <sic>lettig</sic>
            <corr>letting</corr>
          </choice></l>
          <l>the audience join in the chorus. <choice>
            <sic>Somemimes</sic>
            <corr>Sometimes</corr>
          </choice> he made a few lines</l>
          <l>that exactly matched his emotion--</l>
          <!--find a way to render the blank lines -->
          <l> </l>
          <l> </l>
          <l> </l>
          <l> </l>
          <l>but there is no <add place="above">name</add> <choice>
            <sic>mae</sic>
            <corr>name</corr>
          </choice> to that song.</l>
        </p>
        <p>
          <l>Then when the houses had come together in some</l>
          <l><choice>
            <sic>lcearing</sic>
            <corr>clearing</corr>
          </choice> in a ring and roads, often flooded, often deep in</l>
          <l>mud, led from hxxxx the cottage ot the Manor, from the Manor</l>
          <l>to the Church in the middle, along the roads came <choice>
            <sic>minstersl</sic>
            <corr>minstrels</corr>
          </choice></l>
          <l>jugglers, bear leaders, singing their songs at the back door</l>
          <l>to the farm hands and the maid servants in the uncouth</l>
          <l>jargon of their native tongue.</l>
          <quote source="">
            <l>Icham for woing al forwake</l>
            <l>Wery no water in wore</l>
          </quote>
          <l>Up stairs they spoke French. Anons words were as</l>
          <l>uncouth to the master and mistress as to us.    Anon</l>
          <l>singing at <choice>
            <sic>yhe</sic>
            <corr>the</corr>
          </choice> back door was  <choice>
            <sic>despsied</sic>
            <corr>despised</corr>
          </choice>. He had no name;</l>
          <l>he had no place, yet even if they felt contempt for the</l>
          <l><add hand="ms" place="above">singer ?????</add>man who made songs, they tolerated him. Even Kings and Queens</l>
        </p>
      </div>
  </text>
</TEI>
