<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M108 [The Reader: There is a jolt at the points.]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 7p, fol. 3v.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m108</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M108 [The Reader: There is a jolt at the points.]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 7p. Paginated 23-28, with an unpaginated page at end.</p>
            <p>These and successive folders of [The Reader] were contained in two multigrip folders, headed by Virginia Woolf: "Turning the page"; "Transformations" and "Spare sheets of T.P." labels on the spines. They are filed under her Anon, holograph and typescript fragments.</p>
            <p>The fragments grouped in the successive folders under [The reader] may or may not have formed part of Anon. They have been grouped in this fashion based on the evidence of paper and typewriters. The pagination 23-28 is the lowest in the sequence. Internal evidence would indicate that manuscript drafts preceded that of Anon, since Articles, 1938-9 notebook contains a fragment. Some of the versos of this run of material contains fragments of typescripts of Between the Acts and other contemporary works.</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote  xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="2779" lry="3500" xml:id="facs_">
         <graphic url="m108-6.tif" width="2779px" height="3500px"/>
         <zone points="" rendition="TextRegion" xml:id="facs__eSc_dummyblock_">
         </zone>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body><div><pb facs="#facs_" n="" xml:id="img_NaN"/>
            <ab facs="#facs__eSc_dummyblock_">
            </ab></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>