<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M54, 9 of 11. [Anon: The road led to the old graves...]. Typescript fragment, 8 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m54-8</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M54, 9 of 11. [Anon: The road led to the old graves...]. Typescript fragment, 8 fols.</p>
            <p>N.B.: This is one of eleven sub-fragments identified in the Berg Collection's M54. [Anon: The printing press brought the past into existence...]. Typescript fragments, unsigned and undated, 35 fols. I have determined pagination and sequencing based on subject matter. M54 as curated by the Berg Collection is available as part of 'The Digital Anon' and can be found at [LINK].</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-1/945,42,191,166/full/0/default.tif">
          16
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-1/958,188,1662,892/full/0/default.tif">
          The road led to the old graves, to the stones where the
          old pagan English had offered sacrifice. The peasants still
          went that way, in 
            spir ng (spring), summer and winter, by instinct.
          The old Gods 
            stil (still) lay hidden beneath the new.
          Even if they were now nameless, it was to txxxxx do them
          homage, to win crops, husbands, health, that the
          peasants came amxmxmxmxmxmxm in spring summer and
          winter.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-1/911,1104,1830,2124/full/0/default.tif">
          It is the printing press that we owe their
          preservation. "After that I had accomplished and 
            finsihed (finished)
          divers histories"  wrote in 
            41470 (1470) in the preface
          to the , "many noble and divers gentlemen
          of this realm of England came and demanded me many and oft
          times ..... to imprint the history of the said noble king
          and conqueror , and of his knights with the
          history of the  and of the death and ending of
          the said Arthur." The twenty one books of the Morte DArthur
          preserve what lay 
            benea th (beneath), <sup/>
            Ther (there) we tap into the deep reservoir
          of common belief that lay behind <sup> </sup>the peasant and the noble.
          The 
            legnd (legend) was still alive in the nineteenth century.
          "...folks do say" said a peasant at  that on the
          night of the full moon King 
            Arthus (Arthur) and his men ride round
          the hill, and their horses are shod with silver..."
          A silver horseshoe,  says, was found in 
          time at . It is in  pages that we hear the
          voice of anon murmuring in the mind of King and Queen and
          peasant, They remembered how the old King
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-3/976,147,138,143/full/0/default.tif">
          17
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-3/958,262,1744,678/full/0/default.tif">
          and his knights went their ways through the wild woods seek
          ing adventure. <sup>When</sup>  <s>himself</s> doubted. <s>No</s>such <sup>a</sup> man, he
          objected, had ever lived. But the nobles were positive,
          they said that you could see  skull at 
          and the  at  and in "in other places
           sword and many other things.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-3/935,924,1782,1980/full/0/default.tif">
          The book itself represents  scepticism, and the
          nobles faith. It is half fable, half fact. There is ,
          and  and ; there is the 
           and . But the roads lead past London to
          castles where Knights lie in prison; down the roads ride
          Queens on white mules;  turns suddenly to
          stone; and a hand rises from a lake holding .
          In the 
            canfdour (candour) with 
            wh h (which) it is told, it is a childs story.
          But <s>the</s> <sup>the</sup> child has lived for centuries. It has not our pers
          spective. The inventories, the catalogues are 
            mad (made) with
          a childs 
            partciularity (particularity). The clear eye sees definitely and
          without exaggeration. Beauty is in the thing itself, not i
          in the writers manipulation. So he went in and searched
          
            chamber from chamber to chamber, and found his bed, but she
            was not there; then Balin lookedinto a fxmx little garden
            and under a laurel tree he saw her lie upon a quilt of
            green samite and a 
              kmight (knight) with her, and under their heads
            grass and herbs."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-3/975,2864,1694,588/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>But</sup> It is not a childs world; it is a world before self
          consciousness has raised 
            i s (its) mirror. The men and women are
          
            angualr (angular), gigantic; freed from 
            somthing (something) impure; yet sin
          tarnished, 
            acqauinted (acquainted) with sorrow, corrupt, in the midst of
          this fresh landscape, remembering,
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-5/903,105,164,153/full/0/default.tif">
          i8 (18)
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-5/910,238,1696,562/full/0/default.tif">
          We lose our bearings following these Knights and ladies;
          to live in 
            t is (this) 
            prehistroic (prehistoric) land we must 
            sehd (shed) many habits
          of 
            thoght (thought); but after all it is not an unreal world;
          a fabricated world; it still exists in us, deep sunk,
          savage, primitive; m remembered.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-5/884,778,1784,1018/full/0/default.tif">
          Of the writer, nothing is 
            knonw (known). He is not <sup>[illeg.] emerged</sup>
          
            disnctin c (distinct) from 
            hsi  ook (his book). It is still the anonymous voice
          speaking 
            anonysmously (anonymously) generally 
            hat (that) the 
            lsiener (listener) already
          
            hald (half) knows, or 
            rmemebers (remembers). The 
            lsiener (listener) hears the voice
          partly in himself; as it comes from the man at the back
          door who has been travelling in 
            trange (strange) parts 
            acrsoos (across) the
          marsh across the flood to 
            r mind (remind) the 
            peasnt (peasant) and the noble
          of the world that was before them. And still the dream
          lingered; for the 
            peasnts (peasants)
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-5/876,1824,1812,1490/full/0/default.tif">
          In the great house and the cottage this half articulate
          voice murmured of old gods 
            a d (and) kings and 
            inihgts (knights)
          The well and the tree were still haunted. King Arthur
          the 
            foreste s (foresters) said in the thirteenth 
            cnetury (century),    ;;;"about
          
            noon or 
              midngiht (midnight) when the moon is 
              sufulland (full and) shining
            [we?] often see an array of hunters with dogs and sound of
            horns who 
              ins anser (answer) to the 
              enwuirers (enquirers) says
            
              yhat (that) they are of the 
              hosuehold (household) and fellowship of
          
          King 
            Art ur (Arthur)." Along the roads from town to town
          from house to 
            ouse (house), came the 
            minstresl (minstrels) the jugglers and
          the impudent bardes. 
            whil (While) for those who could read it,
          Caxtons book 
            tol (told) the old stories set out in print.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          then 
            late (later) the instinct to enact, to impersonate
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-7/825,80,175,154/full/0/default.tif">
          19
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-7/847,196,1790,1596/full/0/default.tif">
          
            hat () they believed imagined came into existence.
          Even the King and Queen shared the it, and must have
          their actors or 
            minstersl (minstrels) to 
            vie (give) <sup>body</sup> tongue to this
          hidden 
            insticnt (instinct) <sup>[illeg.]</sup>. The 
            acror (actor) was 
            despied (despised);
          did he not make use of his body? and did he not,
          feeling himself an 
            otcast (outcast), use the 
            outiders (outsiders) privilege of
          
            irrepsoneible (irresponsible) mockery? But the Kings and Queens tolerated
          him, as 
            to rate (tolerate) those who say what we are too proud
          to admit. Even the church men <s>had to a  re</s> <sup>aware</sup> that the 
            Gids (Gods)
          that <s>he worshipped 
            wre (were) not theirs</s> had to 
            yeild (yield) to him;
          or <s>to make use of his gift to</s> If they could they constrained
          the 
            c ors (actors) and the 
            da cers (dancers) 
            t (to) put off their 
            l evea (leaves) 
            na d (and) bells
          and dress themselves as the sacred figures in a miracle play.
          But the churchmen did their best to 
            prvent (prevent) them.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-8/1742,3215,138,169/full/0/default.tif">
          7
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-8/131,1640,1787,1594/full/0/default.tif">
          The printing press brought the past into existence.
          It <sup>also</sup> brought into existence, seen 
            agoanst (against) the back
          
            rgound (ground) of the past. And it brough by degrees the 
            indivual (individual)
          into existence--the <s>
            indi idual (individual) who looking back sees himself</s> <sup>the man who is separate from his book.</sup>
          <s>against the background</s>. The individual emerges
          at last. <sup>He is a chronicler and the [illeg.]</sup>His name is 
            ; it is also 
            .
          Harrison tells us that he has books; and a mastiff;
          and digs 
            i (in) the ground for Roman coins. He tells us that he
          has 
            nev (never) been more than forty miles from  in .
          The individual, <s>still much 
            sumplified (simplified)</s>, but sxxxxx no longer
          nameless, 
            emrges (emerges). He is losing his ambiguity.
          the present is becoming visible. Harrison sees the present
          moment (15     ) against the settled orderly past.
          The present looks 
            degenrate (degenerate), raw, against that past.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-9/828,68,186,161/full/0/default.tif">
          20
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-9/804,232,1816,2004/full/0/default.tif">
          It was at half past two in 
            th (the) afternoon that the
          trumpets 
            dounded (sounded) and the flag flew over the Theatre.
          The playhouse was open to the sky. A penny or twopence was
          the price of a seat. There was no scenery; but the walls
          were painted; and the actors were richly dressed, according
          to one spectator in the cast off robes of the nobles, sold
          by their servants. What other amusement 
            as (was) there in the
          afternoon, for the gentlement of the court, txxx of the Inns
          of Court, for the numbers of captains and soldiers about
          London? Only the amusements that Latimer deplored;
          carding, dicing, gaming, following of xmxmxmxmxmx
          harlots and drinking. The rivxmxmxmxmx audience came from
          the 
            drowded (crowded) festering little streets txxxx round 
          where the buried smelt so strong. The river was crowded with
          wherries ferrying them across: The riverside people 
            depnded (depended)
          upon their fares. The flag flew; the trumpets 
            dsounded (sounded); and
          
            audince (audience) crowded into the open playhouse, clustered round the
          stage; and heard:
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-9/962,2216,1364,346/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Brother Cosroe, I find myself aggrieved,
            Yet insufficient 
              yto (to) express the same;
            For it requires a great and thundering speech
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-9/768,2544,1912,870/full/0/default.tif">
          At last the voice speaks from the actual body of one man.
          xmxmxmxmxm.And the 
            wolrd (world) became visible. Egypt, Libya;
          Persia; Greece. It unrolled itself <sup>time</sup>; and the armies of 
            gr at (great)
          Kings; and plains; and palaces. There is no abstraction any
          longer. All is visible tangible, audible. Txmxmxmxmxm
          
            ords (Words) seem to swell and stretch and tumble over 
            themslves (themselves)
          in the effort to give body to this vast universe.
          They can scarcely contain all they would bring forward.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-11/889,84,172,147/full/0/default.tif">
          21
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-11/887,214,1403,434/full/0/default.tif">
          
            The 
              sprung (spring) is hindered by your smothering host,
            For neither rain can fall upon the earth,
            Nor sun reflex his virtuous beams thereon,
            The ground is mantled with such multitudes.
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-11/851,648,1863,770/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Abrtactions (Abstractions) withdraw themselves. Axmxmxxx The Kings and
          Emperors stride forth, palpable, coloured, strident. The ae
          They are hewn, mob- monstrous, brilliantly painted;
          but they movel they speak. They emerge like great moths,
          
            stillcreased (still creased) and damp, shaking their wings in splendid
          
            aburd (absurd) hyperboles and raptures and The great names crash
          like cymbals
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-11/911,1406,1495,442/full/0/default.tif">
          
            tell him, xmxmxx thy Lord the Turkish Emperor,
            
              Dre d (Dread) Lord of Afric, 
              Eruope (Europe) and Asia,
            Great king and 
              conqueor (conqueror) of 
              Greacia (Graecia),
            The ocean, Terrene, and the coal-black sea....
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-11/909,1852,1623,342/full/0/default.tif">
          It is bombast, <s>it is 
            pagenatry (pageantry)</s>; it is hyperbole. And yet
          <s>
            pusis ant (puissant)</s>, Words 
            mout (mount); pile on top of each 
            ther (other);
          surpass common sense; 
            clah (clash) and rebound:
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-11/889,2158,1631,470/full/0/default.tif">
          
            
              W se (Whose) eyes are brighter than the lamps of 
              Haevan (Heaven),
            And speech more 
              pl sant (pleasant) than sweet harmony!
            that with thy looks canst 
              clclear (clear) the 
              datkemed (darkened) sky,
            And calm the rage of thundering Jupiter...
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-11/857,2594,1671,662/full/0/default.tif">
          He is beyond the provinces of plain 
            pseech (speech),
          revelling in some untouched garden of untouched blooms;
          picking 
            plaucking (plucking) words, and strewing them.
          There is no shadow; all is gold and 
            urple (purple).
          Yet in the very pitch and height of this extravagance,
          xmxmxmxmx he veers,
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-11/1111,3248,859,178/full/0/default.tif">
          
            So poets say my lord.
          
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-13/949,97,122,133/full/0/default.tif">
          22
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-13/935,206,1000,127/full/0/default.tif">
          
            
              An (And) tis a pretty toy to be a poet..
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-13/947,314,1375,238/full/0/default.tif">
          So distended with rapture, the tune changes
          effectively.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-13/913,1302,1671,666/full/0/default.tif">
          Could he stop, he would cutdeeper. But there is no pause;
          no shadow. The 
            pagenat (pageant) <sup>[illeg.]</sup>. The horses neigh.
          Kings and 
            Empeors (Emperors) emerge. Battles are fought. Blood flows.
          And all over this 
            multitidionous (multitudinous) splendour broods 
            agedy (tragedy)
          xmxmxmmxmxmxxx We forbode. We behold the thing as <sup>We [illeg.] there</sup>
          spectacle. There is the end to come. Meanwhile, let us 
            boas (boast)
          and triumph.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-13/919,1302,1695,662/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Our souls, whose faculties can comprehend
            The wondrous architecture of the world,
            And measure very wandering planets course
            Still climbing after 
              knowlede (knowledge) 
              infinute (infinite),
            And always moving as the restless 
              spe eres (spheres),
            Well us to wear ourselves, and never rest...
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-13/933,1950,1707,566/full/0/default.tif">
          That is the 
            meldy (melody) the marching song of this brave
          
            septacle (spectacle). And yet, as if the poet slipped the noose of his
          audiences, 
            releved (relieved) himself of its pressure for one moment,
          we hear:
          amid the 
            so nding (sounding) brass:
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-13/923,2500,1779,946/full/0/default.tif">
          
            What is 
              beautym (beauty,) saith my sufferings, then?
            If all the pens that ever poets held
            Had fed the 
              feelingsx (feelings) of their masters' thoughts,
          
          .....
          
            If all these had made one poems 
              riod (period),
            And all combined in 
              b auty's (beauty's) worthiness,
            Yet should there hover in their 
              estless (restless) heads
            one thought, one wxxxxxxx grace, one wonder, at the least,
          
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-15/868,91,144,133/full/0/default.tif">
          23
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-15/898,221,1080,105/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Which into <s>words no virtue can digest</s>
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-9/m54-9-15/802,308,1848,1442/full/0/default.tif">
          It is a break; <sup>a [illeg.]</sup> out of keeping; <s>to be recalled at once</s>
          a sign that the dramatist is separate from the 
            anony ous (anonymous) play
          maker; There is no little language to put on Kings lips;
          so that he cannot as yet 
            amalgamante (amalgamate) naturally
          the thought and the action. The audience, the 
            shopr keeprs (shopkeepers)
          apprentices 
            insoored (ensured) not 
            relfection (reflection) <sup>blood [illeg.]</sup>, but action,
          
            movemnt (movement). The play is still partly the work of the audience;
          of the undifferentiated gluttonous word greedy mass.
          It is inspired by the common voice, demanding great names,
          simple 
            outl nes (outlines); clamour and 
            virtory (victory) and death; not the 
            singe (single)
          subtlety of one soul. <s>
            Refelction (Reflection) breaks off from</s>
          <s>
            ction (action); there is no 
            harml sing ([harmonising? harming?]) common speech.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>