<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M54, 4 of 11. [Anon: Anon has emerged sufficiently from the forests...]. Typescript fragment, 2 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m54-4</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M54, 4 of 11. [Anon has emerged sufficiently from the forests...]. Typescript fragment, 2 fols.</p>
            <p>N.B.: This is one of eleven sub-fragments identified the Berg Collection's M54. [Anon: The printing press brought the past into existence...]. Typescript fragments, unsigned and undated, 35 fols. I have determined pagination and sequencing based on subject matter. M54 as curated by the Berg Collection is available as part of 'The Digital Anon' and can be found at [LINK].</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-4/m54-4-1/900,112,162,150/full/0/default.tif">
          9
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-4/m54-4-1/888,232,1788,3132/full/0/default.tif">
           has emerged 
            sufficiently (suffievcntly) from the forests and the<br/>
          floods to let us see a rough outline of a human shape.<br/>
          He has a dog and a garden. He has books; and he digs in<br/>
          the earth. His name is of no great moment. It may be<br/>
          Harrison; or it may be . There is very little to dis 
            distinguish (dis)<br/>
          
            distinguish (tingusih) one from the other. He has no 
            expression (exr ssion) on his 
            face (fae)<br/>
          He conveys to us chiefly what his eye sees, what his body<br/>
          feels. He sees 
            England (ngland) very clearly. He sees<br/>
          its 
            emptiness (emptines); ; he conveys the scarcity of people; the<br/>
          
            predominance (predominace) of individuals. The  is the dominant<br/>
          
            figure (fogure). He can count her 
            possessions (posses ons)-- a few ships; a few<br/>
          great 
            houses (hous s). He watches her 
            progresses (progeresses). She is 
            parliament (parliemtn),<br/>
          press, society, law and order. But the man who sees this<br/>
          the individual, is still cumbered and stiff. Writing is<br/>
          still an art that requires great ceremony. What you make<br/>
          with the pen is separate from what you say with the tongue.<br/>
          Only a few years back words were written 
            elaborately (elbaorately) in<br/>
          lustrous ink upon valuable parchment; and the leaves,<br/>
          bound together, were chained to the lectern and read,<br/>
          by a few, in great physical discomfort,<br/>
          on hard 
            benches (neches) in the cold. Even now, when words are printed,<br/>
          the great public is not the reader, or the paymaster.<br/>
          Written words must please a single man in the first place,<br/>
          must find its way into some noble room, where the nobles<br/>
          and the gentry, have 
            leisure (lisure) after hunting, after<br/>
          seeing their estates, and 
            controlling (contrlling) their servants,<br/>
          to to pick up a book and read its history or sing its song.<br/>
          For Words must tell stories; or they must sound to<br/>
          the ear. For the nobles had their music; they played tunes
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-4/m54-4-3/919,112,173,146/full/0/default.tif">
          10
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-4/m54-4-3/905,228,1401,142/full/0/default.tif">
          tunes to the words that the writers wrote.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-4/m54-4-3/831,352,1861,2938/full/0/default.tif">
          It is the printing press 
            that (th t) disturbs this company.<br/>
          It is the printing press that makes the writer a 
            many (nany) headed<br/>
          many limbed. a mongrel with so many different 
            parents (pearants)<br/>
          that it requires a 
            whole (hole) army of learned men, and a perpetual<br/>
          provision of fine tasters to keep any order or distinction<br/>
          
            between (etween) the different members. The presses of , <br/>
          , sucking in copy, and casting out legible books<br/>
          that 
            any one (nany one) could read was not a nice 
            [feeder?] (fedder). Anything<br/>
          that could be written could be printed. What Any morality,<br/>
          any record, whatever men wished 
            recorded (recored), it would deliver<br/>
          as a book. Unlike the 
            painter (pa nter) or the musician the writer<br/>
          after the birth of the printing press is exposed to<br/>
          innumerable 
            inappropriate (inappropirate) and 
            irrelevant (irelveant) 
            solcitations (s licitaions).<br/>
          Why not write the 
            history (hist) of your parish? Or the life of a<br/>
          Roman emperor? Why not take part in the 
            government (governement) of your<br/>
          country? Why not advise the soul of its 
            perils (erils)? Why not become<br/>
          
            pamphleteer (pampheleteer) 
            historian (histroain) moralist, or playwright? The Press is<br/>
          read to accept anything. And as the 
            public (oublic) becomes less<br/>
          
            servile (serivile), less martial less concerned to keep out the cold<br/>
          and fight the enemy, as glass is fitted into windows<br/>
          and pillows replace logs, the public adds its own invitation<br/>
          to the writer. It is an inquisitive 
            active (acti e) minded public;<br/>
          it soon dissipates and takes hold of . It makes him<br/>
          into an innumerable 
            company (comany) of familiar 
            spirits (sprits), one<br/>
          
            preaching (pr aching) another delighting, 
            another instructing (anotherinstructing). Only a few<br/>
          still persist into making words into works of art.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>