<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M54, 5 of 11. [Anon: a more crowded, a more divided audience...]. Typescript fragment, 3 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m54-5</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M54, 5 of 11. [a more crowded, a more divided audience...]. Typescript fragment, 3 fols.</p>
            <p>N.B.: This is one of eleven sub-fragments identified the Berg Collection's M54. [Anon: The printing press brought the past into existence...]. Typescript fragments, unsigned and undated, 35 fols. I have determined pagination and sequencing based on subject matter. M54 as curated by the Berg Collection is available as part of 'The Digital Anon' and can be found at [LINK].</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-1/858,120,171,147/full/0/default.tif">
          12
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-1/875,238,1793,1666/full/0/default.tif">
          a more crowded, a more divided audience, to a
          public which desires 
            accordind (according) to its education, its poverty,
          
            it (its) wealth, 
            n w (now) history, now instruction, now poetry itself,
          and now whatever will make them forget the drab, the
          <s>mudcoloured</s>, the dismal in their own lives. As the book
          becomes more and more spun over with these influences,
          the thing that the writer has to say becomes increasingly cumbered. It is only to be discovered in a flash of
          recognition Thus some say they that their beards
          bristle when they come up on it; others that a thrill
          runs down the nerves of the thigh. To disengage the song
          from its encumbrances becomes as time 
            gos (goes) on a task for
          the critic-- that specially equipped taster and trier
          who was not yet in existence <s>in print</s> when  <sup>[illeg.]</sup> emerged
          weed 
            hunf (hung) 
            peral (pearl) 
            enc  sted (encrusted) from the depths of silence.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-1/829,1894,1797,1282/full/0/default.tif">
          
            "For why, a Gods' name, may not we, as else the
            Greekes, have the kingdome of our owne 
              langauge (language), and measure
            our accents by the sound, reserving the quantity to the verse
            Why in Gods name may not we have the kingdom of our own
          
          
            lanague (language)--- thus he proves himself word 
            cosncious (), an
          artist, aware of his 
            meidum (medium), aware that words are not
          paint, nor music; 
            nbut (but) have their possibilities, their
          
            mlimitations (limitations). To be thus aware, the writer must
          have a past behind him; as the 
            hisrian (historian) to see the present,
          must set it against an earlier age. To , the golden
          age was Cahu . Dan Chaucer, well of English
          un filed... "that the infusion sweete
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-3/823,106,185,138/full/0/default.tif">
          13
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-3/727,208,1861,2630/full/0/default.tif">
          Of thine owne spirit which doth in me survive
          He looks back to 
            ; he descends from 
            Cahucer (Chaucer).
          It was Chaucer that gave him the <s>
            meausre (measure)</s> <sup>
              stabdard (standard)</sup> by which to
          measure 
            hiw (his) own words. <sup>But</sup> Where the modern writer 
            attackes (attacks) the
          actual works of some 
            on (one) of the generation that is just
          gone, making that book the kicking off point <sup>starting point</sup> in another
          direction,  revolt was against no 
            particualr (particular) writer
          ---had not years of silence intervened? <sup>who was there in English save ?</sup>--- but against the
          
            langauge (language) itself, its decay, since Chaucer, its corruption.
          It was partly as an antidote to his own facility; <s>that he</s>
          <s>needed him</s>. He found the e 
            ourge (urge) which the self critical
          writer so often applies to his own disease in the old English
          words that were now obsolete. A glossary was added to the
           to explain them. But partly he used the
          crabbed, English of the past not as we in our day
          seek to bring back the sharpness which much use has worn
          smooth; but to restrain what was to come. He was, as we <sup>are not</sup>
          <s>cannot be</s>, aware of the future. Everywhere, in 
            ballds (ballads),
          songs, talk in the street, at the tavern, at the back
          door, he heard 
            wit (with) his acute ear for sound
          thxx something rising, moving, 
            buursting (bursting) up
          from 
            beanth (beneath) <sup>[illeg.]</sup> the old exact words; the crabbed but precise
          language of Chaucer. Was it not <sup>[illeg.]</sup> to restrain that 
            insur ction (insurrection)
          
            thzthe (that he) looked back to the 
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-3/669,2854,1897,530/full/0/default.tif">
          Yet what comparison is possible between the poetry of
           and the poetry of ? The one clear, sharp,
          
            me erry (merry); definite; 
            strifding (striding) straight on. the other sen
          
            sisensuous (sensuous), sinuous, dallying, winding in out of the glooms
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-5/915,93,133,131/full/0/default.tif">
          14
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-5/853,220,1761,2214/full/0/default.tif">
          of 
            th (the) forest glades. The one direct, 
            abo t (about) this real
          man, this real woman, here and now; 
            th (the) other making qua
          qualities 
            og (of) 
            noblenees (nobleness) of baseness in to 
            symblic (symbolic) Knights,
          or 
            dawrfs (dwarfs); and sending this 
            visionay (visionary) company, 
            thse (these)
          ladies and demons, these Squires and 
            domerdaries (dromedaries),
          through time which is neither past 
            npr (nor) present,
          through lands which are neither hxxxx known or 
            unkwon (unknown). Like
          the figures in dreams they are distorted; 
            y tlike (like) dreams
          very vivid, now close, now 
            dfading (fading) away. Now,
          like the 
            fgures (figures) in some great fresco, they cxmxmxmxmx
          are <s>composed</s> <sup>grouped</sup>, with the flowers 
            grwoing (growing) at their feet, and
          behind them marble pillars, or trees with bright birds
          and <sup>with</sup> the libbard and the lion couchant or romaning.
          The monotony of the metre, flinging its
          curve of sound <sup>[</sup>like a wave that always falls<sup>]</sup> <sup>there</sup> fills and
          falls, like a wave, is beneath them. There is no tension;
          no direction. but always movement, <s>on and on</s> and bright
          
            visons (visions), <sup>[</sup>and folded in this 
            inactation (incantation) we 
            drwise (drowse) and
          sleep; but again, wake so such is the and we sleep,
          <sup>so that we drowse yet</sup> yet a start awake.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-5/m54-5-5/849,2390,1785,934/full/0/default.tif">
          English poetry, then, might have continued to be a v
          book read aloud; a pageant; a recollection; 
            somet ing (something) half
          seen half heard, by the leisured, listening in 
            th (the) great
          room to some one reading aloud. Onxmxmxmxmxmxm
          But there was the other voice.         - the voice of ;
          xmxmxmxmxmx not as we hear it, reading those first
          
            carbbed (crabbed) lyrics in the beginning 
            ot (of) the anthology; but the
          voice that  heard; loud; rough; brutal.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>