<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M111, set 3 of 3 [The Reader: Anonymity was a great possession]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections. 6 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m111-3</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M111 [The Reader]. Set 3 of 3. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections. 6 fols.</p>
            <p>Fragments paginated 29, 31, 31, 3L [i.e. 31]</p>
            <p>Two loose pages paginated 32 and 33, but not consecutive with the rest, on verso p. 32 is p. 185 of <hi rend="italic">Between the Acts</hi> <!-- find out which draft --></p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-1/860,74,178,162/full/0/default.tif">
          29
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-1/855,208,1818,1876/full/0/default.tif">
          Anonymity was a great possession. It gave the early writing
          an impersonality, a generality. It gave us the 
            ballds (ballads);
          it gave us the songs. It allowed us to know 
            notning (nothing) of the
          writer; and so to concentrate upon his song.  had
          great 
            privilges (privileges). He was not responsible. He was not self
          conscious. He is not self conscious. He can borrow. He can
          repeat. He can say what every one feels. No 
            ne (one) tries to
          stamp his own name, to 
            disover (discover) his own 
            expereince (experience), in his
          work. He keeps at a distance from the present moment.
          Anon the lyric poet repeats over and over again
          that flowers fade; that death is the 
            ned (end). He is 
            nver (never) tired
          of celebrating red roses and white breasts. The anonymous
          playwright has like the singer this 
            namless (nameless) vitality,
          something drawn from the crowd in the penny seats and not yet
          dead in ourselves. We can still become anonymous and forget
          something that we have learnt when we read the plays to which
          no one has troubled to set a name.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-1/827,2076,1794,1252/full/0/default.tif"> 
          But at 
            asome (some) point there comes a break when anonymity
          withdraws. Does it come when the playwright has absorbed
          the 
            contrbution (contribution) of the audience; and can return to them
          their own general life in <sup>
            indivisualised (individualised)</sup> single and separate figures?
          xmxmxmxmxmmmxxmxmxmx <sup>the complete [figure?] the , the </sup> There comes a 
            mpoint (point) when the
          audience is no longer master of the 
            palaywright (playwright). Yet he is
          not separate from them. A common life still unites them;
          but there are moments of 
            seapaeation (separation). Now we say, he is
          
            spaeking (speaking) our own 
            thoghts (thoughts). Now thxmxmxmxmxmxmxxxx he is
          our 
            slves (). But <sup>then</sup> this sense of 
            indivi uality (individuality) comes fitfully.
          The beauty which is so <s>frequent and</s> 
            astoinshingly (astonishingly)
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-3/893,66,145,166/full/0/default.tif">
          31
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-3/743,192,1929,2788/full/0/default.tif">
          The great house that  deplored becomes
          solid and entire in the pages of Lady s
          diary. From childhood she was tenacious of her hereditary
          rights--her father had the right to carry the Kings
          sword "and so it lineally 
            descnded (descended) to me.<sup>/</sup> All her youth
          she fought, against kinsmen, husband and the king himself
          for her lxmxmxx right to inherit 
            he (her) lands in .
          "... I would 
            bever (never) part from 
            estmoreland (Westmoreland) while I lived
          upon any condition whatsoever" she told him. When the
          lands and the five castles were hers, she instantly began
          rebuilding; Not only the land was hers, but
          diamond buttons, rubies, fur cloaks. She As if to solidify
          
            he (her) possessions she wrote out inventories of them. Family
          love is in part the 
            drire ([desire? drive?]) to hand on her 
            proprty (property). She sends
          for her 
            gran (grand) children in order that they may taste the
          delight of possession and so refresh her own satisfaction.
          <sup>[</sup>The living body is robed 
            slendidly (splendidly) in taffetas and satins.
          the dead body is 
            seale (sealed) in lead to preserve it from decay.<sup>]</sup>
          The sense of the body permeates her pages. All 
            movemnts (movements)
          become spectacular. Crowds attend her.
          Six bay horses 
            darg (drag) the 
            coah (coach). The 
            coah (coach) is lined with 
            grreen (green)
          cloth, and laced with green and black silk lace. She is
          for ever asserting 
            he (her) 
            idnetity (identity). 
            he (She) has her initials carved
          even over farm hose walls. This is her property; this land
          is hers 
            b (by) right. Certain flesh and blood--
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-5/915,100,193,202/full/0/default.tif">
          31
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-5/1091,186,413,134/full/0/default.tif">
          xmxmxRmxmxmx.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-5/978,300,1562,228/full/0/default.tif">
          Some speculations on the life and person of the
          Reader.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-5/859,488,1794,2836/full/0/default.tif">
          We can suppose that the reading public was brought into
          existence by two causesl when the playhouse was shut down in
                 ; and, less 
            definietly (defintely), when the play outgrew the
          theatre--when, that is, it could only be fully realised
          if read. In the great age of Elizabethan literature
          the reading public must have been<sup>was</sup> a small one <sup>,</sup> <s>and</s>
          composed mainly of scholars and aristocrats. The lack of
          general common reading is proven by the long pause,
          between  death and the eighteenth century,
          when the plays of 
            Shakepare (Shakespeare) hung suspended,
          unrealised. They had to wait until the printed book was
          held in many hands, read by many eyes <s>in the private room</s>
          before they received the other life, the detailed the
          
            pa tciaulr (particular) life that the reader confers Again the small
          ness of the reading public and its special quality accounts
          for the scarcity of Elizabethan criticism, and the general
          nature of what criticism there is. It is written by writers
          for writers. Both  in his 
          and  in  are concerned with
          the theory of writing; not with 
            partciular (particular) instances.
          They are <sup>not</sup> conscious of any curiosity on the art of the
          general public. The reading public is not yet asking
          for explanations, for instructions. The general public
          never read the play. They had to draw in the play
          as they sat or stood at 
            t e (the) playhouse, through their
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-7/784,32,190,182/full/0/default.tif">
          3L (31)
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-7/756,176,1788,796/full/0/default.tif">
          venerable institutions were being 
            critisiced (criticised). But the public
          at the  and the  could not feel as the public in the
          
            i9th (19th) 
            cent ry (century) felt when  was acted that old humbugs
          were being shown up; and the rottenness of society.
          After all, when country squires must call in  to
          express their meaning, prose was not yet serviceable;
          the critical spirit had no proper tool.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-7/680,972,1492,460/full/0/default.tif">
          And in fact the dramatists were not [depicting?]
          society. They were showing men &amp; women
          themselves <s>they were</s>
          the <s>gulf silence</s>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-7/360,1432,2372,2020/full/0/default.tif">
          <s>So</s> Anonymity thus lay over the 
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-9/888,32,188,244/full/0/default.tif">
          32
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-9/840,252,1772,1140/full/0/default.tif">
          But if we cease to consider the plays 
            separetly (separately), but
          
            scra, ble (scramble) them together as one common attempt; 
          then we are able to make them serve as sketches for one 
          masterpiece. And the darkness in which these plays
          lie helps the endeavour to 
            conveive (conceive) of that 
          many nameless 
            worjers (workers) ; and many private people
          were pressing their weight were discharging their
          emotion into that vast cauldron of seething matter which 
          at last  struck out into his plays.
        </p> 
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/894,114,194,150/full/0/default.tif">
          185
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/848,244,1692,260/full/0/default.tif">
          the horse had a green tail… What had happened 
            tp (to) her?
          When she looked out again, the flowers had vanished.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/804,476,1868,740/full/0/default.tif">
           flicked on the reading lamp. The circle of
          readers was lit up. There in that hollow of the sun baked 
          field were congregated the grass hopper, the ant, and the
          beetle, rolling pebbles of baked earth through the glistening
          stubble. In that rosy corner of the sun baked field,
          Bartholomew,  and , polished and nibbled, and broke off crumbs,
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/800,1240,1868,228/full/0/default.tif">
          "A gentleman at  has seen a  in his
          garden" Bartholomew announced.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/816,1448,1868,228/full/0/default.tif">
          The butterfly that looks 
              life (like) a leaf? Lucy queried.
          looking up from her letter.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/824,1672,1860,124/full/0/default.tif">
          The newspaper dropped.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/828,1776,1860,124/full/0/default.tif">
          "Done?" said Giles taking it from his fathers hand.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/820,1888,1892,1084/full/0/default.tif">
          The old man relinquished his paper. He basked,
          <s>silently</s>, in the mixed light; one hand, caressing the dog,
          xixlxcx rippled folds of skin towards the collar.
          The clock ticked; the house gave little cracks as if it
          were very brittle, very dry.  hand on the window sill
          suddenly felt cold. Shadow had obliterated the garden.
          Roses had 
            withdarwn (withdrawn) fxxm <sup>for</sup> the night.	Mrs Swithin,
          folding her letter, 
            l ant (leant) towards  and said; "I looked
          in and saw the babies; so happy; with the paper flowers on
          their cots.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-10/840,2956,1844,316/full/0/default.tif">
          Giles looked up from his newspaper; Isa became a
          mother again, and also a wife.
        </p>
     </div>
     <div xmlns="">
      <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-11/916,58,190,174/full/0/default.tif">
        33
      </p>
      <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-11/996,188,1274,146/full/0/default.tif">
        In every 
          Elizabethna (Elizabethan) play sunk beyond recall.
      </p>
      <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-11/916,316,1572,212/full/0/default.tif">
        If xmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxm
        somxmxmxmxmxmxmxmx
      </p>
      <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-11/824,544,1892,2420/full/0/default.tif">
        The <s>life</s> The reader then is born sometime in
        the 
          siteenth (sixteenth) century. But he is xmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxm
        but his 
          p wer (power) of influencing the playwright is very weak
        in the early days. The 
          twentiteh (twentieth) century reader
        that is to say, 
          instinctivly (instinctively) tries to adapt himself
        to unfamiliar conditions in reading the earlier plays.
        He tries to supply the trumpets and the flags; the citizens
        and the apprentices. He 
          substanitates (substantiates) the <s>rather</s> shadowy
        emotion that is all he can get in the plays with a dip into
        , with a dip into . He labours to supply
        the sunk parts of the play;  <s>he labours</s> to revive
        the vanished cooperation between the playwright and the
        audience. And he is perpetually rebuffed. He cannot
        read the play into 
          comlete (complete) being. He is therefore apt
        to become not a reader but a student, a careful
        collector of scattered bones. Reading is an imperfect
        way of bringing the early plays into existence. It is only
        fitfully that the readers faculty comes into play.
        When the dramatist becomes 
          consc ous (conscious) of the play as a work
        of art; when he is able to unite the play by something
        in himself-- his 
          personal ty (personality), his style, his conception
        it is then that he brings the reader into existence.
      </p>
      <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-3/m111-3-11/868,2948,1828,340/full/0/default.tif">
        The life history of the reader from Elizabethan
        times to our own is full of obscurity. At some point his
        ear must have been much more acute than it is now; his sight
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>