<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-1/909,104,243,252/full/0/default.tif">
          1<br/>
          ANON.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-1/829,368,1859,1108/full/0/default.tif">
          "For many centuries after (afte) Britain became an island" the<br/>
           says "#"the untamed forest was king. Its moist<br/>
          and mossy floor was hidden from Heavens eye by a close drawn<br/>
          curtain woven of innumerable tree tops." On those matted<br/>
          boughs innumerable birds sang; but their song was only heard<br/>
          by a few skin clad hunters in the clearings (lcearings). Did the desire<br/>
          to sing come to one of those huntsmen because he heard the<br/>
          birds sing, and so rested his axe against the tree for a<br/>
          moment? But the tree had to be felled; and a hut made<br/>
          from its branches before the human voice sang too.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-1/1059,1450,1003,468/full/0/default.tif">
          
            By a bank as I lay<br/>
            Musing myself alone, hey ho!<br/>
            A birdes voice<br/>
            Did me rejoice,<br/>
            Singing before the day<br/>
            And me thought in her lay<br/>
            She said, winter was past, hey ho!
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-1/687,1904,2015,1424/full/0/default.tif">
          The voice that broke the silence (sielnce) of the forests was<br/>
          the voice of . Some one heard the song and remembered (re embered) it<br/>
         for it was later written (wrteen) down, beautifully on parchment.<br/>
          Thus the singer had his audience, but the audience was so<br/>
          little interested in his name that he never thought to give<br/>
          it. <s>For</s> <sup>T</sup><s>t</s>he audience was itself the singer; Terly terlow"<br/>
          they sand; and "By, by lullay" filling in the pauses,<br/>
          helping <sup>out</sup> with a chorus. Every body shared in the emotion<br/>
          of Anons song, and supplied the story. Anon sang because<br/>
          spring has come; or winter is gone; because he loves; because<br/>
          he is hungry, or lustful; or merry. or because he adores<br/>
          some God. Anon is sometimes man; sometimes woman. He is the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-3/851,118,152,170/full/0/default.tif">
          2
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          common voice singing out of doors, He has no house. He lives (l ves)<br/>
          a roaming (r ming) life crossing the fields, mounting the hills,<br/>
          lying under the hawthown to listen to the nightingale (nightigale).
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-3/841,248,1851,1116/full/0/default.tif">
          By shutting out a chimney or a factory we can still<br/>
          see what  saw-- the bird haunted reed whispering fen,<br/>
          the down and the green scar<s>e</s> never quite <sup>not yet</sup> healed along which<br/>
          he came when he made his journeys. He was a simple singer,<br/>
          lifting a song or a story from other peoples lips and letting (lettig)<br/>
          the audience join in the chorus. Sometimes (Somemimes) he made a few lines<br/>
          that exactly matched his emotion--
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-3/851,1616,1251,196/full/0/default.tif">
          
           <br/>
           <br/>
           <br/>
           
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-3/851,1616,1251,196/full/0/default.tif">
          but there is no <sup>name</sup> name (mae) to that song.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-3/783,1830,1891,760/full/0/default.tif">
          Then when the houses had come together in some<br/>
          clearing (lcearing) in a ring and roads, often flooded, often deep in<br/>
          mud, led from hxxxx the cottage to the Manor, from the Manor<br/>
          to the Church in the middle, along the roads came minstrels (minstersl) <sup>came</sup><br/>
          jugglers, bear leaders, singing their songs at the back door<br/>
          to the farm hands and the maid servants in the uncouth<br/>
          jargon of their native tongue.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-3/1162,2604,832,148/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Icham for woing al forwake<br/>
            Wery no water in wore
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-3/837,2774,1819,572/full/0/default.tif">
          Up stairs they spoke French. Anons words were as<br/>
          uncouth to the master and mistress as to us. Anon<br/>
          singing at the (yhe) back door was  despised (despsied). He had no name;<br/>
          he had no place, yet even if they felt contempt for the<br/>
          <sup>singer whose body took its [small?] part in the [dance?]</sup> man who made songs, they tolerated him. Even Kings and Queens
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-5/877,70,123,160/full/0/default.tif">
          3
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-5/827,188,1871,1528/full/0/default.tif">
          the scholar tell us, must have their 
            minstrel (misntre). They must<br/>
          have They needed his comment, his buffoonery. <sup>his [uncouth?] at [illeg.]</sup> They kept him<br/>
          in <sup>the [illeg.]</sup> being, 
            tolerating (tolerting) him (h m), as we tolerate those who say out<br/>
          loud what we feel but are too proud to admit. He used the<br/>
          outsiders privilege to co mock the 
            solemn (solmen), to comment upon<br/>
          the established. The  church men hxmxmxmxmxmxmxxx feared<br/>
          and hated <sup>hating the</sup> the 
            anonymous (anonymo s) singer. They did their best to <sup>[illeg.]</sup><br/>
          If they could, they pressed him and his <sup>[illeg.]</sup> actors gift into<br/>
          the service of the church. He was to be found acting the<br/>
          Mass in the church; but <sup>[illeg.]</sup> as he acted more and more his own<br/>
          art, he left the church, and staged his pageant in the<br/>
          churchyard, or later was given a pitch for his drama in the<br/>
          market place. Still he remained nameless, often ribald,<br/>
          often obscene.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-5/839,1710,1867,1672/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>Yet </sup>During the silent 
            centuries (centruies) before the book was printed<br/>
          his was the only voice to be heard in England.<br/>
          Save for  singing his song at 
            the (yhe) back door the English<br/>
          might be a dumb race, a race of merchants, soldiers, 
            priests (preists);<br/>
          who left behind them stones houses, cultivated fields and<br/>  
          great churches, but no words. <s>He it was</s><sup>It was he</sup> who gave voice to<br/>
          the old stories, who incidted the peasants when he came to<br/>
          the back door to put off their working clothes and deck them<br/>
          selves in green leaves. He it was who found words for them<br/>
          to sing, and 
            when ( shen) they went at the great seasons to do<br/>
          
            homage (himage) to the old pagan Gods. He wxxxxxxxx taught them<br/>
          the songs the  sung at Christmas and at midsummer. He<br/>
          led them to the haunted tree; to the well; to the old<br/>
          burial place where they did 
            homage (himage) to the pagan gods.<br/>
          If we could see the village as it was before  time
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-7/904,144,114,124/full/0/default.tif">
          4
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-7/852,252,1840,2856/full/0/default.tif">
          we should see tracks across the fields 
            joining (joing) manor house to<br/>
          hovel, and hovel to church. Some of those paths of course<br/>
          were worn by 
            soldiers (soliders) and
            labourers (labouerers). They must fight to<br/>
          
            gather (gether) and plough together if they were not to be conquered<br/>
          by man and by nature. That connection isxx as time goes on<br/>
          and the <sup>[he? her?] <s>me</s> records the daily struggle</sup><s>classes separate themselves</s>, is still painfully<br/>
          recorded in old letter books and ledgers. It makes the<br/>
          staple of the old 
            correspondence (corresp ondence) between the <br/>
          of  and the  and  of .<br/>
          But there was also the the other less visible connection<br/>
          --the common belief. That track between the houses in the<br/>
          village has been grown over<sup>;-</sup> like the track along which the<br/>
           rode to .--no one rides that way now.<br/>
          But before  time thxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx<br/>
          it was trod daily. <sup>which</sup> It led <s>the peasants</s> to the tree<br/>
          to the well. In spring it led to the Maypole, where they<br/>
          danced and sung Anons song. At Midsummer they lit the bon<br/>
          
            fire (fir) on the hill. At Christmas the mummers acted the old<br/>
          Anons old play; and the boys came singing his wassailing<br/>  
          song. The road led to the old graves, to the stones where<br/>
          in time past the English had done sacrifice. The peasants (peasnts),<br/>
          led by anon, still went that way by instinct, in spring<br/>
          and summer and winter. The old Gods lay hidden beneath the<br/>
          new. It was to them led by Anon that they did worship,<br/>
          in their coats of green leaves, bearing swords in their hands<br/>
          dancing through the houses, enacting their ancient parts.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-7/912,3095,1752,300/full/0/default.tif">
          It was the  <s>in 1477</s> that k <sup>finally was to kill</sup><br/>
          Anon. but it was the press also that preserved him. When
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-9/883,126,94,88/full/0/default.tif">
          5
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-9/815,212,1869,2976/full/0/default.tif">
          in 1477  printed the twenty one <br/>
           he fixed the voice of Anon for ever. There we tap<br/>
          the reservoir of common belief that lay deep sunk in the<br/>
          minds 
            of (od) peasants and nobles. There in  pages<br/>
          we hear the voice of Anon murmuring still. Hexxxxxx<br/>
          If Caxton himself doubted---  he objected<br/>
          never lived-- there were still nobles and gentry who<br/>
          xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx were positive. They said that<br/>
          you 
            could (soulc) see  skull at ; and the <br/>
          at ; and "in other places  sword and<br/>
          many other things." So  printed the old dream.<br/> 
          It is still half fact. <sup>[illeg.] It is a [buried?] world</sup>
            There (Ythere) is ; and ; and<br/>
          ; there is the  and<br/>
          . But real places are set in a dream world.<br/>
          The 
            roads (raods) lead past CxmxmxxuLondon to castles where 
            Knights (Kinghts)<br/>
          lie 
            enchanted (enchannted); down the 
            roads (rodas) ride Queens on white mules;<br/>
           
            turns (truns) herself to stone; and a hand rises from<br/>
          a lake holding . <sup>The [illeg.]</sup> It has a childs implicit belief. <sup>in the [story?]</sup><br/>
          It has a childs love of particularity. Txxxxxxxx Everything<br/>
          is stated. The beauty is in the statement, not in the<br/>
          suggestion. "So he went in and searched from chamber to<br/>
          
            chamber, and found his bed, but she was not there; then Balin<br/>
            looked into a little garden, and under a laurel tree<br/>
            he saw her lie upon a quilt of green samite and a knight with
          her, and under their 
            heads (hedads) grass and herbs". The world is<br/>
          seen without comment; <sup>and</sup> did the writer know what beauty he<br/>
          makes us see?
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-9/415,1178,447,484/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            it brought to<br/>
            the surface<br/>
            the old<br/>
            hidden<br/>
            world
          </sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-9/839,3142,1867,280/full/0/default.tif">
          But, save that self consciousness had not 
            yet (hyet)<br/>
          raised its mirror, the men and women are ourselves, seen
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-11/888,100,130,148/full/0/default.tif">
          6
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-11/863,212,1799,1560/full/0/default.tif">
          out of perspective, xxx elongated, foreshortened, but<br/>
          very old, with a knowledge of all good and<br/>
          
            all evil (allevil). They are already corrupt in this<br/>
          fresh world. They have evil dreams.  is doomed; the<br/>
          Queens are 
            lustful (luftful). There never was, it seems, a time<br/>
          when men and women were without memory; <s>were innocent</s><br/>
          There 
            never (enver) was a young world. <s>There</s> <sup>B</sup><s>b</s>ehind the English<br/>
          lay ages of toil and love. 
            This (T is) <sup>That</sup> is the world beneath our<br/>
          consciousness; the 
            anonymous (anoymous) world to 
            which (whcich) we can still<br/>
          
            return (re urn). Of the writer nothing is known. <sup>The scholar can find something. But</sup> Malory is not<br/>
          distinct from his book. The voice is still the voice of<br/>
          . murmuring <sup>[illeg.]</sup> about Kings and Queens who are base and<br/>
          heroic; vile and gentle, like 
            ourselves (ourslves), stripped of the<br/>
          encumbrances that time has wrapped about us.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-11/895,1762,1799,1560/full/0/default.tif">
          <s>But </s> printing press 
            foretold (foreold) the end of that<br/>
          
            anonymous (anoyl s) world; it is now written down; fixed; nothing will<br/>
          be added; even if the legend still murmurs on, and still<br/>
          down in  the peasants (peants) 
          remember (rmember) how " on the night<br/>
          of the full moon King Arthur and his men ride round the<br/>
          hill, and their horses are shod with silver." After<br/>
          that the audience became separate from the singer; <s>After that</s><sup>For a time we</sup><br/>
          we hxxxx find someone who looks back, who gathers<br/>
          together a 
            chronicle (chornicle) of what has happened. We find the<br/>
          individual, emerging from the past; His name his ;<br/>
          he has a library; he owns a mastiff and digs up coins.  is<br/>
          dead when we meet with him. The  have gone<br/>
          their way. He sees the past against a back ground of the<br/>
          
            present (presn t), and the present looks raw, degenerate against
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-11/257,2006,639,1124/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            But The<br/>
            printed book<br/>
            brought into existence<br/>
            the man who can<br/>
            read the man who<br/>
            becomes<br/>
            conscious, of the<br/>
            present, of<br/>
            himself, against<br/>
            the background<br/>
            of the past.<br/>
            it brings into being the<br/>
            whole, the audience—<br/>
            a man like it.
          </sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-13/961,58,110,124/full/0/default.tif">
          7
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-13/947,144,1743,664/full/0/default.tif">
          against the past. There is too much comfort now; <s>too many</s><br/>
          xmxmxx the pillow has taken the place of the old log with<br/>
          a dip in the middle; there are too many 
            chimneys (chimenys). The young<br/>
           and  are not the men their fathers were.<br/>
          They are tender and subject to rheumatism. Also<br/>
          they dress most 
            fantastically (fantasically) 
            compared (com ared) with 
            their ancestors (theirancestors).
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-13/879,812,1855,2536/full/0/default.tif">
          He does not see the mummers and the wassailers;<br/>
          he does not hear the voice of ; he 
            scarcely (scracely) listens even<br/>
          to the song of  Canterbury pilgrims. <sup>For </sup>The English<br/>
          past as  saw it, served only to show up the material<br/>
          change--the change that had come over houses, 
            furniture (furnt iture)<br/>
          clothing. There was no English literature to show up the<br/>
          
            change (chnage) in the mind. <sup>the English songs were [illeg.]</sup> Anons song at the back door was as<br/>
          difficult 
            for (cfor) him to spell as for us. But the old<br/>
          
            English (Eglish) songs were more painful. for they reminded him of<br/>
          his lack of intellectual 
            ancestry (ancstry). His intellectual pedigree<br/>
          only reached back to , to  to .<br/>
          In order to have 
            ancestors (anscetors) by way of the mind he must cross<br/>
          the  his ancestors by way of the mind are the<br/>
          Greeks and Romans. His page is 
            burdened (burdneed) with these proofs<br/>
          ofgood breeding--- ; ; , --he quotes them to prove his<br/>
          nobility of mind as we to prove ours quote the<br/>
          Elizabethans. The mummers and the wassailers,<br/>
          the actors who <sup>were acting</sup>who staged their crude dramas in the 
            churchyard (churchayrd)<br/>
          or in the market place hxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx<br/>
          were sxmxmx   He turns from the present to the past;<br/>
          he ignores the 
            actors (acors) who were acting their crude 
            dramas (daramas)<br/>
          now in the market place. Yxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmx
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-15/861,128,108,152/full/0/default.tif">
          8
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-15/855,268,1734,1528/full/0/default.tif">
          The 
            historians (histroians) work from the outer to the inner;<br/>
          from the house they infer the tenant of the house. It is the<br/>
          house they uncover; the chairs, the tables, the bills, the<br/>
          close 
            stools (stolls), the spinning wheels, the tapestry.<br/>
          It is as if we were bidden to infer from a tweed suit,<br/>
          six hats, a fox terrier, and a silver 
            knobbed (knovved) walking stick<br/>
          the life and works of a novelist called .<br/>
          Save for 
            Chaucer (Vhaucer) and Lydgate and the voice of Anon singing<br/>  
          at the back door the English might be a dumb race; a race<br/>
          of merchants, 
            soldiers (s ldiers), 
            priests (preists) and builders who left
            behind (nehind)<br/>
          them stone houses, cultivated fields and many churches and<br/>
          cathedrals. ; but no words. The great house is silent.<br/>
          Only the furniture remains, stiff and ornate, fantastic and<br/>
          uncushioned.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-15/839,1780,1814,1664/full/0/default.tif">
          At  for 
            instance (instnace) <br/>
          sat at her table writing (rwiting) to . Her letters (lettres) <sup>—compare them with</sup> might have<br/>
          
            been (veen) sermons from the pulpit (pulpi;t); or state documents (dosuments), intricate (intrcaite)<br/>
          
            involved (inlvoved) and evasive. She is a counsellor admonishing a sub<br/>
          ordinate; 
            she (sShe) is 
            aware (awrae) only of the wickedness 
            of (fof) men,<br/>
          the dangers and 
            deceits (decits) of the world; and the awfuless of<br/>
          God. Greek and Latin come to her pen as easily as 
            English ( nglish).<br/>
          If she has to descend to the actual object--a basket of<br/>
          strawberries--it is with 
            circumlocutions (cirumlocuitions) and dark<br/>
          
            insinuations (insiutaions). "I have sent them by the boy of my kitchen,<br/>
          a shrewd witted boy and prettily 
            catechized (catchized) but yet an un<br/>
          toward 
            crafty (rcrafty) boy...." She xxxxxx exhorts (ex horts):<br/>
          "God keep us sound in faith the faith and send us 
            health (h  lth)<br/>
          and a care to please God above all." She admonishes:<br/>
          "Be not speedy of speech, nor talk suddenly, but where
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-15/199,1876,667,264/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            until <br/>
            </sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-17/893,86,114,106/full/0/default.tif">
          9
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-17/875,178,1707,496/full/0/default.tif">
          
            discretion (disctreion)
           requireth, and that soberly then...."<br/>
          Let not Lawson that fox, be 
            acquainted (acqainted) with my letters...."<br/>
          So 
            the (Lthe) , mother to the poet Earl<br/>
           writes:
        </p>
        <p facs="">
           <br/>
           <br/>
           <br/>
           <br/>
           
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m50/m50-17/831,1094,1843,2000/full/0/default.tif">
          Fear of God, fear of man, hate, agony, passion, surround<br/>
          them with the walls of a dungeon. There is no gaiety,<br/>
          
            no (nu) freedom no 
            familiarity (familairity) in the world the live in. Only in<br/>
          extremity, of hate, of fear, do urges them to pick up the pen<br/>
          The sound of the bible is in their ears, 
            it is (Itis) a garment only<br/>
          to be worn when the mind is in the right attitude. And the<br/>
          garment may of course conceal a Lady Ann who is merry and<br/>
          gay; it may conceal a Duchess who is 
            sensitive (snesitove), amorous<br/>
          and sensual; we cannot tell. Anybody  may live on the other<br/>
          side of that wall of formal language. Using the prose of<br/>
          the Bible when they write prose the Elizabethans are unknown<br/>
          to us. They can say nothing simple, subtle, or little.<br/>
          Bright contrasted colours meet on 
            their (ther) faces; carnation<br/>
          and snow; ebony and gold. In their portraits, the young mens<br/>
          bodies are sewn into padded doublets; school boys faces<br/>
          are raised above 
            starched (strached) ruffs; and young women serve only<br/>
          to 
            support (supp rt) heavy 
            quilted ( uilted) dresses stuck about with<br/>
          huge xxxx pearls.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>