<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M111 Set 1 of 3, [The Reader: But her own passion, the disgrace, the humiliation...]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 5 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m111-1</idno>
          </msIdentifier>s
          <physDesc>
            <p>M111, Set 1 of 3 [The Reader: But her own passion, the disgrace, the humiliation...]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 5 fols.</p>
            <p>Paginated 29-33.</p>
            <p>p. 29 with discarded page paginated 34 on verso.</p>
            <p>p. 30 with page from <!-- ask Bryony --> story on verso.</p>
            <p>p. 32 with page from Between the Acts paginated 155 on verso.</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-1/880,82,125,141/full/0/default.tif">
          29
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-1/759,192,1953,2428/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>But</sup> Her own passion, the disgrace, the humiliation of her <sup>are all [actual?] in dumb shows</sup>
          family are all hidden under silence itself; or such
          flourishes and ornaments that reveal 
            notning (nothing). After
          that amount to 
            sielnce (silence). The plain country squires, 
            the (they)
          are all teased once they take pen in hand by the demon
          of poetry. 
            Af e (After) fl flxmxmxmxmxm floundering out a page
          of conceits and 
            fanatsies (fantasies), Mr  has indeed recourse
          to poetry. After trying to explain My conceit of this
          triple love, of affection passion and 
            conjnuction (conjunction)" with a
          
            w nedrin ([wandering?]) 
            welt th (wealth) of imagery he quotes ... "... of lae
          
            late I have light upon Mr 
              Soensers (Spensers) opinion so rightly 
              Soensers (Spensers) opinion so rightly 
              agreeig (agreeing)
            with that which nature had 
              taight (taught) me before, as the
            same might have been thought to have drawn out of his
          
          discipline." It is the poets still who speak for the
          squires 
            whocannot (who cannot) speak for 
            themslces (themselves). Yet behind these
          
            gfloird (florid) decorations, these strained elegancies,
          the wolves and foxes of the 
            cort (court) prey and raven.
          Bastards are 
            borb (born). There is a crude appetite a greed a 
            passin (passion)
          which moves under the flowers and suddenly glares at us.
          Bastards are born in the flesh. Reputations are ruined.
          Only the people 
            themlves (themselves) pass unseen. They too like the
          dramatists remain anonymous.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-1/779,2628,1921,764/full/0/default.tif">
          Yet there is a strange contradiction. If the
          wr country 
            bgentlemen (gentlement) and their wives must speak in
          hyperbole when they write 
            f (of) love, they write of possessions
          in plain English. No generation had more anxiety to preserve <sup>[illeg.]</sup>
          their physical bodies from decay. 
            Theyeat (They eat) prodigously.
          They wear clothes that are so heavy they can scarcely move
          in them. 
            Invenory (Inventory) after inventory records their 
            furiture (furniture),
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-2/504,76,262,278/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>34</sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-2/727,20,1930,2204/full/0/default.tif">
          are all 
            contrbutions (contributions) to our knowledge
          of what  looked like, if you see him through
          a certain 
            visoon (vision). But there always remains
          something further. It is this that lures the
          reader 
            Abd (and) it is this quality that
          finally eludes us. gives him his perpetual vitality,
          he 
            ecites (excites) 
            perp tual (perpetual) curiosity. He does not as so many
          writers feed momentary 
            appettites (appetites). The 
            resder (reader) who has a dash
          of the writer in him, seeks out certain styles; certain
          forms. But 
            Shakespere (Shakespeare) has 
            nosuch (no such) appeal to the reader-writer.
          His styles are too 
            innumerabel (innumerable) 
            Perhpas (Perhaps) then he is chiefly
          used for more general 
            piposes (purposes)--when the ink has gone dry
          upon the pen to revive the sense of 
            langauge (language); or to
          testify, when words seem 
            motiinless (motionless), to the enormous
          possibilities of speed. One reading always supersedes another
          Thus the 
            trueest (truest) account of reading 
            Shakespere (Shakespeare) would be
          not to write a book with a beginning middle and end;
          but to collect notes, without trying to make them
          consistent.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-3/791,48,185,162/full/0/default.tif">
          30
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-3/791,192,1690,684/full/0/default.tif">
          their jewels, their horses and carriages. When they die,
          heavy marble tombs are raised over them. The outer life
          is as 
            substa tial (substantial) as cloth of gold and pigs capons hogs
          can make it. But the mind that lives in the head, the
          heart that hxxx speak only on the , through the
          mouths of the players.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-3/273,318,541,326/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup> 
            
            
            
          </sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-3/1108,870,557,115/full/0/default.tif">
          Txmxmxmxmxmxmx
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-3/655,968,1969,2316/full/0/default.tif">
          Yet in no age can there have been a deeper gulf
          between the artist and 
            socity (society).  dedicates his
          sonnets to  Not one of all those highly 
            eduvated (educated)
          nobles troubles to ask who is this patron? It is not a matter
          of interest in court circles. The plays are not discussed.
          Lord 
            Southmapton (Southampton) and Lord Rutland,  wrote to
          , pass away the time in London, merely in
          going to plays 
            ev y (every) day" But the attraction of the stage
          called forth no comment. The players lived too far from the
          court to stir curiosity. They were too much of servants,
          too much of minstrels, jugglers 
            nbear (bear) 
            laeders (leaders) to
          be a proper topic for gossip. Thus the early works of
          
            Shakeepare (Shakespeare) make no ripple in the pool of 
            sielnce (silence).
          No one protests that here is an upstart writer who is
          for 
            throwin (throwing) society into the melting pot. The 
            grreat (great) might
          be mocked--that was the 
            anicient (ancient) privilege of the court
          
            jster (jester); or some scene from history 
            re encated (reenacted). But the 
          was quick to control irreverence. And in fact the dramatist
          wasn ot destroying society. The indignation that, after the
          first silent surprise, that  for example stirred in
          London was partly the rage of those who felt that
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/799,50,181,182/full/0/default.tif">
          2
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/827,200,1514,172/full/0/default.tif">
          stop in the middle of her song. and shut the piano.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/791,376,1690,580/full/0/default.tif">
          Her father beat her oftener and 
            oftner (oftener).
          She would show the marks on her flesh in the kitchen.
          "The squire didnt out to" said Pink the groom.
          xmxmxmxmxm Jinny the parlourmaid agreed <sup>would have agreed.</sup>; but her cough
          prevented her xxxx
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/1136,935,423,145/full/0/default.tif">
          Stxxx
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/823,1040,1690,676/full/0/default.tif">
          There were many legs on the alwn <sup>lawn</sup> in the summer.
          She would watch them from between the 
            rasperry (raspberry) canes,
          where she had a cave A grass path led between the bushes,
          and once the legs came walking there; and her brother(
          
            ni (in) white flannel) stooped; and the girl in a white 
            shkirt (skirt)
          who was with him 
            stopped (stooped) too.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/823,1692,1706,580/full/0/default.tif">
          Hullo 
            LElizabeth (Elizabeth)" said her brother. "
            VCut (Cut) 
            alkng (along)
          into the 
            houseand (house and) fetch my pipe; and I'll give you 
            sipence (sixpence)"
          She guessed it was not his pipe he wanted; but to be
          rid of her. So she mooned round the library looking at the
          great pictures.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/831,2240,1706,580/full/0/default.tif">
          They had been in that house for ever so long.
          And the great pictures were almost part of the walls.
          They were ancestors; children; youths; grown men and women;
          sea captains; bishops. And the strange men used to look at
          them 
            andmake (and make) notes in their pocket books.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/811,2784,1778,364/full/0/default.tif">
          The only person she saw whole, from her yellow head
          to her little black slippers, was Carry Elmer, the 
            duag ter (daughter)
          of another squire.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-4/819,3128,1778,236/full/0/default.tif">
          At intervals of ten miles apart 
            ther (there) were then
          great houses. Perry Hall, the 
            E;mers (Elmers) house, was famous.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-5/900,76,182,190/full/0/default.tif">
          31
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-5/796,264,1884,3036/full/0/default.tif">
          The Elizabethan audience were not readers. They had to
          draw in the play as they sat or stood at the playhouse,
          through their ears, through their eyes. There was no book
          of 
            thee (the) words. They could not dxxxx deepen the impression,
          chew it over, and compare it, at a <s>
            atble (table)</s> in a private room.
          This perhaps 
            exp;ains (explains) the scarcity of Elizabethan
          criticism; and the general nature of what <sup>[certain?]</sup> there is.
          
            Bioth (Both)  and  deal with the 
            neral (general)
          not with the 
            particualr (particular); with the rules of 
            compsition (composition),
          not with 
            t e (the) details of one play or poem in 
            partciualr (particular).
          It accounts too for the long pause <sup>between [sixteenth? seventeenth?] &amp; the 18th centuries</sup> when the plays of
          
             even hang suspended and unrealised. It was only
          when <sup>they had to [wait?]</sup> they were printed and the book of the words lay in many
          private rooms txxxx <sup>before they</sup> received their other life from
          the reader. Much that was lost in the 
            playhous e (playhouse) was
          discovered in the private room. But much has also been lost <sup>, when the </sup>
          We have lost the sound of the spoken word; all that the
          sight of the actors body gives through the eye to the mind.
          We have lost too the sense of being part of the audience.
          We miss a thousand shades that the 
            darmatistconveyed (dramatist conveyed)by inflection of voice, by gesture, by the 
            palcing (placing) of
          the actors 
            vbodies (bodies). This can still be tested, at least with
          Shakespeare, by 
            comapring (comparing) whxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxx our impression
          xmxmxmxmxmxxx after seeing the 
            p ay (play) with our
          impression after reading the play. But as the modern actor
          inevitably imports much that is of his own day, but foreign
          to 
            Shshakespeare (Shakespeare), there is still something sunk beyond
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-7/763,66,161,118/full/0/default.tif">
          32
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-7/779,170,473,134/full/0/default.tif">
          beyond recall.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-7/679,352,2067,2188/full/0/default.tif">
          Presumably the earlier plays, in
            whichnthe (which the) 
            pplaywright ()
          was more at 
            tge (the) mercy of the audience, are <sup>the</sup> more damaged
          by 
            rreading (reading) them xmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxx The reader instinctively
          tries to be there in person. He tries to 
            sup ly (supply) the 
            trumepts (trumpets)
          and the flags; the citizens and the apprentices.
          He furbishes himself <sup>nourishes himself</sup> with a dip into ,
          with a dip into . He makes an effort to 
            sppply (supply) what
          <s>is so obviously</s> the sunk part of the play. But he is 
            perp (perpetually)
          
            tually (perpetually) rebuffed. He is apt <sup>pat</sup> to become not a reader but a
          student; txmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmmxmxmx a collector of
          scattered bones. At some point however in the Elizabethan
          drama the 
            rezder (reader) is born. There are 
            spepeches (speeches) and 
            scnes (scenes)
          that call upon his special faculty. When the dramatist
          becomes conscious of the play as a work of art; when he
          becomes able to unite the play by a unity which is
          not that of the plot-- by something in himself <sup>his [illeg.], his [illeg.]</sup>
          by some individuality of his style, of his whole temper,
          <sup>It is the apprehension of this power at work</sup>
          <s>it is this apprehension</s> that serves to 
            drow (draw) together the
          faculties <s>which are proper to the reader.</s>
          
            th t (that) brings the reader into being.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-7/723,2532,1979,836/full/0/default.tif">
          The reader has been in existence for round
          about four 
            hubdred (hundred) years. But his life 
            hisotry (history) is an
          obscure one. At some point his ear must have lost its 
            a uten (acuteness)
          acuteness; then his eyes became dull. Then he became word
          conscious, aware of suggestions and echoes. As time 
            paassed (passed),
          he imported into the 
            writteh (written) word much that was
          unintended by the writer. A word spelt in the Elizabethan
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-8/1740,3287,209,159/full/0/default.tif">
          155
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-8/159,1528,1985,1772/full/0/default.tif">
          
            ho mes (homes) will be built. <sup>Each flat with</sup> With refrigerators <s>in each flat</s>?
          xmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxm xxxx <s>And churches</s>...
          The tune <s>changed. It</s> chopped and changed. <s>It broke off. It</s>
          broke up. 
            Withthe (With the) means at 
            he (her) 
            dispoal (disposal) you couldnt ask too
          
            mcu (much). Thxmxmxmxmxmxmx; What a cackle; a 
            cocophony (cacophony)...
          like the yaffle, a they call the woodpecker. The laughing
          bird who flits from tree to tree. <sup>Out they skipped.</sup>
          Children? Imps --elfs... <s>Out they skipped.</s> The riff raff
          of the village... Holding what? Tin cans? Bed room candle
          sticks? <s>S<sup>h</sup>aving glasses?</s> Old 
            tobbaco (tabacco) jars? My dear, thats the
          
            cehval (cheval) glass from the rectory... and the mirror-- I lent her.
          My 
            motgers (mother's)... And 
            grabdpas (grandpa's) old top hat! Whats the notion?
          Anything thats bright enough, presumably, to 
            refelct (reflect)...
          <s>
            Thats the mens shaving glass from the stable..
            Mrs Sands, did you really lend her that?
          </s>
          Ourselves Ourselves?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-9/915,30,161,150/full/0/default.tif">
          33
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-1/m111-1-9/915,168,1755,1692/full/0/default.tif">
          the meaning of words is tremendously developed; so that they
          remain attached to certain aspects of the printed page;
          the 
            sch ars (scholars) the students whxmxmxmxmxmxx, Again there is
          the very large class of perfectly 
            literatue (literate) 
            peole (people) 
            whorun (who run)
          their eyes over miles of print yearly, yet never read a w
          word. Txmxmxmxxx The reader, distinct from the 
            schoar (scholar),
          distinct from the print stripper of news paper print,
          has a curious 
            p wer (power) to make houses and countries
          visible, men and 
            womn (women) and their thoughts and emotion,
          from marks on a piece of paper. His faculty is always 
            changig (changing)
          The reader 
            agains (again) is always changing. The  is now
          
            develpojg (developing) his eyes, the 
             is 
            dev pojg (developing) his ear.
          He is still in existence; for it is a fact that
          he is still 
            casuing (causing) books to be printed.
          He is still reading 
            Sjakespere (Shakespeare).
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>