<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M54, 11 of 11. [Anon: there is a jolt at the points...]. Typescript fragment, 1 fol.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m54-11</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M54, 11 of 11. [Anon: there is a jolt at the points...]. Typescript fragment, 1 fol.</p>
            <p>N.B.: This is one of eleven sub-fragments identified in the Berg Collection's M54. [Anon: The printing press brought the past into existence...]. Typescript fragments, unsigned and undated, 35 fols. I have determined pagination and sequencing based on subject matter. M54 as curated by the Berg Collection is available as part of 'The Digital Anon' and can be found at [LINK].</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-11/m54-11-1/815,42,199,194/full/0/default.tif">
          23
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-11/m54-11-1/815,214,1775,742/full/0/default.tif">
          there is a jolt at the points; the mind slides onto another<br/>
          rail, lovely as the words are. To speak them the poet has<br/>
          separated himself from the actors. He cannot yet make <br/>
           speak those words. The play is still 
            mainly (manly) the work<br/>
          of the undifferentiated audience, demanding great names,<br/>
          great deeds; simple outlines; and not the single subtlety<br/>
          of one soul.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-11/m54-11-1/785,938,1851,1518/full/0/default.tif">
          For the play itself was still anonymous. The lack of Marlowes<br/>
          name is by 
            itself (itslef) enough to show how largely the play was<br/>
          a common product, written by one hand, but so moulded<br/>
          in transition from actor to 
            actor (acotr) that the author had no<br/>
          sense of property in it. It was half the work of the audience.<br/>
          Yet the audience is dumb. The silence of the audience is<br/>
          one of the deep gulfs that lies between us and the 
            Elizabethan (Eliza)<br/>
          Elizabethan (bethan) play. The audience was a large one. Fifteen<br/>
          hundred people, Dr Greg computes, was an average 
            attendance (attanedance).<br/>
          Their presence, in the penny part of the house, is obvious.<br/>
          It draws 
            up (pup) the 
            hyperbole (hypberpole) as a sheet of paper<br/>
          draws 
            up (pup) fire. It makes the writer capable of great strides<br/>
          and vast audacities beyond his private reach. Yet the 
            audience (audiene)<br/>
          sits silent.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-11/m54-11-1/771,2444,1838,1004/full/0/default.tif">
          To 
            understand (underdtand) the silence we must 
            compare (comapre) it<br/>
          with our own 
            attitude (attidtue) at the  at the <br/>
          in the early days. A new art comes upon us 
            so (si) 
            surprisingly (surprisningly)<br/>
          that we are silent, recognising something that we cannot<br/>
          measure. To <sup>the</sup> Elizabethans, the power of words after their<br/>
          long 
            silence (silnce) must have been overwhelming. There at the <br/>
          or at the  men and women who had never seen themselves<br/>
          whose only reading was 
            history or (historyor) sermon or some old 
            chronicle (chornicle)<br/>
          or perhaps could not 
            read (r ad) but spent all their days in the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>