<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          1  25th Nov. 1940<br/>
          Anon.<br/>
          @@@@@@@@@@@@@@<br/>
          For many centuries 
            after (aft) Britain became an island<br/>
          the  says, the untamed forest was king.<br/>
          On the matted boughs of that forest innumerable birds sang;<br/>
          but their song was only heard by a few skin clad hunters<br/>
          in the clearings. Did the desire to sing come to one<br/>
          of those savages because he heard the birds sing? <sup>&amp; did</sup><s>Did he</s><br/>
          rest his stone axe against a tree for a moment? <sup>[illeg.]</sup> The tree<br/>
          was felled; some sort of hut 
            was (ws) made from its branches, and<br/>
          then by degrees, the clearing became larger; the birds<br/>
          fewer; and the human voice sung instead. <sup>&amp;</sup> The first songs<br/>
          are out of door songs; spring songs; summer songs; winter<br/>
          songs. <sup>&amp;</sup> for there was no comfort 
            indoors (indoor), little<br/>
          light and no books.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          The eye therefore was xxxx more acti<sup>v</sup>e in the first sxxxxxxx<br/>
          singers than in ourselves. And some parts of 
            England (Englab)<br/>
          can still be seen as they saw it. Now and then by choosing<br/>
          a view carefully to shut out a chimney or a 
            bungalow (bungalwo),<br/>
          we can still see a flat fen, reed whispering, waterlogged;<br/>
          or a down, covered w still with turf only <s>And over</s><sup>But on</sup> the<br/>
          down lies a green scar, along which the travellers came,<br/>
          with the pack horses, dressed in wool, not in skins,<br/>
          _____________________________________________________<br/>
           by  p. 3
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          2<br/>
          the common voice, singing out of doors. He has no house.<br/>
          He has a quick eye. connected, for the eye is a youthful<br/>
          sense, with the body, with colour, with substance, rather<br/>
          than with the mind. He lives a 
            roaming (romaning) life, going from<br/>
          house to house, stopping oftener at the back door than at<br/>
          the front. He crosses the fields, mounts the hills, and<br/>
          lies down on the grassy 
            road (roa ) by the hawthorn to listen to<br/>
          the nightingale.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          By choosing a 
            view (vuew) carefully to shut out a chimney or a<br/>
          bungalow we can still see what  saw-- the bird haunted<br/>
          reed whispering fen; the down covered with turf, and the<br/>
          scar long healed over the moor, over the down, along which<br/>
           came when he made his journeys. He was<br/>
          for the most part a simple singer, lifting a song or story<br/>
          from other peoples lips, and letting the <sup>audience</sup> country people<br/>
          join in the chorus. But now and again <sup/>hxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmx<br/>
          he made a few lines <sup>himself</sup> that exactly corresponded to his emotion.<br/>
          He was an artist.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        4   2<br/>
        But for him of course we have to wait until winter was<br/>
        past.
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          3<br/>
           died round about 1477. It was the printed book with<br/>
          the authors name attached that killed him. <sup>[</sup> After that the<br/>
          audience was separate from the singer. <sup>]</sup> And with <s>him</s><sup>Anon</sup> died<br/>
          that part of the song that the audience sang, the voice that<br/>
          supplied the story, filled in the pauses, andadded sometimes<br/>
          a nonsensical chorus. After that the song was attached to<br/>
          the singer<sup>the singer was separate from the audience</sup><sup>:</sup>Anon is , or  or Peter. He live<sup>d</sup> in<br/>
          a house axmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxxx had features of his own,<br/>
          has xmxmxmxxx features of his own <s>and above all </s><sup>there is</sup> a past.<br/>
          and <sup>behind him</sup> looks back at the past. Time has drawn its blue veil<br/>
          over the horizon. Hexsxmxmxmxmxxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmx <sup>He looks back to/over the forests &amp; the roads.</sup><br/>
          <sup>One can [see?] <s>is</s> clearly when the present where there is a past behind it.</sup><br/>
           is dead; and 
            the (th)  have gone their<br/>
          way. He-- <s>as it happens</s> <sup>to take the first of the individuals</sup> he is 
            called (aclled) -- is the <sup>a parson</sup><br/>
          first in that long line of leisured and learned men who have<br/>
          time to think about the past in the quiet of 
            the (th)<br/>
          parsonage. He is a 
            representative (representa ive) man, often repeated with<br/>
          little variation in other 
            centuries (centruies). Like , like<br/>
           Harrison the parson of  had a library; and<br/>
          dug up coins. <s>
            Winter (Wint) is past and</s> <sup>H</sup>e <s>already</s>sees <sup>already</sup> sees the present<br/>
          against a background.<sup><s>He is able to see</s> Now that he has a past he can see the present</sup> T<sup>he</sup> past has become so settled, so<br/>
          ordered that the present looks ungainly and degenerate<br/>
          xmxmxmxmxx against it. There is too much comfort; too many<br/>
          pillows too many chimneys. The 
            young (y ung)  and <br/>
          are not the men their fathers were. The smoke drawn up by<br/>
          chimneys no longer salts and 
            hardens (hard ns) them. They are tender<br/>
          and subject to rheumatism. Also, they dress most<br/>
          fantastically compared with their ancestors.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          But the 
            English (Eng ish) past as seen by  only
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">4</p>
        <p facs="">
          served to show up the material change--the change that had<br/>
          
            come (coke) over houses, furniture, clothing. There was no English<br/>
          literature to 
            show (s ow) up the change in the mind. There was <sup>were</sup> no<br/>
          
            English (Ebglish) <s>
              literature (literture)
            </s> <sup>books</sup> to prove the decline of English literature<br/>
          The English 
            language (lnaguage) as  tells us had gone<br/>
          underground <sup>after the conquest</sup> for two centuries. Up stairs they talked French.<br/>
          English <s>language</s> had gone 
            downstairs (dow  stairs) into the kitchen, into<br/>
          the farmyard. Anon had sung his song at the back door in a<br/>
          jargon that was as uncouth to Harrison as to ourselves. 
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            Icham for woing al forwake<br/>
            Wery no water in wore
          
            An hendy hap ichabbe yghent<br/>
            Ichot from hevene it is me sent
          
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          --- the words were as difficult for him to spell out as for<br/>
          
            ourselves (ourslves). But they were more paiful, for they reminded him<br/>
          of his lack of intellectual ancestry. His intellectual pedi<br/>
          gree reaches back only to , , 
            .<br/>
          In order to have ancestors he must 
            cross (ross) the ;<br/>
          his 
            ancestors (anc stors) by way of the mind are the Greeks and the<br/>
          Romans. His page is 
            burdened (burdneed), xxx with <s>proofs</s> <sup>[protestations?]</sup> of good 
            breeding (breedg)<br/>
          ; ; ; ---<br/>
          he quotes them to prove his good 
            breeding (bredding) <sup>nobility of mind</sup>, as we, to prove<br/>
          ours, 
            quote (quite), or , or <br/>
          The Greeks and the Romans occupied <sup>[</sup> the same place<sup>]</sup> in his<br/>
          mind <sup>the place</sup> that the 
            Elizabethans (Elizabtehans) occupy in our own. The  
            great (geeat) book<br/>
          that were chained to the shelves of college libraries were<br/>
          written in the learned 
            tongues (tong es). Only the 
            learned (leraned) and the<br/>
          <sup>leisured</sup> noble read them. ...our ancient ladies of the court as<br/>
           tells us, were to be found reading the 
            [Greeks?] (G      ) [and?]
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          5<br/>
          LaTins as they sat at their needlework.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          In the back ground then stood the marble busts of<br/>
          
            Greeks (Greekd) and Romans, overpowering (overpwering), and  and<br/>
          . And in the foreground there is the house,<br/>
          no longer a hut made with branches, no longer thi<sup>ck</sup> with<br/>
          wood smoke. There is a pillow now, instead of the old log<br/>
          with a dip for the head to rest in; glass fills the windows,<br/>
          <sup>the ceilings are curiously worked;</sup> and the spoos and plates are of silver and pewter. 
            Beyond (Beyo m) the<br/>
          
            house (h use) there are <sup>a few</sup> roads wxmxmxmxmxmxx with great many 
            roomed (roome)<br/>
          Inns at intervals. The roads lead to ; a fine city;<br/>
          and sometimes harrison     <s>The roads</s> lead <sup>say here &amp; there</sup> all across England<br/>
          <s>they lead</s> to the <s>channel</s> <sup/>; Great 
            travellers (tarvellers) there are who have<br/>
          
            crossed (crosses) the 
             and been to  to . But<br/>
           himself <s>is no 
            traveller (travller). Harrison</s> has never been<br/>
          more than forty miles from <sup>,</sup> he tells us. He tells 
            us (s)<br/>
          that he has a garden; <sup>that he</sup> digs for coins; and <sup>that he</sup> owns a mastiff.<br/>
          The age of 
            anonymity (anoynmity) is over <s>when wxmxxxx the writer</s><br/>
          <s>tells us that.</s><br/>
          "Winter is past".
        </p>
        <p facs="">
           then has 
            emerged (em ged) from the forests and the floods.<br/>
          He has a dog and a garden; He has books; and he digs in the<br/>
          
            earth (aearth). e xhmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmx. He has a name too,<br/>
          but his name is of no great moment. It may be Harrison; it<br/>
          may be ; <sup>[illeg.] or </sup> it may be 
            Smith ( m th) or Jennings. There is very<br/>
          little to him, save his name. He has no expression<br/>
          on his face. He conveys to us chiefly <sup>the emptiness of England</sup> what he sees--England,<br/>
          xmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmmxx; its emptiness;<br/>
          its scarcity 
            of (o) people; <sup>its few [roads?]</sup>; the 
            predominance (predominence) of individuals.<br/>
          The  is the predominant figure. He counts her 
            possessions (possession)<br/>
          her ships; her palaces He watches her progresses from
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          6<br/>
          along those few rutted and pitted roads to this great<br/>
          house or that. She is parliament, press, society, law, order.<br/>
          But the man who sees this is hard <sup>p</sup>ut <s>to it write</s><br/>
          describe what he sees. Writing is still an art that requires<br/>
          great ceremony. <s>It is</s> a painful an 
            elaborate (elborate) art.<br/>
          What you make with the pen is separate from what you say<br/>
          with the 
            tongue (t nue). Words are stiff and cumbersome and resist<br/>
          the efforts of the pen to shape them. Only a few years back<br/>
          words were written beautifully in lustrous ink upon valuable<br/>
          parchment, and the leaves bound together were chained to the<br/>
          shelf and read in great discomfort on 
            hard benches (ard nechces) in the 
            cold (cod)<br/>
          Even now when words are 
            printed (pr nted) the great 
            public (ublic) is not the<br/>
          reader, or the paymaster. Written words must please a single<br/>
          
            man (an) in the first place, <sup>&amp; win his patronage.</sup>, <s>and the</s>  is<br/>
          ceremoniously <s>tended</s> tendered to <s>a</s>  in words as<br/>
          ornate as the carvings and decorations that shocked him<br/>
          in the fashionable 
            Elizabethan (Elizavethan) house. For the book<br/>
          must find its way into the hall, into the great room where the<br/>
          nobles and the gentry have leisure to read <s>it when</s> they have<br/>
          <s>
            hunted (hjnuted) when they have ordered their estates <sup>after the business &amp; pleasure of the day is over</sup></s>, when the<br/>
          night has come and the ladies are busied with their 
            embroidery (embroidey)<br/>
          It is written for the great who <s>wish</s><sup>like</sup> to <s>learn how their</s><br/>
          <s>
            ancestors (anecstors) lived; and who</s> <sup>to</sup> read aloud the exploits of their<br/>
          ancestors; or <s>who want</s><sup>want</sup> a song to sing to their lutes and<br/>
          citherns.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          7<br/>
          The great 
            Elizabethan (Elizabetha) house is still in existence,<br/>
          standing in its green island of park, separated often from<br/>
          the high road only by a dip in the ground and a low red<br/>
          wall. I<sup>t</sup> is out of proportion now; either it is too<br/>
          large, or the village with its eighteenth nineteenth 
            twentieth (twentieh)<br/>
          century shopps and villas is too small. With its 
            conglomeration (congoler)<br/>
          
            conglomeration (artion) 
            of (o) roofs chapels 
            chimneys (chimenys) it dwarfs its neighbours.<br/>
          Inside all is kept as if , were<br/>
          expected. The rxmxmxxx upright 
            Elizabethan (Elizabthan) chairs stand round<br/>
          
            the (th) walls. Their 
            fringes (frimges) and their tapestry are not much<br/>
          faded. The great oak tables are polished and heavy.<br/>
          The carved chests and 
            cupboards (cupbaords) look brand new.<br/>
          The floor is 
            strewn (ste wn) with rugs; the windows curtained<br/>
          with red and green brocades; and cut glass chandeliers<br/>
          hang down from 
            the (th) xmxmxmxxx the decorated plaster work of 
            the (th)<br/>
          ceiling. Even the 
            toys and knicknacks (t ys and kicknacks) have survived <s>inate</s><br/>
          intact; and there is the varnished pear shaped lute<br/>
          upon which the Queen once played.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          But where are the 
            Elizabethans (Elizabthans) themselves? Human<br/>
          lif<sup>e</sup> has receded from this convoluted iridescent shell.<br/>
          <s>upon which the sun of 1940 shines so brightly. The 
            historians (histprians)</s><br/>
          have ransacked their archives; their old chests; their<br/>
          writing table drawers, their muniment rooms. They have<br/>
          
            disinterred (disnterred) from the <sup>their faded pages</sup> fifteenth century the  of  and the  of . They have <sup>[illeg.]</sup><br/>
          proved that they fought; and 
            betrayed (baretred); and loved; for they<br/>
          begot 
            children (chi ldren). But it is a rudimentary life immured in<br/>
          silence. <s>The shell is polished</s>; something moves and st<br/>
          stirs inside the polished shell. But it the story of the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          8<br/>
          the Elizabethans. He 
            turns (tunrs) away from the present. He does<br/>
          not hear Anon singing at the back door; he ignores the<br/>
          actors who were acting their crude dramas in the market<br/>
          place. Upstairs he says in the great room<br/>
          our ancient ladies of 
            the (th) court are to be found reading<br/>
          
            histories and chronicles (histoires and chornicles), the 
            Greeks and the Latins (Geeks and the atins) as they<br/>
          sat at their 
            needlework (needlwork). <sup>not  not </sup> And the scholars were 
            reading (readong) the<br/>
          
            classics (clasics) that were chained to the shelves in 
            the college (th co  ege)<br/>
          libraries. Yet in spite of the printed book,<br/>
          the common people were still at 
            their (tgeir) lewd 
            practices (pracises).
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          The preacher, going on his round on horseback, from<br/>
          village to village found them at it and raised his voice<br/>
          in anger.  "riding on a journey 
            homeward (homewar) from London" <sup>[London? Latimer?]</sup><br/>
          ixx about 1549 went to the Church to preach and found the<br/>
          door locked fast against him. <sup>For more than half an hour</sup> he waited; and t at last
          
            one of the parish came to me and said: Sir this is a<br/>
            busy day with us, we cannot hear you, it is <br/>
            day. The parish are gone abroad to gather for 
              Robin Hood (Robin Hodd).<br/>
            I was fain there to give place to Robin Hood. I thought my<br/>
            
              [Pocket?] (Rocjet) would have been regarded, though I were not: but it<br/>
            would not serve, it was fain to give place to 
              Robin Hood's (Rbin hoods) men.<br/>
            It is no laughing matter, my 
              friends (freinds), it is a weeping matter,<br/>
            a heavy matter, a heavy matter, under the pretence for<br/>
            gathering for Robin Hood, a 
              Traitor (Traoter), and a 
              Thief (Theif), to put out<br/>
            a preacher...."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          Latimer made war against the minstrels and the<br/>
          mummers. It was his voice that riddled the old 
            superstitions (superstitons)<br/>
          with scorn. For he was no antiquary. He did not dig in his
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          9<br/>
          <s>To </s>  was a txmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmx <sup>nothing but a</sup> thief, <sup/>to Latimer<br/>
          the peasants doing him honour were still blind with<br/>
          
            superstition (supersttion). He himself had walked "in the 
            shadow (shdow)of death"<br/>
          xmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmmxxx till he was thirty.<br/>
          Then gentle Mr master  at  had opened his<br/>
          eyes. Now they saw through the old 
            popish practices (pop sh paracices), the <br/>
          old Pagan customs. He saw <sup>they saw</sup> England itself at this moment<br/>
          in its reality. The cry of the 
            women (wormen) is come up into my<br/>
          eares he said. When he walked trying to read his book in<br/>
          the  garden there 
            was (awas) a 
            knocking (kocking)<br/>
          at the gate. And his 
            man (ma) came and said "Sir, there is one<br/>
          that would speak with 
            you (ou)." So he shut his book and went<br/>
          out among the poor; into the prisons, into the fields.<br/>
          <sup>The cry of the workmen "came up into my eares" he said</sup> He heard the poor Labourrers, gun makers,<br/>
          
            Powdermen, Bow makers, arrowmakers, smiths, carpenters
          
          soldiers and other crafts " crying that 
            they (yhey) were unpaid.<br/>
          
            They (The) found the poor without a goose or a pig for the<br/>
          great were enclosing the fields. He went to the great man<br/>
          and found him still in bed, after his 
            hawking (hakwing) and<br/>
          his 
            hunting (hutning), and the hall full of poor suitors waiting to<br/>
          make their plaints. <sup>[</sup>As 
            for (fot) the Bishops, "they hawke, they<br/>
          
            
              hunt (huntm) they carde, they dice, they pastime in their<br/>
            prelacies with gallant gentlemen, with their dancing<br/>
            minions and with their fresh companions..."<sup>]</sup>
          
          He saw the curates in their 
            velvet (velevet) shoes and slippers<br/>
          "meet to dance 
            the morris (themorris) dance". He saw the fine ladies<br/>
          dressed in fa vardigalls with their hair 
            puffed out (puffedout)<br/>
          in 
            tussocks (tuccosks) and French hoods. He saw the 
            young (yo ng) men,
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          10<br/>
          no longer 
            shooting (shot ing) with the long bow, as his father had<br/>
          taught him to shoot, but bowling, 
            drinking, (drinkingl) whoring. And 
            in (inh)<br/>
          the streets of London he saw the harlot going to ec<br/>
          execution, making merry as she went and crying, "that if<br/>
          
            good (goof) fellows had kept touch with her, she had not been at<br/>
          this time in that case." He noted the smell of<br/>
          rotting bodies 
            in (un) the churchyard at  and<br/>
          foretold plague to come. And in every village he found the<br/>
          peasants going on pilgrimages, setting up candles, 
            worshipping (worshippig)<br/>
          
            pigs' (p gs) bones, and 
            following (follwing) Robin Hood. How should they know<br/>
          
            better (bet er) when 
            there (the re) was no preaching in the pulpits, when<br/>
          the words they heard were in a tongue they could not<br/>
          understand?
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          So he went about England preaching in English,<br/>
          no matter if he preached on horseback or stood under a tree.<br/>
          It did not matter either if he spoke to the  in person.<br/>
          or preaching to the King in person. He did not moderate<br/>
          his words. He spoke to the King himself in a voice that<br/>
          stumbles, that repeats, that loses the thread of its argument<br/>
          <sup>- one [illeg.] about them the first [sticky?] he [illeg.] -</sup>no matter, he will bring before the King the real state of<br/>
          xxx
            England as (Englandas) it axmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxx He will 
            unveil (unbeil)<br/>
          show up, speak the truth, even if it brings him to the<br/>
          faggot as it brought his master, the gentle Mr Bilney.<br/>
          "who was for ever 
            visiting prisoners (visitng risoners) and sick folk."<br/>
          There is only ashort pace left him before he too will<br/>
          stand outside the  at  and feel the flames<br/>
          on his own flesh. So he pours out his anger;<br/>
          So he lights up the state of England with his
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          11<br/>
          <s>He speaks</s> in a voice that stumbles, that uses the plain<br/>
          language of the farm from which he sprang, <s>but</s><sup>I</sup>t is the<br/>
          voice of of reason, of 
            humanity (huamity), of common sense. <sup>[</sup>He will tell<br/>
          the truth, even if it brings him as it brought the gentle<br/>
          Master Bilney to the faggot.<sup>]</sup> He is aware that he has only<br/>
          a short time in which to state his case--which is the case<br/>
          of the poor, of the <sup>]</sup><sup>and there is</sup> there is an urgency in his preaching<br/>
          wxxxxx so <s>that it</s> It is not a 
            learned (learmed) voice; it is not<br/>
          a 
            courtly (c urtly) voice; it is the voice of a plain man, whose<br/>
          bxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxxtearing down superstition,<br/>
          a voice that does not issues from a<br/>
          before he too goes to join Master Bilney at the faggot.<br/>
          And yet for all his urgency, his severity, he is a man of<br/>
          <sup>a people, a man of humour, of</sup>flesh and blood. He cracks his joke. He tells his story.<br/>
          <sup>He has a [certain?] in [illeg.] for the human</sup> He is a man of the people, with a love of 
            shooting (shotting), with a<br/>
          respect for the gentry. But he sees, as the 
            courtier (courteir) cannot<br/>
          as the poor cannot, what 
            superstition and ignorance (supersition and igno ance) are<br/>
          rife in the land. It is for light and learning that he cries.<br/>
          Give the money he implores that used to be<br/>
          spent on <sup>"</sup>
            pilgrimage (pilgirmage) maters, in trentalls and masses in<br/>
          purgatory matters" to poor mens sons so that they (thatthey) may become<br/>
          scholars. It will come 
            to (tp) pass there txmxmxmxmxx we shall have nothing<br/>
          but a little English divinity , that will bring the realm<br/>
          into a very barbarousness, and utter decay of learning."<br/>
          xxxxx And while 
            the peasants (th peasnts) are starving, and continuing<br/>
          their gross 
            superstitions (supe stitions), the <sup>he sees [illeg.]</sup>
            great (gr at) house is rising.<br/>
          "All the affection of men now adays is in building gay"
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          12<br/>
          and sumptuous houses, it is in setting up and pulling down,<br/>
          and never have they done building."
        </p>
          <p facs="">
            <s>
              <s>Let</s><sup>But</sup> ironically enough, the preacher who was for<br/>
              banishing  and other such papish superstitions<br/>
              was forging the very 
                weapon (weapin) that gave the old 
                minstrels (misntersl)<br/>
              a new lease of life. When he spoke 
                English (Eng ish) in 
                the (hthe) pulpit,<br/>
              when he said the Lords 
                prayer (paryer) in 
                English (Englisg), he was<br/>
              putting 
                English (Ebglish) into high places. He was rescuing it from<br/>
              the jugglers and the bear leders at the back door. He was<br/>
              giving the poets a language which was to bring all<br/>
              the English crowding to the stage <sup>see the 
                mummers (mu mers) acting on 
                the (th) stage.</sup>
            </s>
          </p>
        <p facs="">
          Both Hxxxx xmxmxmxxmxxx <sup> and </sup> the preacher and the<br/>
          chronicler, saw the great 
            house (hous) rising on the ruins of<br/>
          old. Bxmxmxmxmxmxx Each in his own way 
            denounced (deno nced) the<br/>
          gay sumptuous house, <sup>its [illeg.], its [illeg.]</sup>. <s>It is</s> there <s>still</s><sup>today</sup>, standing in<br/>
          its green island of park, separated often from the high road<br/>
          only by a dip in the ground and a low red wall. It dwarfs its<br/>
          neighbours now It looks incongruous, standing among the<br/>
          bungalows and the shops. With its conglomeration of chimneys<br/>
          chapels roofs it looks out of 
            proportion (porportion), 
            stranded (starmded), derelict.<br/>
          Inside all is kept as if Queen Elizabeth were still<br/>
          expected. The 
            upright ( p right) 
            Elizabethan (Elizabthan) chairs stand round the<br/>
          walls. Their 
            fittings and tapestries (ftinges and tapestri s) are not much faded.<br/>
          The great oak tables are heavy and polished. The carved<br/>
          cupboards and chests look 
            brand (ba nd) new. Cut glass chandeliers<br/>
          hang down from 
            the (th) decorated plaster work on 
            the ceiling (th celing).<br/>
          Even the 
            knick knacks (k cki knacks) have 
            survived (survibed)--; the inlaid work box,
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          13
          <s>
            The pear shaped lute on which 
              the (th)  herself once played.<br/>
            Th<s>ir</s> furniture remains; stiff, ornate, 
              fantastic (fanatstic) and<br/>
            uncushioned. There are the very "vardigalls" that roused the<br/>
            preachers wrath. But the 
              Elizabethans themselves (Elizabthans themslves) are silent.
          </s>
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          <s>
            We cannot hear them talking because <sup>this</sup><s>it is to</s> the<br/>
            <sup>them in</sup> 
              rhythm (rhym) of the Bible that they write their familiar prose. <sup>that they are unknown to us</sup><br/>
            There is <s>therefore</s> no little language; no warmth, no gaiety<br/>
            nothing brief, intimate, 
              colloquial (colloqauial) <s>about them</s>.<br/>
            When  writes to  she is a preacher<br/>
            addressing a subordinate. Fear of God and fear of man<br/>
            surround her as with 
              the (th) walls of a dungeon. She 
              admonishes (admonhsies)
          </s>
          <s>s she exhorts.</s> The actual object--a basket of 
            strawberries (strawberris)<br/>
          is approached circuitously 
             (ceremonieously). Greek and Latin<br/>
          come as easily to her pen as a French phrase comes to ours.<br/>
          <s>She</s><sup>They</sup> wraps herself about in a cumbrous garment when she <sup>they</sup> tries<br/>
          to 
            talk (tal) 
            Then (The ) again we cannot 
            hear (haear) the rough English<br/>
          voice that they heard at the back door. the 
            voice (voi) of the<br/>
          mummer and the minstrel. Nor can we see the paths that led<br/>
          to the well and the tree. Robin Hood is gone<br/>
          with all of his 
            merry men (me  y men). <s>This</s><sup>T</sup>he gay and sumptuous house<br/>
          that was <s>O latimer</s> full of oaths and coarseness and also of<br/>
          learning , of 
            courtesy (coutrsey), is an <sup>a lone</sup> isolated house;<br/>
          a house full of furniture and finery but without inhabitants.<br/>
          Bright contrasted colours meet on their faces; scarlet<br/>
          and snow; 
            ebony (enby) and gold; but there is no 
            natural (natual) connection,<br/>
          no common complexion.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          The writer then must be a poet. --the 
            writer (writ) who is
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          14<br/>
          The writer, who is distinct from the minstrel, whose words<br/>
          are printed with a book with his name to it, must be a poet.<br/>
          For when familiar 
            letters (lettres) are written in Biblical prose,<br/>
          there is a limit to what can be put into words. There is a<br/>
          barrier between the sayable and the unsayable. If he cannot<br/>
          talk, he must sing. But though at the beginning of the<br/>
          
            sixteenth (sixeneth) century the printing press has given the poet<br/>
          a name, he is still 
            unspecialised (unspeciliased). He is not wholly writer,<br/>
          wholly musician or wholly painter. It seems possible that<br/>
          the great English art may not be the art of words. He sees<br/>
          acutely what is before him without <sup>the</sup> shadow <sup>or reflection</sup>; his ear is<br/>
          stimulated by the 
            sounds (ouns) of words spoken aloud. He must make<br/>
          words 
            sonorous (sornours), 
            rhythm (rhytm) obvious. since they are to <sup>read</sup><br/>
          be out in company. "I spent most of my time" wrote Lady<br/>
           "in playing at Glecko and hearing <br/>
           read the ... Rivers used to read to me in<br/>
            and Moll Neville in the <br/>
          Further, words must move easily to the lilt 
            of (o) the singing<br/>
          voice, to the sound of lute and virginals. The English<br/>
          sang their songs then, or played them . When London<br/>
          was burning,  noted that hardly one lighter or boat<br/>
          in three that had the goods of a house in it, but there<br/>
          was a pair of virginals in it." Music moved beneath the<br/>
          words. No grammar bound them tightly together. They could<br/>
          be read aloud; danced or sung to; but they could not
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          follow the pace of the speaking voice. They could not<br/>
          
            enter (ent r) into the private world.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
           then--a little man with short hair,<br/>
          a small band and cuffs" standing on the threshold of the<br/>
          "gay and sumptuous house" at  was separate from<br/>
          from the minstrel; from the chronicler; and <s>separate</s> from<br/>
          his audience. They no longer joined in the song and added<br/>
          their own verses to the poem. But the book that had given<br/>
          him a separate 
            existence (existnce) had brought into being a little<br/>
          group of readers. Thaxmxmmxxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxxsx<br/>
          xmxmxmxmxxx It had to find its way into the great room where<br/>
          the gentry sat at leisure when they had hunted and hawked<br/>
          and done the business of their estates. That 
            audience (audeince) at<br/>
          once began to exert its pressure. What is the book that will<br/>
          please my patron ? What is the theme that<br/>
          will recommend itself to ? Whom must I praise, whom<br/>
          may I satirise? At once come into existence some of<br/>
          those innumerable influences 
            that (  at) are to tug, to distort,<br/>
          to thwart; as also they are to 
            stimulate (srimulate) and draw out.<br/>
          The poet is no 
            longer (long r) a nameless wandering voice, but<br/>
          attached to his audience. 
            tethered (tehetred) to one spot and played<br/>
          upon 
            by (my) outside influences. Some are visible to himself<br/>
          only; others show themselves only when time has past.<br/>
          As the book goes out into a 
            larger (larher), a more varied audience<br/>
          these influences become more and more complex. According to<br/>
          its 
            wealth (welaht), its poverty, its education, its ignorance,<br/>
          the public demands what satisfies its own need--poetry,<br/>
          history, instruction, a story to 
            make (makr) them forget the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          16<br/>
          their own drab lives. The 
            thing (t ing) that the writer has to say<br/>
          becomes increasingly cumbered. It is only to be discovered<br/>
          in a flash of recognition-- Thus some say that their beards<br/>
          bristle when they hxmxmxxx 
            come (coke) upon it; others that a<br/>
          thrill runs down the nerves of the thigh. To disengage the<br/>
          song from the effect of the audience becomes as time goes on<br/>
          a task for the critic-- that specially equipped taster<br/>
          who was not yet in existence when the 
             emerged<br/>
          from the <sup>depths</sup> deeps of anonymity.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          Those depths, xxxxx those long years of<br/>
          anonymous minstrelsy, 
            folk song (fo   song), legend and words that had<br/>
          no name attached to them, lay behind him. <sup>Their confusion pressed upon him.</sup> He was conscious<br/>
          of them. "For why a Gods name " he exclaimed "<br/>
          may not we, as else the Greeks, have the kingdom of our<br/>
          own language...." ? He was word conscious; an artist;<br/>
          aware of his medium; that words are not paint, nor music;<br/>
          but have their possibilities; their limitations. To be thus<br/>
          aware the 
            writer (writ) must have a past behind him. To Spenser the<br/>
          golden age was 
            . "Dan Chaucer, well of English<br/>
          undefiled..." He trusted that the infusion sweet<br/>
          Of thine own xxxxxx spirit which doth in me survive"<br/>
          might help him. He looks back to 
            Chaucer (Cahucer); he 
            descends (descneds) from<br/>
          Chaucer. It was Chaucer who gave him the 
            standard (standdard) by which<br/>
          to measure his own 
            works (wor s). But where the modern writer<br/>
          attacks the 
            actual (actul) work of some of the generation that<br/>
          has just gone, making that book the starting point<br/>
          in another direction, Spensers revolt was against no<br/>
          
            particular (particular) writer-- who was there writing English except
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          17<br/>
          
            Chaucer (Cahicer)?-- but 
            against (agianst) the language itself, its decay,<br/>
          since Chaucer, its corruption. Perhaps Chaucers crudity<br/>
          served as an antidote to his own facility. Perhaps too<br/>
          he used 
            the crabbed (th carbbed) old words, not as we now might revert to<br/>
          them to <s>bring back</s><sup>[illeg.]</sup> sharp<s>ness</s> where <sup>when</sup> much use has worn<br/>
          words smooth; but to restrain what was to come. He was, as<br/>
          we cannot be, aware of the future. 
            Everywhere, (E  rywhere,) in 
            ballads (ballds),<br/>
          in talk at the tavern, at the back door, he must have heard<br/>
          something rising, bursting up, from 
            beneath (benaeth). 
            Was ( as) it partly<br/>
          to restrain the coming insurrection that he looked back to<br/>
          the ?
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          <sup>As so often happens it was the attraction of what is opposed that drew  to .</sup><br/> 
          For <sup>them, that</sup>there <s>was no other</s> connection between the 
            <br/>
          Queen and the . <sup>but no [illeg.]</sup>xmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxm<br/>
          xmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxx The one is 
            clear (claer) sharp definite;<br/>
          the other sensuous, sinuous 
            dallying (daalying). The one is direct,<br/>
          about this real man, this real woman, here and now.<br/>
          the other wanders through time which is neither past nor<br/>
          present; 
            through lands (throu nlands) that are neither known nor 
            unknown (unknwon).<br/>
          Unlike  he has 
            ceased (c ased) to believe in 
            giants (ginats).<br/>
          The faith that the nobles had in 1470 <sup>of the real existence of </sup> has 
            turned (tunred) to<br/>
          scepticism. His poem lacks <s>the</s> <sup>some</sup> reality <s>of</s> the <br/>
           <sup>that Malory achieved [illeg.]</sup>. Malory too was 
            behind (ehind) him. <sup>[</sup>But the faith<br/>
          that the old nobles had in the reality of  has<br/>
          turned to scepticism.<sup>]</sup> Where Malory sees directly Spenser sees<br/>
          at a distance. He sees Knights and ladies with regret, with<br/>
          
            desire (dseire), but not with belief. There is 
            no (nos) sharpness in<br/>
          his figures; no edge; no 
            anguish (angusih); no sin; no On the other<br/>
          hand he shows us as 
            Malory (alory) cannot the world surrounding them.<br/>
          He 
            realises (realis s) time and change. And looking back, from a
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          18<br/>
          distance he sees them pictorially; grouped like the<br/>
          figures in a fresco, with the flowers growing at their feet,<br/>
          
            behind (behi d) them marble pillars, 
            trees (tree s) with bright birds, and<br/>
          the libbard and the lion roaming or couchant. There is<br/>
          no tension; no direction; but always movement,<br/>
          as the metre flings its curve of sound, to break, like a<br/>
          wave on the same place, and like a wave to withdraw, to<br/>
          fill again. Folded in this 
            incantation (intation) we 
            drowse (drwose) and<br/>
          and sleep; bxmxmxmxmxx yet 
            always (alwys) see through the 
            waters (w ters),<br/>
          something ixmxmxmxmxmxmxx <sup>[irradiated?]</sup> lit up.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          Spenser 
            standing on the (standinn othe) threshold of the great house<br/>
          is half in 
            shadow (shdow), half in light, xxx Half is still unrealised<br/>
          <sup>For </sup>He cannot confine emotions within <s>one body</s> <sup>[himself?]</sup>. He must<br/>
          symbolise, 
            exteriorise (exterirorise). 
            Jealousy (Jealous) is not a passion to issue<br/>
          on actual lips. He must float it outwards; make it 
            abstract (abtsract);<br/>
          give it a symbolical shape. He cannot speak through the<br/>
          mouths of 
            individuals (indivisuals). The body 
            containing (contianing) within itself<br/>
          all of the passions is still sunk in shadow. But the other half<br/>
          of him is in the light. He is aware of his art as 
            Chaucer (Cahucer)<br/>
          was mot, nor , nor Malory. His is no longer a<br/>
          wandering voice, but 
            the (th) voice of a man practising an art,<br/>
          asking for recognition, and bitterly conscious of his<br/>
          separation <sup>relation</sup> from the world, of the worlds scorn.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          19<br/>
          Had the poet 
            remained (r mained) in the great room, 
            proffering (p offering) his<br/>
          book to the little group of readers, English poetry might 
            have (hav)<br/>
          remained book poetry, read aloud; <sup>[</sup>a recollection; a reflection<br/>
          
            something (som hing) rxmxmxmxxx heard by the leisured listening in the<br/>
          great room <s>to a voice reading aloud.</s> But there was the<br/>
          other voicel the voice at the back door. Spenser had heard it<br/>
          / He recalled the voice of "
            minstrels (misntrels) making goodly 
            merriment (merrimen)<br/>
          With wanton bards and 
            rhymers (erhyjers) impudent." he had been, it<br/>
          is said, at the 
            pageant (pagenat) at  when, to amuse the<br/>
          
            , an old story was staged <sup>&amp; had [heard?] the player to [suggest?] a [illeg.]</sup>. He had seen "the player<br/>
          
            dressed (drssed) in green", the --the old play that the peasants acted<br/>
          when 
            spring (srping) came and to placate the earth, the mummer hung<br/>
          himself with green leaves.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          <sup>Like other great people the queen must have her diversion.</sup>xmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxx The 
            Queen (Qyeen) must have her 
            minstrels (minstresl). <sup>But English was coming to court.</sup><br/>
          Tmxmxmxmx Whenever the Queen went to the 
            great (g eat) house,<br/>
          a   the minstrels acted before her <sup>repeat</sup>. 
            Ironically (Irnoically) enough,<br/>
          the preacher who was for banishing Robin Hood and <s>such</s><br/>
          <s>mummeries</s>, had himself forged the very weapon that gave<br/>
          the old minstrels a new leash of life. When Latimer said the<br/>
           in English at the beginning and the 
            end (endd) of his<br/>
          sermons he was putting English into high places. He was<br/>
          rescuing it from the back door. He was teaching the nobles<br/>
          and the peasants to use <sup>repeat</sup> their mother tongue. He was making<br/>
          that alliance between the <s>nobles and the peasants</s> that was<br/>
          
            necessary (nesscary) were they to come together in 
            the playhouse (theplayhouse).<br/>
          And already, even while the old mummers 
            came (ca e) before the<br/>
          Queen, dressed in leaves at Kenilworth, the house was being<br/>
          built which was to give the minstrel a lodging;<br/>
          which was to give him a name. a <sup>centre</sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          20<br/>
          and the 
            peasants (peasnts) to respect their mother tongue. He was making<br/>
          it possible for the gentry and the commons to sit together<br/>
          in one house listening to a play.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          For the wandering minstrels, driven from the Church,<br/>
          now taking up their pitch in the market place or in the<br/>
          yard of an Inn had by 1576 somehow 
            possessed (posssed) themselves of a<br/>
          house. <sup>[illeg.]</sup> It was In 
            1591 (i59i) the playhouse in  needed<br/>
          rebuilding. 
            Planks (Pla ks) and nails and hinges and timber were<br/>
          brought to . 
            Carpenters (Crrpentrs) and painters were hired.<br/>
          and the 
            sums (s ms) spent on the rebuilding were entered at last<br/>
          by  in his vellum covered book. It was a wooden<br/>
          house, part open to the air, part thatched. It stood in<br/>
          Southwark, next the   and <br/>
          "
            recognised (regongise) stews."<s>The  was infested with hogs.</s><br/>
          The contrast between town and 
            country (countru), judging by <br/>
          , was sharp. There, in one fretted mass of spires and<br/>
          little 
            streets (stretts), lay the . But 
            grass fields (gras fileds) rose behind it<br/>
          From Southwark there 
            was (w s) a view of 
            open (ppen) country. Fields<br/>
          and hills came close down to the stews on the Bankside.<br/>
          And the Bankside was infested with hogs.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          The house 
            according (accroding) to , could 
            hold (gold)<br/>
          three 
            thousand (thousnad) people. Most paid one penny to stand in<br/>
          the open; twopence secured a seat; sixpence was the price of<br/>
          a seat under cover. The audience came 
            flocking (flcking) across the<br/>
          
            river (roiver). For what other 
            amusement (amusment) was there, a contemporary<br/>
          asked, of an afternoon for the "numbers of captains and<br/>
          
            soldiers (soliders) about London" Only the 
            amusements (amusments) that the preachers<br/>
          so furiously 
            denounced (denouned); carding, dicing, gaming, the following<br/>
          of harlots and drink. The common people came from the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          21<br/>
          
            over (ovet) the river from the crowded festering little<br/>
          streets round , where the dead bodies smelt so strong<br/>
          They came in such nukmbers that the watermen lived on their<br/>
          fares. <sup>they came in [illeg.] as [illeg.] &amp; [inquisitive?]</sup>. The flag flew; the trumpets sounded, and at about<br/>
          half past two in the afternoon, the audience crowded into<br/>
          the playhouse. In cloud or in sun shine they saw<br/>
          actors issue from the doors, richly dressed in the taffetas<br/>
          and tinsels, in the satin doublets and hose laid thick<br/>
          with gold lace that 
             entered in his book. or,<br/>
          according to one spectator, dressedin the cast off robes<br/>
          of the nobles sold by their servants. They were splendidly<br/>
          dressed. But there was no scenery. The sun beat or the rain<br/>
          
            poured (poi ured) upon the common people standing in the yard.<br/>
          Then the actor <sup>King</sup> spoke:
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            Brother 
              Cosroe (Cosore), I find myself aggrieved<br/>
            Yet insufficient to express the same;<br/>
            For it requireth a great and thundering speech
          
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          At last one man 
            speaks (s  aks) in his own person. The wandering 
            voices (voice)<br/>
          are collected, embodied. There is no abstraction any longer.<br/>
          All is visible, audible tangible in the light of the present<br/>
          moment. The world takes shape 
            behind (behin) him. Egypt and Libya<br/>
          and Persia and Greece rise up. Kings and Emperors<br/>
          stride forth. Like great moths shaking their wings still<br/>
          damp and creased they 
            unfurl (unfrul) the great 
            sentences (senetences), the absurd<br/>
          
            hyperboles (hypberloes).
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            The spring is withered by your smothering host<br/>
            For neither rain 
              can (cam) fall upon the earth<br/>
            nor sun reflex his virtuous beams thereon,<br/>
            The ground is mantled with such multitudes.
          
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          22<br/>
          The 
            utmost (ut  st) stretch of words can 
            scarcely (scarely) give body to this<br/>
          vast universe that is struggling into exmxmxmxx being.<br/>
          Words mount; pile on top of each other; over balance and<br/>
          tumble. Great names clash their cymbals. If, blown on this<br/>
          pressure, the poet veers aside
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            So poets say my lord<br/>
            And 'tis a pretty toy to be a poet
          
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          he is urged on. There is no pause, no shade. Armies trample;<br/>
          horses neigh; Battles are fought. Blood flows. Over all<br/>
          the Gods are seated on their thrones. The Gods 
            will exact (willexact)<br/>
          tribute. Meanwhile let us boast:
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            Our souls, whose faculties can comprehend<br/>
            The wondrous architecture of the world,<br/>
            And measure [the] very wandering 
              planets (p anets) course,<br/>
            Still climbing after knowledge infinite,<br/>
            And always moving as the restless 
              spheres (psheres),<br/>
            Will us to wear ourselves, and never rest...
          
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          Then 
            suddenly (su denly) the 
            triumph (truimu triumph) parts 
            asunder (ausnder)<br/>
          the poet changes 
            his (is) tune
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            What is beauty, saith my sufferings then?<br/>
            If all the pens that 
              ever poets (everpoets) held,<br/>
            Had fed the feelings of their masters thoughts.....<br/>
            If these had made one poems period<br/>
            And all combined in beautys wemxmxmxx worthiness,<br/>
            Yet should there hover in their restless heads<br/>
            One thought, one 
              grace (gace), one wonder, at the least,<br/>
            Which into words no virtue can digest.
          
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          22
          
            The spring is hindered by your smothering host,<br/>
            For neither rain can fall upon the earth,<br/>
            Nor sun reflex his 
              virtuous (virtuo s) beams thereon<br/>
            The ground is mantled with such multitudes.
          
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          The utmost stretch of words can 
            scarcely (scarely) give<br/>
          body <sup>[illeg.]</sup> to the this vast universe that is struggling into<br/>
          being. Words mount; pile on top of each<br/>
          other.xxxx great names clash and rebound. And<br/>
          And <sup>If</sup> 
            under (unde) the stress and pressure of this excitement,<br/>
          the poet can veer aside <sup>for [illeg.]</sup>;  <sup>with that</sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            So poets say my lord,<br/>
            And 'tis a pretty toy to be a poet--
          
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          <sup>[illeg.]</sup> this interjection cuts deep. <sup>[s?]he must press on.</sup> <s>Could he stop, it</s> would cut<br/>
          <s>deeper</s>. But there is 
            no (ni) pause, no shade. <s>The</s> armies trample;<br/>
          horses neigh; Battles are fought; Blood flows. Yet over this<br/>
          
            multitudinous (multitudionous) 
            splendour (spnedour) 
            broods (brrods) 
            tragedy (trag dy). <sup>man exalts &amp; </sup>The Gods are<br/>
          on their thrones. Thxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxxxthe Gods will exact<br/>
          
            tribute (trib te). But let us triumph and boast:
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            Our souls, whose faculties can comprehend<br/>
            The 
              wondrous (wondr us) architecture of the world,<br/>
            And measure every wandering planets course,<br/>
            Still climbing after knowledge infinite,<br/>
            And always moving as the restless spheres,<br/>
            Will to us wear ourselves, and never rest.....
          
          Then, <sup>,</sup> <sup>suddenly</sup> the boast and 
            the triumph (thetirumph) part asunder; and the poet<br/>
          changes his note:
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          
            What is beauty saith my sufferings, then?<br/>
            If all the pens that ever poets held<br/>
            Had fed the feelings of their masters thoughts
          
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          23<br/>
          .....
          If these 
            had (h d) made one poems period,<br/>
          And all combined 
            in (i ) beautys worthiness<br/>
          Yet should there hover in their restless heads<br/>
          One thought, one grace, one wonder at the 
            least (lleast)<br/>
          Which into words no virtue can digest.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          Lovely as the words are <sup>;</sup>  they break the current <sup>, </sup><sup>suddenly the mind slides over points [illeg.]</sup><br/>
          The poet has <sup>[illeg.]</sup> separated himself from the <s>breath of the</s><br/>
          audience. xtmxsmamxamxsxgmxat <sup>&amp; [illeg.]</sup> He cannot as yet<br/>
          make use of his 
            characters (characters); he takes leave of them when he<br/>
          speaks thus. The xmxmxmxx play is still partly the work of <sup>For the play is</sup><br/>
          the 
            undifferentiated (undifferentaited) audience. It is 
            ensured (insored) by the common<br/>
          voice, demanding great names; great deeds and simple outlines<br/>
          not the single 
            subtlety (suntely)
            of (one) one soul. <sup>He has not [subdued?] the audience so that they can say [illeg.] have to say</sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          2xxx 24
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          <s>Somehow</s>, lovely as they are, the words break the current. <sup>there is a jolt at the points &amp; the [illeg.]</sup><br/>
          To speak them the poet has separated himself from his<br/>
          actors. He cannot as yet, make use of them <sup>speak them [illeg.]</sup> to 
            speak (s eak) certain<br/>
          thoughts. The play is still mainly 
            the (th)work of the<br/>
          
            undifferentiated (undiifferantaited) 
            audience (audeince), demanding great names;<br/>
          great deeds; simple outlines, and not the single subtlety<br/>
          of one soul. <sup>There is some [bear?]</sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          <sup>The play</sup>  was anonymous. That fact is by itself<br/>
          enough to show largely how the play was a common product,<br/>
          written by one hand, but so moulded in 
            transition (tranition) from the<br/>
          written to the spoken that the author had no sense of<br/>
          property in it. It was half the work of the audience. <sup> But</sup><br/>
          yet the audience is 
            dumb (sdumb). That silence is one of 
            the (th) deep<br/>
          gulfs that lies between us and the 
            Elizabethan (Elizabetahn) play.<br/>
          Fifteen hundred people, Dr 
            Greg (Greg) says, hexmxxx<br/>
          went to the play, for the most part, presumably,<br/>
          in the penny part of the house, And <s>these</s> <sup>T</sup>he presence<br/>
          
            of (o) these apprentices, soldiers and citizens is obvious.<br/>
          It draws up the extravagance the hyperbole as a sheet of<br/>
          paper draws up a fire. It causes that glow that speed that<br/>
          audacity which make the writer capable of great strides and<br/>
          vast audacities beyond his private reach. Yet the<br/>
          audience says nothing . It makes no comment. It sits silent.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          To understand that silence 
            we (w) must compare it
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="">
          with 
            our (theour) own attitude say at the 
             ballet<br/>
          or at the 
             in their early days. A new art comes upon us<br/>
          so suddenly, so 
            surprisingly (surprisningly) that we are silent,<br/>
          recognising something true, which we <sup>recognise but</sup> cannot measure.<br/>
          To the Elizabethans, after the long silence of England,<br/>
          the <sup>hidden</sup> power of words to say what was in them must have been<br/>
          overwhelming. After ages of of scattered hints, a few<br/>
          wild songs, here and there a 
            chronicle (chornicle) or a 
            history (hitsiry), they<br/>
          suddenly came <sup>to [illeg.]</sup> out into the open and saw human life as it is<br/>
          at this moment. They saw themselves. It is a curious inversion<br/>
          We <s>see</s> realise the blood flesh and blood of the Elizabethans<br/>
          because we see it in the 
            reflected (r fl cted) in the drama.<br/>
          We neither see nor hear them in person; we 
            see (s ee) and hear<br/>
          them in the reflection. But if the audience sat silent<br/>
          as they saw 
            themselves (themslves) there on the stage between the<br/>
          stews, they <sup>but</sup> they saw themselves with rapture. Again and again<br/>
          the  protested against the intoxication<br/>
          that was 
            brewed (b rewed) in the Playhouse. The attraction was<br/>
          irresistible. There at the Rose, at the  at the <br/>
          men and women who had
            never seen (neverseen) 
            themselves (themslves) yet, whose only<br/>
          
            reading (readung) was 
            history (histoy) or sermons, or some old
            chronicle (chonicle) of<br/>
          Knights and ladies, , and perhaps could not even read,<br/>
          but spent all their days struggling, loving, 
            cheating (chaeting),<br/>
          burrowing in the little festering streets 
            round (rounf) ,<br/>
          saw their very own lives composed, 
            adored (adoredn), and heard at<br/>
          
            last (kast) 
            their (thier) dreams their 
            aspirations (aspriarions) their satires their<br/>
          profanities spoken out loud in poetry.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          The play then owes its extravagance, and its riot,<br/>
          and its plot and its glow to the 
            audience (audie ce) in the penny seats.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>