<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M54, 3 of 11. [Anon: for coins. When he was walking...]. Typescript fragment, 4 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m54-3</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M54, 3 of 11. [for coins. When he was walking...]. Typescript fragment, 4 fols.</p>
            <p>N.B.: This is one of eleven sub-fragments identified the Berg Collection's M54. [Anon: The printing press brought the past into existence...]. Typescript fragments, unsigned and undated, 35 fols. I have determined pagination and sequencing based on subject matter. M54 as curated by the Berg Collection is available as part of 'The Digital Anon' and can be found at [LINK].</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-1/876,84,209,139/full/0/default.tif">
          9
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-1/840,220,1882,3054/full/0/default.tif">
          for coins. When he was walking in xxx the 
           garden, " the poor come 
            kkocking (knocking) at the gate
          and my man says "Sir, there is some one at the gate would
          speak with 
            oyuyou ()." So he laid aside his book and went
          out among the poor. He visited them in their hovels. He
          noted their poverty. He saw the poor man unable now
          to buy a goose, for the great lords were enclosing the
          fields. He went to the great man and found him still in
          bed, after his hunting 
            anf hid (and his) hawking. He saw the poor 
            sutis (suitors)
          waiting 
            ho (hour) in the hall to get their suit 
            herad (heard).
          These were the casees that he brought before 
          In a voice that 
            sumbles (stumbles) and uses the old language of
          his fathers house, ))" they say in my country to the hogs
          mingle mangle, cum pur, cum pur" --- he brought into the
          light of day the hxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmx
          xmxmxmxmxmxxx the harlot going to execution at 
          and saying as she went "that 
             f (if) good fellows had kept
          touch with her, she had not bin at this time in that case."
          He saw the curates   in their 
            velevet (velvet) shoes and slippers
          meet to dance the morris dance. And the fine ladies
          dressed in 
            vardinaglls (vardingalls) with their hair puffed out in tussocks
          He saw the 
            yo ng (young) men given over in the s t to gulling 
            drinm ig (drinking)
          and whoring. The young men dice away their thrift; Instead of
          shooting with the long 
             ow (bow) they their sports are lost
          turned into bowling 
            drinming (drinking) and whoring. He And the poor
          are still going on pilgrimages, setting up candles and
          
            wirshipping (worshipping) pigs bones. <sup>[illeg.]</sup> He casts the light of the new
          learning upon the the old superstitions. He too, until he
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-3/984,80,166,154/full/0/default.tif">
          10
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-3/906,244,1826,2790/full/0/default.tif">
          thirty "had walked in the shadow of 
            d ath (death)." It was Master
           at 
             who 
            ppened (opened) his eyes; Master Bilney
          who went about among the poor and the 
            sivk (sick),
          Master Bilney heard him preach 
            agianst (against)  and his
          opinons. and desired me for Gods sake to hear his 
            confessio (confession)
          "did so; and to say the very truth, by his confession
          I learnt ed more than for many 
            yeares (yeares). With Bilney he 
            vi ted (visited)
          the 
            prisones (prisoners) in the Tower at Cambridge, for he was ever 
            visig (visiting)
          
            pirsoners (prisoners) 
            andsick (and sick) folk. There was a woman who had killed
          her child. And  brought her story before King
           as he talked with him after the sermon in
          the gallery. and he got her 
            padrdon (pardon). Master Bilney was burnt;
          so it may wi be, he will be burnt. 
            eanehile (Meanwhile) he will speak
          the truth so that the 
            simp le (simple) can understand. In their own
          tongue. Standing on the verge of the 
            Elizabetha (Elizabethan) age,
          he saw, as  saw, the great buildings rise on the
          foundations of the old. "There 
            ws (was) never such buildings then
          as 
            if (is) now, planting, nor marrying." And yet the 
            Englis (English) are
          still sunk in 
            supe stition (superstition). Give 
            thmoey (the money) he implores that          
          was wont to bestow on 
            pilgrimagesmatters (pilgrimages matters), in trentalls
          in masses, in purgatory matters" to poor men sons so that
          they may become 
            schlars (scholars). "There be now none but greate mens
          sons in colleges." It will come to pass that
          
            we 
              shallhave (shall have) nothing but a little 
              Ebglish (English) divinity, that will
            bring the realm into a very barbarousness, and utter
            decay of learning."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-3/1002,3040,1710,394/full/0/default.tif">
          This was the voice of the new 
            lraning (learning), the 
            vo ce (voice)
          that ousted 
            superstiti,n (superstition), the voice of reason, charity, common
          sense. But it was by an 
            irnoy (irony) ironically enough, the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-5/877,84,145,166/full/0/default.tif">
          11
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-5/863,206,1809,770/full/0/default.tif">
          the preacher who was for banishing and such
          
            supersitions (superstitions) was forging the very weapon 
            theat (that) give the old
          
            mibstrels (minstrels) a new lease of life. <s>His English.</s> When he
          said the  at the beginning and at
          theend of his 
            ermon (sermon) he was putting English intpo high places.
          He was rescuing it from the back door. He was teaching
          Spenser and 
            Shakespere (Shakespeare) how to write.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-5/823,966,1813,1982/full/0/default.tif">
          Both Harrison and Latimer see the very same house <sup>[The house was being?]</sup>
          the 
            hose (house) that was being built on the foundations of the
          old house. We can still see the great Elizabethan house
          whose building was to both preacher and antiquary a
          sign of txmxmxmxmxmxmxmxxx luxury. in all its glory.
          There it is, standing in its green island of Park 
            seapareted (separated)
          often from the high road by only a 
            d p (dip) in the ground and a
          low red wall. With its 
            congloeration (conglomeration) of roofs and chapels
          and 
            chimeys (chimneys) 
            i (it) dwarfs its 
            neighboyrs (neighbours). Inside all is kept as
          if the Queen Elizabeth were expected. The upright 
            Elizabetahn (Elizabethan)
          chairs stand round the walls. Their 
            ftinges (fittings) and tapestry
          are not much faded. The great oak tables are heavy
          and polished. The 
            carbed (carved) chairs and cupboards look 
            barnd (brand)
          new. The floor is strewn with carpets; cut glass chandeliers
          hang down from the decorated 
            pl ter (plaster) work on the 
            celing (ceiling).
          Even knick knacks 
            ha v (have) survived; the inlaid work box,
          the and the pear shaped 
            l te (lute) on which the Queen once
          played.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-5/883,2940,1697,398/full/0/default.tif">
          But the Elizabethans themselves are silent. Only
          the furniture remains,, stiff and ornate, fantastic and
          
            uncushioned (uncushioned).
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-7/877,110,205,198/full/0/default.tif">
          12
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-3/m54-3-7/915,272,1761,2658/full/0/default.tif">
          Latimer had read the 
            Lord (Lord's) Prayer in English. The Bible
          was printed in English. And, using the prose of the bible
          when they write prose, the 
            Elixabethans (Elizabethans) are 
            unknwon (unknown) to us.
          When in some extremity of anguish or fear they take up the
          pen they use the 
            rhyms (rhythms) of the Bible. 
            Itis (It is) a garment only
          to be worn when the mind is in the right 
            attidtue (attitude). They can
          say nothing simple, subtle, or 
            breif (brief). At  Lady
           sat writing to . But her letters are like
          
            seroms (sermons), or 
            satte doucments (state documents), intricate, involved,
          circumtutious. She is a counsellor admonishing a subordinate;
          She 
            e hosrts (exhorts) God keep us sound in the faith
          and send us health and a care to please God before all."
          She admonishes Be not speedy of speech, nor talk
          
            suuddenly (suddenly), 
            discrteion (discretion)
            requieth (requireth) and that
          soberly then..." If she has to descend to an actual object
          a basket of 
            starwberries (strawberries) it is with c dark 
            insintuat ons (insinuations).
          Greek and 
            atin (Latin) come as easily to her pen as
          English. There is no 
            gaity (gaiety), no freedom no 
            familairty (familiarity)
          in this world. Fear of God, 
            suspciion (suspicion) of man surround
          the writer as with the 
            wlls (walls) of a dungeon. The wall may
          conceal a Lady Ann 
            whois (who is)merry and gay; it may <s>conceal</s>
          must 
            cobneceal (conceal) passion, laughter and sorrow;
          but no one can tell who it is that lives on the other side
          of the wall of formal 
            langauge (language).
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>