<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M110 [The Reader: Spenser with his eye upon the reader in the great room.]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 5p.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m110</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M110 [The Reader: Spenser with his eye upon the reader in the great room.]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 5p.</p>
            <p>Paginated 26-30. On verso of p. 29, a fragment from Between the Acts, paginated 186.</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-1/926,98,125,123/full/0/default.jpg">
          26
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-1/939,220,1666,220/full/0/default.jpg">
           with his eye upon the reader in the great room.<br/>
          Yet the audience for all its size and compulsion is silent.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-1/595,180,443,540/full/0/default.jpg">
          <sup>
            If we<br/>
            could (cd.) measure<br/>
            the effect<br/>
            of the audience<br/>
            we should (shd.)<br/>
            have a hold<br/>
            upon the<br/>
            play.
          </sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-1/923,436,1754,1660/full/0/default.jpg">
          That is one of the deep gulfs that lies between us<br/>
          and the play. They crowd there; daily; but they neither<br/>
          
            praise (priase) nor blame. We must compare it with our 
            own (won) 
            silence (sielnce)<br/>
          at the  or the <br/>
          A new art comes upon us so 
            surprisingly (surpinsgly) that we sit<br/>
          silent, recognising what we cannot measure.<br/>
          To the Elizabethans the expressive power of words<br/>
          after their long inadequacy 
            must (ust) have been overwhelming.<br/>
          There at the  or at the  men and women whose only<br/>
          reading had been the Bible or some old 
            chronicle (chonicle) came out<br/>
          into the light of the present moment. They saw themselves<br/>
          splendidly dressed. They heard 
            themselves (themslves) saying out loud<br/>
          what they had never said yet. They heard their aspirations,<br/>
          their profanities, their 
            ribaldries (ribaldires) spoken out loud by human<br/>
          voices in poetry.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          <sup/>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-1/859,2128,1754,1220/full/0/default.jpg">
          The play then owes its hyperbole to the audience in the<br/>
          penny seats. At their command it is 
            violent (vio;ent); it xmxmxmmxmx<br/>
          it is coarse; it is poexxx xmxmxmxm a parody, of actual<br/>
          facts. like our own detective stories and best sellers<br/>
          a 
            parody (paody) a 
            transformation (trasnformation) of actual fact. But in the seats<br/>
          in the covered part of the house, there were nobles, rulers,<br/>
          scholars. Their 
            silence (silenc) is harder to explain. For they were<br/>
          
            readers (redares); they had the Latins and the Greeks at the back<br/>
          of their minds. How could it have been that the trained<br/>
          taste of such 
            spectators (speactoars) received the extraordinary<br/>
          illumination of these English plays with no more comment
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-1/526,3010,518,434/full/0/default.jpg">
          <sup>
            said nothing<br/>
            about the<br/>
            [revelation?],<br/>
            was not<br/>
            outraged, by<br/>
            an excited<br/>
            - as seems to be the <s>common</s> reader to a [illeg.] 
          </sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-3/871,36,203,212/full/0/default.jpg">
          27
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-3/915,196,1667,332/full/0/default.jpg">
          How can it have been that they made no critical comment<br/>
          upon this extraordinary xmxmxmxmxmxmmxx revelation of this new<br/>
          art?
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-3/807,528,1907,1756/full/0/default.jpg">
          Perhaps  in his essays supplies a reason.<br/>
          "These things be but toyes" he wrote in the essay called<br/>
           To the aristocratic scholar (sch lar)<br/>
          the players were still only mountebanks (mo ntebanks) bear leaders and<br/>
          acrobats. They spoke in the vulgar tongue. Off the stage<br/>
          they lived in the heart of darkness.  lying on the<br/>
          bed in Deptford reached out and stabbed <sup> in the head</sup><br/>
          <sup>whoever</sup> in the back. Mr <sup>Ingram gave Marlowe a mortal wound</sup> then drove his dagger through<br/>
          Marlowe's (Marloews) eye (eeeye) <sup>over his right eye</sup>.  S  through the<br/>
          body with a sword that cost three and sixpence. So complete<br/>
          was bacons contempt for this underworld that he could be<br/>
          tolerant. The stage is more beholding to Love than the<br/>
          Life of Man..... great spirits and great businesses do keep<br/>
          out of [this? their?] (thid) weak passion." The proper place for the wak<br/>
          weak passion was the stage, for love leads to speaking in<br/>
          perpetual hyperbole.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-3/815,2296,1907,892/full/0/default.jpg">
          The proper topic (tipic) of discussion in the upper (upp r) world<br/>
          was the life of man.   The titles (tiles)of the Essays enumerate (enurmate)<br/>
          enumerate (enurmarte) those topics. "Of Truth. Of Death. Of Unity in<br/>
          Religion. Of Revenge. Of Simulation and Dissimulation.<br/>
          Those were the subjects (subjactes) that the rulers discussed at<br/>
          their high tables. The sediment of that conversation is in<br/>
          the rich deposits of the essays. He is concerned with the<br/>
          great world of action; with government; with the tortuous
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-5/861,30,161,202/full/0/default.jpg">
          28
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-5/831,196,1857,1020/full/0/default.jpg">
          nature of Princes; with the arts by which rulers can sway,<br/>
          can coax, and can supress. He lives 
            entirely (netirely) in the<br/>
          world of great spirits and great business. The common people<br/>
          is contemptible. "The master of superstition is the 
            People (Peopoe).<br/>
          Praise "if it be from the common people, it is 
            commonly (commnoly)
          
            false and naught. The lowest virtues draw 
              praise (priase) from them;<br/>
            the middle virtues work in them 
              Astonishment (Astonihsment); and admiration;<br/>
            but of the highest vertues they have no sense or 
              perceiving (perceibging)<br/>
            at all..."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          <sup>
            <br/>
            <br/>
            <br/>
            
          </sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-5/823,1212,1865,1108/full/0/default.jpg">
          The soul that walked between delicate groves keeps to a<br/>
          narrow path between hedges. While  ranged the world.<br/>
          
            mixing (micing) garrulously with everyone, and speculating freely,<br/>
           kept to the narrow path. Yet even in the shade<br/>
          his thought is embodied. His deep meditations are given 
            visible (visibe)<br/>
          xxxxx concrete form. "Nay 
            retire (bretire) men cannot when they would:
            
              neither will they when it were reason; 
                but (bu) are 
                impatient (impateint)<br/>
              of privateness even in age and sickness which require the<br/>
              Shadow; Like old Townsmen that will still be sitting at 
                their (ther)<br/>
              street door, though thereby they offer Age to scorn."
            
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          Even in the delicate grove thought is coloured.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-5/507,2348,1834,236/full/0/default.jpg">
          <sup>
            
            The <hi xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">colours</hi> that <s>show</s> shew best by candlelight, are:<br/>
            white, carnation, &amp; a kinde of sea-water green
          </sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-5/827,2624,1834,644/full/0/default.jpg">
          His contempt was 
            for (fr) hyperbole; not for the art of speech.<br/>
          He was teaching the ranting players to speak slowly, closely<br/>
          subtly. He was proving that there is another kind of poetry,<br/>
          
            the poetry (thepoetry) of prose. He was doing his part to bring the 
            critical (critic) <sup>share in bringing the shade</sup><br/>
          faculty into being. <sup>prose of the mind</sup> He was making an end of anonymity. <sup>There by [making?] </sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-7/858,128,270,298/full/0/default.jpg">
          xxx<br/>
          29
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-7/848,416,1708,1828/full/0/default.jpg">
          Anonymity was a great possession. It gave the early<br/>
          writing a general nature. It gave us the 
            ballads (ballds); it<br/>
          gave us the songs. It allowed us to know nothing of the<br/>
          mans name.  had great privileges. He is not<br/>
          resopnsible. He is not self conscious. He can borrow.<br/>
          He can repeat. He can say what 
            every (very) one feels.<br/>
          No one asks that he shall stamp his own name on his work.<br/>
          He keeps at a distance from the present moment.<br/>
          Anon the lyric poet repeats over and over again<br/>
          that flowers fade; that death is the 
            end (ned). He is never<br/>
          tired of celebrating red roses and white breasts.<br/>
          The anonymous playwright has like the singer this nameless<br/>
          vitality, 
            something (somwthing) drawn from the crowd in the penny<br/>
          seats and not 
            yet (yey) dead in ourselves. For we too become<br/>
          anonymous 
            and (nand) forget something that we have learnt<br/>
          in reading the 
            plays (p;ays) that no one has 
            troubled (troub led) to set a<br/>
          name to.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-7/876,2260,1756,1220/full/0/default.jpg">
          But at some point there comes a break when anonymity<br/>
          withdraws. It comes presumably when the 
            playwright (playwrgight) has<br/>
          
            absorbed (abosrbed) the 
            contribution (contrbution) of the audience; and returns it<br/>
          to them in a single figure <s>which is individual</s>. There is a<br/>
          moment in <s>play 
            after (aft) play</s> when the audience is no longer<br/>
          master of the playwright; yet is not separate from him.<br/>
          A common life still unites them, but the playwright becomes<br/>
          increasingly diminant. This separation comes fitfully.<br/>
          Now we say He is speaking our woxmxmxx thoughts.
          
            
              O (NoO) God, O God that it were possible<br/>
            To undo 
              things (thin s) done; to call back yesterday.
          
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-8/893,125,183,163/full/0/default.jpg">
          186
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-8/875,240,1763,356/full/0/default.jpg">
          "But we neednt have been to all that trouble," she <sup/><br/>
          continued "making the Barn ready, for it didnt rain this<br/>
          year"
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-8/907,580,1763,356/full/0/default.jpg">
          "This year, last year, next year, never..." muttered<br/>
          old . "Tinker, tailor, soldier, sailor..." He was<br/>
          talking in his sleep.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-8/871,924,1859,540/full/0/default.jpg">
          Lucy slipped her letter into its envelop<sup>e</sup>. It was time<br/>
          to read her boo<sup>k</sup>---the . She had lost her<br/>
          place. She looked at the pictures; mammoths and mastodons,<br/>
          and prehistoric birds. Then she found the page where she<br/>
          had stopped.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-8/839,1460,1859,684/full/0/default.jpg">
          The darkness had 
            increased (incrased), and it was cold. With a little<br/>
          shiver, Mrs Swithin drew her sequin 
            shawl (shalw) about hew shoulders<br/>
          She was too deep in the story to ask for the window to be<br/>
          shut. "London" said the author "
            was (a s) then a swamp...
          
            Thick groves of trees covered the land, and on the top<br/>
            oftheir matted branches, birds sang..."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-8/851,2116,1859,788/full/0/default.jpg">
          The great square of the window showed only sky now.<br/>
          It was <sup>a </sup> losing its light; it was <s>svere</s> <sup>severe</sup> <s>and</s> stone xxxxx<br/>
          blue. The shadow crept over Bartholomews face. He looked<br/>
          leafless, spectral. As a dog shudders its skin, his skin<br/>
          shuddered. He rose, shook himself, glared at nothing,<br/>
          and stalked from the room. They hard the  paws padding<br/>
          on the carpet behind him.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-8/835,2888,1835,444/full/0/default.jpg">
          Lucy turned the page quickly, guiltily,<br/>
          like a <sup>c</sup>hild who will be told to go to bed before it 
            reaches (raches)<br/>
          the end of the chapter. Pre-historic man, she read, half<br/>
          human, half monster, rose from his semi-crouching position
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-9/899,70,177,154/full/0/default.jpg">
          30
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-9/895,224,1763,868/full/0/default.jpg">
          Now we note the beauty of the words.<br/>
          But often it is a suspended, derelict beauty. Chaos 
            intervenes (inter)<br/>
          
            intervenes (venes). The 
            relation (rl ation) of part to part is outraged.<br/>
          The balance is imperfect. Here is profusion; there bareness.<br/>
          The 
            anonymous (anony ous) playwright is irresponsible. He cares nothing<br/>
          has no conscieince about truth; he cares only for the plot.<br/>
          We are left in the end without an end. The emotion is e<br/>
          wasted.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m110/m110-9/831,1088,1859,1756/full/0/default.jpg">
          But 
            gradually (graudally) the mist withdraws. So many 
            playwrights (playwrgihts)<br/>
          are 
            exploring (explroing) So many private people are pressing up<br/>
          their weight of 
            unexpressed (unepxpressed) emotion upon the writers<br/>
          
            consciousness (conscious ess). Country squires are finding 
            themselves (themsleves) able<br/>
          to say what they think without quoting .<br/>
          The 
            curtain (curatin) rises 
            incessantly (incesaantly) upon play after play.<br/>
          <sup>Every Each time, with [illeg.] it rises upon a more complex, <s>highly</s> matured drama.</sup><br/>
          After it has risen again and again it rises finally upon<br/>
          upon the completely embodied; and upon the completely<br/>
          controlled. It rises upon  and  and <br/>
          and . Finally it rises upon . But the play<br/>
          has outgrown the uncovered theatre where the sun beats and<br/>
          the rain pours. The theatre must be replaced<br/>
          by the theatre of the brain.  is replaced by the man<br/>
          who writes a book. The audience is replaced by the the<br/>
          reader. <sup>Anon, <s>when</s> is dead.</sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>