<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M112, set 1 of 3 [The Reader: manner brings in suggestions that give it another meaning]. Typescript fragment with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 4 fols.
        </title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m112-1</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M112, set 1 of 3 [The Reader: manner brings in suggestions that give it another meaning]. Typescript fragment with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 4 fols.</p> 
            <p>p. 33 with fragment paginated p. 30 on verso.</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-1/949,118,139,171/full/0/default.tif">
          30
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-1/899,244,1794,1572/full/0/default.tif">
          But again down on the  the curtain rises.
          The trumpets sound; the flag blows and the
          shadowy insubstantial life txmxmxx of Squires, nobles
          Maids of 
            hnour (honour) and country 
            gentlmen (gentlemen) is before us.
          In one second we are in the thick of love; murder; adultery.
           is before us. There is  and his ;
          there is  the 
            adulterere (adulterer); and  the villain.
          Supper is laid; the cards are on the table, and next moment
          the husband throwing open the door sees his wife lying in
          the arms of her lover. The yellow pages in Record offices
          and Muniments rooms 
            wit (with) their 
            contorsions (contortions), their evasions,
          give place to outright speech. In the play 
            tself (itself) all is
          evident, 
            outapoken (outspoken). In 
            r al (real) life all is shadowy and
          suppressed.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-1/934,1800,1794,1572/full/0/default.tif">
          But by 
            degrrees (degrees) the dramatist sheds his anonymity.
          He separates himself from his audience. He pauses, sometimes;
          he 
            di erts (diverts) the interest from the action to the 
            mtove (motive)
          motive behind the action. What, he broods in 
          , is the effect of mercy?--- if the adulters
          are confronted not with death but with a guilty conscience?
          As the plays come faster and faster, as the curtain rises
          again and again, upon , , , 
          , -- anonymity and the pressure of the
          audience cease to bind the playwright. The reader loses his
          anonymity too. He 
            chhoses (chooses); he 
            discrimitaes (discriminates). Here are
          
            kick nacks (knicknacks); curiosities; illustrations of the time. But
          here on the other hand, what we call for short ourselves--
          the thought that we think 
            instcintively (instinctively), the comment that
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-2/861,44,161,158/full/0/default.tif">
          33
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-2/815,180,1826,1996/full/0/default.tif">
          manner brings in suggestions that give it another meaning
          almost. <sup>the word suggests often the manner of the clothes.</sup> We cannot shut out the contrast often between
          the past and the present. And as the habit of reading becomes
          universal many 
            varities (varieties) of reader split off.
          There are the 
            specilaised (specialised) readers whose power of drawing out
          the meaning of words is tremendously developed; so that
          remain attached to certain aspects of the 
            rinted (printed) page;
          the scholars, the 
            sudents (students). 
            Agaian (Again) there is the very
          large 
            vlass (class) of perfectly literate people 
            whoruns (who run)
          who run their eyes over miles of print yet never read a word.
          <sup>The reader at the moment is probably the [illeg.] reader.</sup>
          When the reader proper, with his power to 
            m kae (make)
          
            ouses (houses) and countries visible, men and women and their 
            though (thoughts)
          and emotions from marks on a 
            ice (piece) 
            eof (of) paper bec
          came into existence <s>it is difficult to say.</s> He is always
          
            chnaging (changing). The  is now 
            develpoing (developing) his eye. The
           is developing his ear. The fate 
            if (of) literature of
          <s>course is in his hands</s>. <sup>But</sup> Axxxhe <sup>He is <s>still</s></sup> is still <s>apparently</s> reading
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-2/811,2156,1826,1260/full/0/default.tif">
          One reason why 
             is still read is simply
          the inadequacy of 
            Shakespriean (Shakespearean) cri  cism (criticism). <s>The</s> inadequacy of
          that criticism is means that is due of course to the
          it is always autobiographical criticism.
          xxxxxxxxxxxxx It is a
            comm nplace (commonplace) 
            tp (to) say that every
          critic finds his own features in 
            Shakepare (Shakespeare). His variety
          is such that every one wxxxx can find scattered here or
          there the <sup>[that which?] he can</sup> 
            develop ent (development) of some one of his own 
            attrbutes (attributes).
          The critic then accents what is he is responsive to, and so
          composes his own meaning, in 
            Shakesperes (Shakespeare's) words.
          The  S. the  S. the  S.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""> 
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-3/895,77,143,139/full/0/default.tif">
          34
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-3/871,224,1810,868/full/0/default.tif">
          that of the , the Cxmxmxxxx , the 
          the  and above all the
            Cliffo ds (Cliffords) has become
          like a precious stone not to be 
            mized (mixed) with baser metal.
          When Lord  marries 
          
            ifit (it) was "held a very mean match
          an 
            indiscreet on (indiscretion) on part of him"
          She 
            believss (believes) in the immortality of the body as firmly as
          in the immortality of the soul.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-3/887,1064,1810,1132/full/0/default.tif">
          Yet there were moments when even this carapace of
          possessions proved too heavy for her; <s>when on the first day</s>
          xmxmxmxmmxmxx If I had not excellent  book
          
            here to comfort me, I were in a pitiable case, having so
            many troubles as I have here, but when I read in that,
            I 
              nscorn (scorn) and make light of them all, and a little part of
            his beauteous spirit infuses itself in me."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-3/847,2196,1810,1132/full/0/default.tif">
          She adds that 
            postcriot (postscript) wxmxmxmxmxmx to a letter about a
          little cabinet and cup which she had left with Lady 
          when she borrowed a hundred pounds of her.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          But it is only when she reads that she comments.
          When she goes to the play she says only "Supped with
          my Lord and Lady  and after supper
          
            OI (I) saw the play of the Mad Lover..." or
          "We stood to see the Masque in the box with my Lady
          " It was when the playhouses were shut
          presumably that the reader was born. xmxmxmxmxmxmxm
          The 
            cur  us (curious) faculty of making houses and countries
          
            visble (visible), and men and women and their emotions,
          from marks on a printed page was 
            undevleoped (undeveloped) as
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-5/872,97,135,141/full/0/default.tif">
          35
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-5/799,212,1811,1868/full/0/default.tif">
          so long as the play was 
            domenant (dominant). The audience at the
          
            plahouse (playhouse) had to draw in the play with their eyes and ears.
          Without a book of the words they could not deepen and revive
          the impression left by the play, or ask those questions that
          are debated daily now in every newspaper. The lack of 
            generl (general)
          
            r ading (reading) 
            acconts (accounts) for the long pause between 
            Sahkespsreas (Shakespeare's)
          death and the 
            i8th (18th) 
            centiry (century) when the plays of 
            Shakespre (Shakespeare)
          hung suspended 
            unreaslied (unrealised). Even in 17 -  could
          say that 
            Shakespere (Shakespeare) still lacked half his proper fame.
          It 
            accojts (accounts) too for the scarcity of criticism, and for the
          general nature of what 
            critisim (criticism) there was. Both  and
           are writing for the 
            s ll ([small? still?]) critical public,
          and thus deal general questions 
            andnot (and not) with
          
            partciularities (particularities) and 
            personalitties (personalities). Mxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxe
          mxmxmmxmxmxmxmmmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmmxmx
          primxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxy
          xmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmx
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-5/843,2056,1803,596/full/0/default.tif">
          A life history of the reader during the past
          four hundred years would <sup>be needed</sup> 
            disocver (discover) at what point he lost
          the 
            acuten ss (acuteness) of his eyes; of his ears. at what point he
          
            devloped (developed) 
            he (the) power of 
            asscoation (association); so that now a word printed
          in the old spelling suggests a 
            thosand (thousand) a
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-5/811,2688,1803,596/full/0/default.tif">
          The biographer of the reader during the past four
          hundred years 
            w uld (would) discover at what point his ear lost
          its acuteness; when his 
            ey d (eyes) became dull; when to balance
            this loss, he became 
              cosncious (conscious) of suggestions and echoes,
          and as time passed added much that was
          unintended by the wxmxmxx writer. It would show that
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-7/853,53,165,163/full/0/default.tif">
          36
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-1/m112-1-7/811,164,1866,2660/full/0/default.tif">
          we lost much 
            whe (when) the p spectator was 
            transfomed (transformed) into the 
            read (reader)
          the sound of the 
            spoeken (spoken) word; a thousand suggestions that
          the 
            dramtist (dramatist) conveys 
            b (by) gestures, by grouping and the
          inflection of the voice. as if <sup>alone that</sup> proved by the
          the effort we make in reading the 
            earky (early) plays
          to supply the trumpets and the flags, the citizens and
          the 
            apprenetices (apprentices). And in attempting this 
            fthe (the) reader is
          perpetually baffled; He is apt to become not a reader,
          but a 
            st dent (student); and as his reading power develops,
          and as the habit of reading becomes universal, 
          there split off the 
            specilaised (specialised) readers with their
          tremendously developed power of 
            ddrawing (drawing) 
            o   (out) the meaning
          of words; and again the very large class of perfectly
          literate people who though they strip many miles of 
            pint (print)
          yearly from paper 
            mever (never) read a word; and finally the reader,
          who like Lady , read excellent  book
          when they are in trouble, "and a little part of his 
            beautoeus (beauteous)
          spirit infuses itself in me." And the reader is always
          changing, The 
            cimea (cinema) is now 
            develpping (developing) his eyes; the 
            Braod (Broadcast)
          cast is 
            develpoing (developing) his ear. He is still causing books to be
          printed His imprtance can be 
            gausged (gauged) by the act that
          when his attention is distracted, in times of public crisis,
          the writer exclaims: I cannot write any more. I have no
          audience. 
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>