<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M108 [The Reader: There is a jolt at the points.]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 7p.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m108</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M108 [The Reader: There is a jolt at the points.]. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 7p. Paginated 23-28, with an unpaginated page at end.</p>
            <p>These and successive folders of [The Reader] were contained in two multigrip folders, headed by Virginia Woolf: "Turning the page"; "Transformations" and "Spare sheets of T.P." labels on the spines. They are filed under her Anon, holograph and typescript fragments.</p>
            <p>The fragments grouped in the successive folders under [The reader] may or may not have formed part of Anon. They have been grouped in this fashion based on the evidence of paper and typewriters. The pagination 23-28 is the lowest in the sequence. Internal evidence would indicate that manuscript drafts preceded that of Anon, since Articles, 1938-9 notebook contains a fragment. Some of the versos of this run of material contains fragments of typescripts of Between the Acts and other contemporary works.</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-1/772,92,234,202/full/0/default.tif">
          23
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-1/723,280,1938,804/full/0/default.tif">
          There is a jolt at the points. Lovely as the words are,
          the mind slides on to a another rail. To speak them the poet
          has separated t himself from the 
            actirs (actors). He cannot yet make
           speak those words with his own lips. The play
          is still in part the work of the 
            undiffrenetiated (undifferentiated) audience,
          demanding great names, great deeds, simple outlines,
          and not the single subtlety of one soul.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-1/731,1076,1978,1284/full/0/default.tif">
          The audience is silent. xmxmxmxmxmmxxxmmxmxmxxmmx
          xmmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmx 
          and , as wrote to 
           "pass away their time in London, merely in going to
          plays every day" But the attraction, strong as it was,
          that drew them to the , roused no comment. A 
           
            dedictes (dedicates)his sonnets to  and not one of those
          highly educated nobles troubles to ask Who is this patron?
          It is not a matter of 
            i nterest (interest) 
            i (in) court circles.
          If we try to look at the audience off the stage
          in their private lives we see only wisps, passing phantoms.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-3/672,42,158,150/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            24
          </sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-3/820,134,158,150/full/0/default.tif">
          28
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-3/760,256,1908,3100/full/0/default.tif">
          If we try to look at them, off the stage, in their real
          persons <sup>private lives</sup>, we see only wisps; passing phantoms. There are the
          Fytton sisters, daughters of , knight of  in . , the younger,
          became one of  Maids of Honour. She goes
          from her country hometo the great world. ,
          xmxmxmmxmx a person of great consequence there, promised her
          father that he will not fail to fulfil your desire in 
            playig (playing)
          
            the Good shepherd and will to my power defend the innocent
            lamb 
              fro (from) the wolvish 
              crulety (cruelty) and foxlike subtlety
          
          of the tame 
            beats (beasts) of this 
            vplace (place)..." His words 
            weve (weave) a veil
          through which nothing is seen in its actual shape. <sup>some horror is concealed [behind?] the flowers</sup>. There is
          silence. Then 
            Sile ce (Silence) falls. Then in involved 
            mata hors (metaphors),
          making use of the old images, speaking 
            circumlocuitouly (circumlocutiously) of
          spring and summer and winter frost and flowers in a fair
          garden he reveals obliquely his illicit passion for the
          girl. 
            Sile ce (Silence) again 
            decends (descends). Then "one Mrs Martin who
          dwelt at the 
          gossips that the Maid of Honour has dressed up <sup>as a man</sup>
          in a <sup>large</sup> great white cloak and gone to meet her lover Lord
           privately. Silence again descends. Then
          Mary has borne him a bastard, whom he refuses to acknowledge.
          And her father conveys her home. 
            Sielnce (Silence) again 
            decsneds (descends).
          It is broken later when some further intrigue makes her
          mother cry: If it had pleased God when I did bear her
          
            that she and I had been buried it had saved me from a great
            deal of sorrow and grief and her from...such shame as never
            had Cheshire woman..... Write no more to me of her."
          
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-5/894,44,194,206/full/0/default.tif">
          25
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-5/880,172,1764,1508/full/0/default.tif">
          But her passion, her disgrace, her 
            humiltaion (humiliation) are all acted
          i in dumb show. They are 
            hidd n (hidden) either by silence, or by
          flourishes and ornaments that 
            amont (amount) to silence.
          Even a plain country squire once he takes pen in hand
          has 
            recource (recourse) to poetry. , after trying to ex-
          plain "My conceit of this tripple love, of 
            affcetion (affection) passion
          and conjunction" has recourse to poetry. He quotes 
          to help him out. It is the poets still who speak for the
          squires. They have no serviceable language Yet behind
          these florid decorations the wolves of the court prye
          prey and raven. 
            astards (Bastards) are born. 
            eputations (reputations) are 
            ru ned (ruined).
          Only the auxmxmxmxmxmx people 
            themslves (themselves) pass unseen.
          They too like the dramatists remain anonymous.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-5/2208,1478,537,607/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            there is an 
            [illeg. tiny words...]
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
          </sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-5/860,1652,1836,1588/full/0/default.tif">
          And the play itself was still anonymous.
          The lack of  name, or , shows how largely
          the play was a common product, written by 
            o e (one) hand, but so
          moulded in transition that the author had no 
            snese (sense) 
            od (of)
          property in it. It was in part the work of the audience.
          And the audience was a large one. Fifteen hundred
          people,  computes was an average audience,
          Of these the 
            gr ater (greater) part were apprentices, citizens
          
            oredom (boredom) of the afternoon. Their presence is obvious enough
          in the early plays. It is they who 
            drw (draw) up the extravagance
          the hyperbole, as a sheet of paper draws 
            yp (up) the fire.
          It was they who made the playwright capable of his great
          strides, of vast audacities beyond the reach of the solitary
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-7/870,88,189,155/full/0/default.tif">
          26
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-7/807,204,1899,3108/full/0/default.tif">
          solitary writer with his mind fixed upon the reader in the
          great room. If we could measure the 
            e ec (effect) of the audience
          upon the play we should have a hold which is denied us
          upon the play itself. But the audience, drawn though it is
          by an 
            irrestible (irresistible) attraction to the play, is silent.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          That 
            sielnce (silence) is one of the deep gulfs that lies between us
          and the play. They come 
            crodwing (crowding) across the river daily;
          but they nxmxmxx sit there silent. They neither 
            priasise (praise)
          nor blame. We can compare this 
            siel ce (silence) with our own d
          silence at the  or at the  in their
          early days. A new art comes upon us so surprisingly
          that we sit silent, 
            recongsing (recognising) before we take the measure.
          <s>And</s> <sup>But</sup>, while we have a measuring rod, <sup>beauty, on our part</sup> thexmxmxmxmxmxm
          a press that at once applies a standard, the Elizabethans
          had no literature behind them to with which to compare the
          play, and no press to give it speech. To the 
            Elizabeathsn (Elizabethans)
          the expressive power of words after their 
            lo g (long) inadequacy
          must have been overwhelming. Silence must have kept them
          silent. There at the  or at the  men and women whose
          only reading had been the Bible or some old 
            chornicle (chronicle)
          came out into the light of the present moment. They saw
          
            themsleves (themselves) 
            sple didly (splendidly) dressed. They heard them selves saying
          out loud what they had never said yet. They heard their
          aspirations, their profanities, their ribaldries
          spoken for them in poetry. And there was <s>always</s> something
          illicit in their pleasure. The preacher and the magistrate
          were always denouncing their emotion. That too must
          have given it intensity.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-8/856,80,164,172/full/0/default.tif">
          27
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-8/808,212,1804,2196/full/0/default.tif">
          The play then owes its <sup>heightened</sup> intensity to the audience in the
          penny seats. At their 
            commandit (command it) is violent; it is 
            corase (coarse);
          it is, like our own detective stories and best sellers
          a parody and a transformation of actual fact. There was a
          <sup>It must have</sup> great temptation for the playwright to exaggerate. It
          <s>was</s> <sup>fed</sup> the desire of the audience in the penny seats. But in the
          seats in the covered part of 
            th (the) house there were nobles,
          rulers scholars. Lord Southampton and Lord Rutland,
          Roland White wrote to Sir Robert Sidney "pass away their
          time in London, merely in going to plays every day".
          Yet they are silent too. A 
            yo ng (young) poet dedicates his sonnets
          to Mr W. H. and none of them troubles to ask,
          
            Whois (Who is) this patron? It is not a matter of interest in court
          circles. And 
            is (this) lack of curiosity is harder to explain.
          
            Fo (For) they were readers; they had the Greeks and the Latins
          at the 
            ack (back) of their minds. How could it have been that they
          said nothing about 
            theis (this) astonishing new art, that they
          did not <sup>[expect?]</sup> 
            expereince (experience) that sense of outrage, of 
            partisanchip (partisanship)
          which seems to be the common reaction of the more cultivated
          part of the public when a new writer of genius appears?
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-8/852,2392,1796,812/full/0/default.tif">
          Perhaps  in his  
            supplys (supplies) a reason.
          These things be 
            b y (but) Toyes" he wrote in the essay
          called . To the 
            aristocratuc (aristocratic)
          scholar the players were still only mountebanks, bear leaders
          and 
            acroats (acrobats). They spoke in the vulgar tongue. Off the stage
          they lived in the . 
             lying on the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-10/902,34,146,134/full/0/default.tif">
          28
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-10/880,176,1756,1276/full/0/default.tif">
          bed at  reached out and stabbed  in the head
          whereupon Ingram gave 
            Mar loew (Marlowe) a mortal wound over the
          right eye.  ran  through the body
          with a sword that cost three and sixpence. If such had been
          the behaviour of  and , <sup> </sup>, thxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmx
          xmxmxmxm <sup> there would have been a gulf between them and</sup>
          the Court. So 
            com;lete (complete) was Bacons contempt for this under
          world that he could be tolerant. "The Stage is more 
            behilding (beholding)
          to Love than the life of Man.... great spirits and great
          businesse do keep out of this weak passion." The proper
          place for the weak passion was the stage, for love "leads to
          speaking in <sup>a</sup> 
            perpetaul (perpetual) hyperbole."
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-10/238,262,670,422/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            , one of the actors,
            <s>danced to</s>
            went dancing to .
          </sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-10/872,1488,1788,1924/full/0/default.tif">
          The proper topics of 
            discccuion (discussion) in the 
            pper (upper)
          world was not the Play at 
            t e (the) Bankside but the life of man.
          The <sup>titles</sup> xxxxxxx of the Essays 
            enumaerate (enumerate) <sup>the [illeg.]</sup> of those topics.
          "Of Truth. Of Death. Of Unity in religion. Of Revenge.
          Of Simulation and 
            Dissumlation (Dissimulation)." These were the subjects
          that the rulers discussed at their high tables;
          and the play was a diversion with which to relax the mind
          after serious work. The sediment of that conversation is
          to be found in the rich deposits of the essays. He is concern
          with the great world of action; with government; with the
          tortuous matures of Princes; with the arts by which Princes
          can 
            way (sway), can coax, can suppress. He lives entirely
          in the world of great spirits and great business. The common
          
            peopl (people) is contemptible. The master of superstition is
          
            t e (the) people." Praise, "if it be from the common people,
          
            it is commonly false and naught. The lowest virtues draw
            praise from them; the middle virtues work in them astonish
          
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-12/776,36,1868,300/full/0/default.tif">
          
            ment; and admiration; but of the highest vertues they have
            no sense or 
              percebing (perceiving) at all."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-12/704,336,1932,1748/full/0/default.tif">
          The soul that walked between delicate groves, now
          and then formulating a 
            pharse (phrase) to be taken down by the 
            y ng (young)
          secretary , kept to a narrow path between
          hedges. While  ranged 
            th (the) world, 
            indulgn (indulging) all
          
            curisoities (curiosities), mixing 
            garrul usly (garrulously) with every one, Bacon kept
          to the narrow path. Yet even in the shade his thought
          is embodied. His deep meditations are given concrete form.
          
            "Nay retire men 
              acnnot (cannot) when they would: neither will they
            when it were reason; but are 
              impateint (impatient) of privateness
            even in age and sickness which require the Shadow: Like old
            Townmen that will be still sitting at their street door,
          
          though thereby they offer Age to scorn." Even in the 
           thought 
            ic (is) coloured. The Colours that show best
          by candlelight , are: White, Carnation, and a kinde of
          Sea-Water Green". It only needs the playwright to put <sup>one push for their thoughts</sup>
          flesh and blood onto his thoughts. <sup>to become [people?]</sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m108/m108-12/736,2056,1924,900/full/0/default.tif">
          Bacons contempt was for hyperbole; not for the art of
          speech. He was teaching the ranting players to speak
          slowly, closely, subtly. He was proving that there is 
            anothe (another)
          kind of poetry, the poetry of prose. He was bringing the
          prose of the mind into being. And thus by increasing the
          range of the poet, bu making it possible for him to express
          more, he was making an end of anonymity.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>