<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M54, 8 of 11. [Anon: With that a joyous fellow issued]. Typescript fragment, 3 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m54-8</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M54, 8 of 11. [Anon: With that a joyous fellow issued]. Typescript fragment, 3 fols.</p>
            <p>N.B.: This is one of eleven sub-fragments identified in the Berg Collection's M54. [Anon: The printing press brought the past into existence...]. Typescript fragments, unsigned and undated, 35 fols. I have determined pagination and sequencing based on subject matter. M54 as curated by the Berg Collection is available as part of 'The Digital Anon' and can be found at [LINK].</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-8/m54-8-1/922,110,291,117/full/0/default.tif">
          <s>16</s>xx 15
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-8/m54-8-1/843,270,1301,370/full/0/default.tif">
          
            With that a joyous fellowship 
              issued (iissued)<br/>
            Of 
              minstrels (misnterls) making goodly merriment<br/>
            With wanton bardes and Rhymers impudent
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-8/m54-8-1/819,612,1889,2652/full/0/default.tif">
          The word remind us that if the great Elizabethan<br/>
          house,  or  looks to us out of proportion,<br/>
          xmxmx a derelict among 
            the (th) bungalows, it is because the<br/>
          connection between it and the village is lost. If we could<br/>
          see the house as it was in  time we should see<br/>
          tracks raying out from the great house across the fields to<br/>
          the cottage, to the farm, even to the hovel. War connected<br/>
          them. Armour, if the enemy came was stored in the church.<br/>
          The young men practised the great English art of<br/>
          the long bow. Also, there was the other fight, the 
            perpetual (pertual)<br/>
          fight with nature. They must together plough and sow if the<br/>
          winter were not to starve them. This connection xxx<br/>
          between master and man is painfully and minutely recorded<br/>
          in the medieval letters. It is 
            the (th) staple of the whole<br/>
          correspondence. But there was also the other less<br/>
          visible connection--the common belief. That bond between<br/>
          the different houses has been grown over, like the<br/>
          track along which the  rode to . No one<br/>
          drives there now. <sup>[illeg.]</sup>. But 
            when (whe)  came to  that<br/>
          track led from house to house. It led to the village green.<br/>
          It led to the tree; to the well. In the spring they danced<br/>
          round the Maypole; at midsummer they lit the bon fire on the<br/>
          hill; at Christmas the mummers acted their dumb show;<br/>
          the boys came wassailing xmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxmxm
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-8/m54-8-3/961,48,137,170/full/0/default.tif">
          16
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-8/m54-8-3/930,184,1738,884/full/0/default.tif">
          at Harvest time the God was worshipped in the<br/>
          sheaf of corn; how thxmXmxmxmmxmx the God was in the<br/>
          
            bay (ay) tree--how in the dances and songs that 
            children (childre) sing<br/>
          the old Gods were worshipped, and served. In these dressings<br/>
          up at thxmxmxx midsummer, at Christmas the 
            English (En lish) 
            remembering (rememberig)<br/>
          the Gods who were there when the stones were set on end<br/>
          at , at , celebrated their gods; and<br/>
          at the same 
            time (tiem) gave shape to to the desire to cease, for<br/>
          that one day, from the 
            perpetual (pertual) fight; to be free; to be som<br/>
          
            something (tjing); to act in their own persons the inner joy; to make<br/>
          something which had no reason, no use. The 
            scholars (schloars) tell us<br/>
          that though 
            the (t e e) actors, presumably because they slipped<br/>
          from the common task, and often made mock of it, were 
            despised (despsed)<br/>
          despised, yet the great had so much of the common desire<br/>
          in them that Kings and Queens must have their 
            minstrels (minstresl), 
            their (ther)<br/>
          dancers and singers. Even the Church, conscious as the<br/>
          
            priests (preists) were that it was not 
            their God (theirGod) but some pagan<br/>
          
            who (wh) was thus 
            honoured (hinoured), could not suppress the minstrels and<br/>
          and the rhymers, the mummers, the jugglers, the bear leaders<br/>
          who came into the village, who acted 
            their (t eir)<br/>
          parts in the churchyard.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          This was the other 
            bond (bo d) between the great house<br/>
          and the cottage. In the noble, as in the 
            peasant (pe asnt), a half<br/>
          conscious, anonymous voice 
            murmured (mur ured) of. The well and the<br/>
          tree were still 
            haunted (hanuted); Some 
            old (o d) woman in her hovel<br/>
          was still to the King even the vessel of an unclean spirit.<br/>
          She 
            mewed (mowed) and mobbed and plucked her chin. When the<br/>
          pilliwinks were 
            applied (appied) to her, she confessed how she had
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-8/m54-8-5/911,97,142,137/full/0/default.tif">
          17
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-8/m54-8-5/885,188,1707,414/full/0/default.tif">
          how she sailed in a 
            sieve (sive) singing to the <br/>
          she confessed to how she had 
            thrown (throw) a cat into the sea and<br/>
          
            raised (rasied) a storm that had sunk the kings ships.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>