<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M112, Set 2 of 3 [The Reader: must in order to sit and stand there, while the sun beats...]. Typescript fragment, unsigned and undated with the author's ms. additions. 2 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m112-2</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M112, Set 2 of 3 [The Reader: must in order to sit and stand there, while the sun beats...]. Typescript fragment, unsigned and undated with the author's ms. additions. 2 fols.</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-2/m112-2-1/905,70,189,155/full/0/default.jpg">
          32
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-2/m112-2-1/863,208,1842,1860/full/0/default.jpg">
          must in order to sit and stand there, while the sun beats
          or the rain pours have some strong inducement; something
          that puzzles; and then concludes. They must have love;
          murder; adultery. And this 
            contrbution (contribution) of the audience
          was more unfortunate to the dramatist 
            tahn (than) to the lyric
          singer. Often the actions is too violent for the words.
          There is a dislocation between the thought and the action.
          No one feels what is said. The emotion is often
          
            las ered (plastered) on to a dumb figure. But if violence rapidity
          movement are dictated by the audience an inevitable 
            confusin (confusion)
          follows. On the other hand the playwright
          like the singer has an anomymous vitality,
          drawn 
            fro (from) other bodies, a 
            pe renniel (perennial) common vigour.
          Nor is  
            dad (dead) in ourselves. The crude early 
            ddrams (dramas)
          have still the power to make us ask--as the audience asked--
          the childs 
            questin (question): what comes next? <sup>a power denied to [20th?] century [illeg.]</sup>
          So we become 
            ourelves (ourselves) anonymous in the early plays.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-2/m112-2-1/911,2048,1770,1332/full/0/default.jpg">
          It is only later when the pressure of silent 
            horaded (hoarded)
          emotion had thrown up words, as the 
            fi gers (fingers) of the man at the
           casts letters from the bubbling lead,
          that we lose this general quality to gain---
          everything it seems. For the 
            curatin (curtain) goes on rising
          incessantly for fifty years. Now it rises on ;
          then on ; on ;
          on ; finally on . 
            Byt (By) that time the sxxgxx
          play has outgrown the stage. The stage has become too small
          to act this drama. Perhaps after 
            cnuries (centuries), the play will
          come to birth again, differently, in ,
          in . But the play never again fitted the stage
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-2/m112-2-3/879,24,187,212/full/0/default.jpg">
          33
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-2/m112-2-3/895,208,1699,220/full/0/default.jpg">
          completely in England. The book after 
             takes the
          place of the play. And Anon is dead for ever.
        </p> 
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>