<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M54, 7 of 11. [Anon: distinct from the minstrel, whose words are printed.]. Typescript fragment, 2 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m54-7</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M54, 7 of 11. [Anon: distinct from the minstrel, whose words are printed.]. Typescript fragment, 2 fols.</p>
            <p>N.B.: This is one of eleven sub-fragments identified the Berg Collection's M54. [Anon: The printing press brought the past into existence...]. Typescript fragments, unsigned and undated, 35 fols. I have determined pagination and sequencing based on subject matter. M54 as curated by the Berg Collection is available as part of 'The Digital Anon' and can be found at [LINK].</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-7/m54-7-1/886,106,191,139/full/0/default.tif">
          14
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-7/m54-7-1/859,220,1825,3094/full/0/default.tif">
          distinct from the 
            minstrel (mistrel), whose words are printed.<br/>
          For when familiar 
            letters (lettres) are written in Biblical prose<br/>
          there must be a barrier between what is sayable and what<br/>
          unsayable. There is a limit to what can be put<br/>
          into words. He cannot talk; he cannot sing. <sup>[illeg.]</sup> At the beginning<br/>
          of the sixteenth 
            century (cnstury) he exists; the printing press has<br/>
          given him a name; but he is still unspecialised.<br/>
          The man <sup>[with?]</sup> who stands outside desiring by some impulse to 
            observe (obsev)<br/>
          , to state, rather than to take part, is not yet wholly<br/>
          writer, wholly musician or 
            wholly (whllly) painter. It seems possible<br/>
          that the great English art 
            may (ma) not be the art of words.<br/> 
          He still has the exact 
            observant (observan) eye <sup>that sees exactly </sup>; his ear is stimulated<br/>
          by the sound of words spoken aloud. His words must have body<br/>
          and 
            substance (substnace), <sup>H</sup>e must make them <sup>words</sup> 
            sonorous (sornous), since they are to<br/>
          be read out aloud. I spent most of my time" wrote Lady<br/>
           "in 
            playing (playin) at Glecko and hearing <br/>
          read the ....Rivers used to read to me in<br/>
           Faery Queen<br/>
          
            Further (Futher), words must <s>
              yield (yeild) themselves</s> <sup>move</sup> easily to the lilt<br/>
          of the singing voice, to the virginals<sup>,</sup> to the lute. The<br/>
          
            English (Eoglish) were a musical race. <sup>For the English were [always?] singing &amp; playing</sup> When 
            London was (Londonwas) burning<br/>
           noted that "hardly one lighter or boat in three<br/>
          that had the goods of a house in it, but there was a pair<br/>
          of virginals in it." <s>These were</s> the influences that<br/>
          told upon the poet; <sup>[illeg.] moved</sup> Under neath the words<sup>:</sup> the old words<br/>
          the new words <sup>the <s>[illeg.]</s></sup>, the 
            French and (Frechand) the Latin moved the music.<br/>
          No grammar bound them tightly to gether. They could be read<br/>
          aloud; danced to and sung to. But they could not follow the
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-7/m54-7-1/528,1290,423,279/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            His senses are<br/>
            attuned then:<br/>
            he sees within<br/>
            shadow
          </sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-7/m54-7-3/797,115,149,111/full/0/default.tif">
          15
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-7/m54-7-3/804,224,1730,218/full/0/default.tif">
          the pace of the speaking voice. They could not enter into<br/>
          the private world.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-7/m54-7-3/716,448,1890,2478/full/0/default.tif">
           then --"a little man with short hair,<br/>
          a small 
            band (vband) and cuffs" standing on the threshold of the<br/>
          "gay and sumptuous house" at , was separate<br/>
          from Anon the 
            minstrel (misntre); and from 
             the Chronicler;<br/>
          He was separate too from his 
            audience (adueince). But the book which<br/>
          had given him his 
            separate (sepatare) existence had brought into being<br/>
          a little group of readers. That audience began at once to<br/>
          exert its pressure. What is the book that will 
            please (plase)<br/>
          my patron  What is the theme that will<br/>
          recommend itself to the ? At once come into 
            existence (ecistence) all<br/>
          those 
            innumerable (iunnmerable) influences that are to tug and distort and<br/>
          thwart; as too they are to stimulate and draw out. The<br/>
          poet is no longer <s>a homeless being</s> <sup>a nameless, a wandering voice</sup>. He is surrounded <sup>[illeg.] with his audience</sup><br/>
          with an <s>
            atmosphere (atmopshere). He subjects his inspiration</s> <sup>He is played upon by others</sup> to outside<br/>
          influences. Some are visible to himself only; others<br/>
          only show themselves when time has past. They become more and more complex. <sup>A</sup> the book goes out into a more and more<br/>
          numerous, a more and more divided audience.<br/>
          <s>Some</s> According to its education to its wealth to its 
            poverty (pverty)<br/>
          the audience begins to demand what it satisfies its own needs<br/>
          Some need poetry; <s>others</s> history; <s>others</s> a story to make<br/>
          them forget the drabness of their lives. The thing that<br/>
          the writer has to say becomes increasingly cumbered.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>