<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M112, Set 3 of 3 [The Reader: so long as the play was dominant.]. Typescript fragment, unsigned and undated. 3 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m112-3</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M112, Set 3 of 3 [The Reader: so long as the play was dominant.]. Typescript fragment, unsigned and undated. 3 fols.</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-1/907,113,105,107/full/0/default.tif">
          35
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-1/819,228,1810,1652/full/0/default.tif">
          so long as the play was dominant. The audience at the play<br/>
          house had to draw in txxxx the play with their eyes and<br/>
          ears. Without a book of the words they could not deepen and<br/>
          revise the impression left by the play, or ask those<br/>
          questions that are debated now in every newspaper. The lack<br/>
          of general reading accounts for the long pause between<br/>
           death and the 
            18th (k8th) century when the plays of<br/>
          
            Shakespeare (Shakespere) hung suspended, unrealised-- even in 17<br/>
           could say that 
            Shakespeare (Shakespera) still lacked<br/>
          half his 
            proper (proer) fame. The lack of a reading public<br/>
          accounts too for the scarcity of criticism and for the<br/>
          general nature of what criticism there is. Both  and<br/>
           are writing for the small critical public, and thus<br/>
          deal with 
            general (ggneral) questions, and not with 
            particular (partciualr) books<br/>
          and 
            persons (perons).
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-1/823,1896,1810,1340/full/0/default.tif">
          The reader then 
            comes (com s) into existence some time<br/>
          at 
            the (teh) end of the sixteenth century, and his life history<br/>
          could we discover it would be worth writing, for the effect<br/>
          it had upon literature. At some point his ear must have<br/>
          lost its acuteness; at 
            another (a other) his eye must have become dull.<br/>
          Our own attempt when we read the early Elizabethan 
            plays (palys)<br/>
          
            to (the) supply the trumpets and the flags, the citizens and the<br/>
          apprentices is an effort to revert to an earlier stage.<br/>
          As time goes on 
            the (th) reader becomes distinct 
            from (f om) the<br/>
          spectator. His 
            sense (snese) of words and their 
            associations (associat ns)<br/>
          
            develops (dvelops). Hxxx A word spelt on the old spelling brings<br/>
          in 
            associations (asscoations). Readers split off into different 
            classes (clases).
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-3/865,52,233,162/full/0/default.tif">
          36
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-3/899,196,1715,1788/full/0/default.tif">
          As the habit of reading becomes universal, readers split off<br/>
          into different classes. There is the 
            specialised (specilaised) reader, who<br/>
          attaches himself to certain aspects of the 
            printed (rpinted) word.<br/>
          Again there is the very large class of perfectly literate<br/>
          people who strip many miles of print yearly from paper<br/>
          yet never read a word. Finally 
            there (ere) is the reader like<br/>
          <sup>who, like</sup> Lady  read excellent  book when they<br/>
          are in trouble "and a little part of his beauteous spirit<br/>
          infuses itself in me." Hexmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxmmx And the<br/>
          curious faculty --the 
            power (pow r) to make places and houses,<br/>
          men and women and 
            their (theit) thoughts and emotions 
            visible (vivible) on<br/>
          the printed page is a xxxx always changing. The <br/>
          now 
            developing (develping) his eyes; the  is 
            developing (develpoing) his<br/>
          ear. His importance can be gauged by the fact<br/>
          that when his attention is distracted, in times of public<br/>
          crisis, the writer exclaims: I can write no more.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-3/899,1996,1683,1260/full/0/default.tif">
          But the presence of the reader was felt even<br/>
          while the play was still on 
            the (th) stage. It was for him that<br/>
           composed that 
            extraordinary (extraodinary) composition the <br/>
          . It is there that the reader makes his<br/>
          first appearance, for it is there that we find the writer<br/>
          completely conscious of 
            his (is) relation with the reader.<br/>
          xxx and He reveals himself. I am a 
            batchelor (bachelor)I am neither<br/>
          rich nor poor. I am a tumbler over of other mens books.<br/>
          I live in college rooms. I am a spectator not an actor.<br/>
          There is 
            no (n) playhouse audience forcing him to embody his
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-5/867,82,193,154/full/0/default.tif">
          37
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-5/831,204,1849,1220/full/0/default.tif">
          
            meditations (meditayions). The vast accumulations, of 
            learning (lear ing), that<br/>
          have filtered from books into the quiet college room<br/>
          meander over the page. He sees through a thousand green 
            shades (shads)<br/>
          what lies 
            immediately (immidately) before him-- the unhappy heart of<br/>
          man. The reflections serve to chequer the immediate<br/>
          spectacle. From books he has won the tolerant sense<br/>
          that we are not 
            single (singl) figures but innumerably 
            repeated (rep ated).<br/>
          In pursuit of melancholy he travels over the whole world,<br/>
          though he has never left his college room. We are at a remove<br/>
          from the thing treated. We are enjoying the spectacle of<br/>
          melancholy, not sharing is anguish.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m112-3/m112-3-5/819,1424,1849,1324/full/0/default.tif">
          It is here then that we develop 
            faculties (facuoties) that<br/>
          the play left dormant. to stop; to pause; to 
            reflect (refelct);<br/>
          to Now the reader is completely in being. He can<br/>
          pause; he can ponder; he can compare; he can draw back from<br/>
          the page and see behind it a man sitting alone in the centre<br/>
          of the labyrinth of words in a college room 
            thinking (thinkinh)<br/>
          of suicide. He can gratify many different moods.<br/>
          He can read directly what is on the page, or, drawing<br/>
          aside, can read what is not written. There is a long drawn<br/>
          continuity in the book that the 
            play (paly) has not. It gives a<br/>
          different pace to the mind. We are in a world where<br/>
          nothing is concluded.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>