<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M47 [Anon: For why a gods name...]. Holograph fragments, undated. Some pages paginated 1-3. 11p.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m47</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
          <p>M47 [Anon: For why a gods name...]. Holograph fragments, undated. Some pages paginated 1-3. 11p.</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-1/630,68,172,128/full/0/default.tif">
          1
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-1/448,206,736,148/full/0/default.tif">
          For why a gods name
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-1/404,306,1936,1516/full/0/default.tif">
          – thus he proves that he was word conscious, an artist,
          aware of the <s>possibilities, of the limitations</s> of his medium.
          <s>Its</s> <s>He</s> <s>The</s> <sup>aware that</sup> words, not paint, not music; words themselves.
          He To be thus aware of language, the writer must
          have a past behind him, just as the historian <sup>must</sup>, in
          order to see the present moment, must <sup>set it against</sup> the past <sup>in counter [illeg.]</sup>
          behind him. <s>There must be a golden age; the</s>
          <s>must be corrupt, degenerate, fallen.</s> <s>But</s>
          The golden age of English was to  the age of
           – "Dan Chaucer, well of English undefiled"
          <s>The language</s> <s>He</s> <s>There is</s> <s>The</s> <s>he</s>
          <s>Chaucer</s> again – he prays: that the infusion
          sweete
          of thine owne spirit which doth in me survive
          <s>He</s> <s>But there</s> <s>It is the language he loves</s>
          <s>Unlike</s> <s>In his</s> <s>At his moment</s>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-1/532,1752,1944,1664/full/0/default.tif">
          <s>
            It <s>was</s> He looked back to Chaucer –
            differing from the What Spenser saw <s>this was</s>
            then across the dumb age of church buildings, of
            was <s>the</s> <s>long</s> Chaucer <s>It was</s>
          </s>
          The <s>language of Chaucer was what he</s> his
          It was <s>by Chaucer</s> <sup>by</sup> <s>through</s> Chaucer <s>that</s> saw himself
          <s>his work</s> <sup>[illeg.]</sup> the measure of his own speech.
          Where the modern writer <s>wrote a long time</s> of
          has <s>close at hand</s> attacks the generation which
          has just gone, using them as <s>the</s> his <sup>taking off in the opposite direction</sup>
          lane of departure, <s>C</s> Spenser's <s>had no</s>
          revolt was against no particular writer, but
          against the language itself, its decay, since
          Chaucer, its corruption. <s>Perhaps</s> This once
          <s>Partly perhaps,</s> <s>Whe</s> <s>Perhaps as an antidote</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-3/445,140,1975,1092/full/0/default.tif">
          When the , the wife of  <s>who</s> the poet
          who was executed <s>comes to the surface</s> <sup>writes</sup>, she writes:
          Only in some extremity of passion or of need do they <s>come to</s>
          take up the pen. <s>She</s> The sound of the Bible is in
          their ears. <s>As if</s> It is a garment only to be put on when the
          being is in <s>an attitude</s> a certain attitude.
          And the garment may of course conceal a 
          who is merry, who is, normally, <s>occupied with</s>
          <s>happy</s> amused, or charming, or – we cannot tell
          what real woman lives in the other side of that
          wall of words.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-3/557,1182,1935,1040/full/0/default.tif">
          Using the prose of the Bible then, the
          Elizabethans are shut off from us. They can say
          nothing subtle, nothing little. Bright contrasted
          colours meet on their faces: carnation &amp; snow, ebony &amp;
          gold. <s>Stitched into their doublets,</s> <s>the young men look</s>
          Young men's bodies <s>look</s> are stiffly sewn into padded
          doublets, school boys faces are raised above
          starched collars &amp; young women serve only to
          display heavy [guiled?] robes [strewn?] about with
          huge pearls.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-3/1199,2174,459,128/full/0/default.tif">
          ....
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-3/643,2364,539,120/full/0/default.tif">
          <s>But the writ</s>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-3/595,2410,1839,848/full/0/default.tif">
          <s>
            The separation of the writer from the audience–
            <s>was</s> the creation of a <sup>an art of</sup> writing, <s>profession art</s>
            seems to have been slow
            <s>When the</s> <s>the</s> <s>writer</s>
            <s>The writer</s> <s>The speaking voice</s> <s>When the</s>
            the <s>speaking voice is concealed with the writing voice</s>
            If familiar letters are written in biblical English,
            <s>the writer cannot be</s> then the writer
          </s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-5/388,83,104,70/full/0/default.tif">
          3
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-5/371,68,2237,3152/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>from the air</sup> foundations of old houses are still marked, we should see the house
          <s>in</s> connected with the village. We should see <s>here</s> a
          <s>ring in the</s> a ring, an oasis, in the midst of
          fields &amp; forests: the road a mere track: &amp; the
          oasis thus like a fortress built against the
          uncivilised <s>country</s>; if out, against the <s>sige</s> siege – the
          everlasting sieve. <s>of</s> If the enemy comes there <s>are</s> is
          armour in the church. If [flood?] &amp; hunger. then there is
          grain in the great barn. <s>And for the spirit <s>there</s> it is</s>
          <s><s>too</s> and to feed the mind</s> <s>But for the hunger of the</s>
          <s>mind, the curiosity, the desire to escape from</s>
          <s>there <s>were books [illeg.]</s></s> That connection <s>is</s>
          between house &amp; church, master &amp; labourer,
          is <s>obvious</s> detailed in the  letters, making
          indeed the staple of that correspondence. <s>But</s>
          <s>the less visible connections is to</s> there is <sup>was</sup> also the
          other connection, which, <s>just as the <s>of</s></s>
          the <s>bodily connection was</s> <s>looked</s> ended by
          <s>the</s> has become <s>almost invisible now;</s> the
          that bond between the great house &amp; the small
          has faded till it is like one of those perhaps
          rather greener lanes <s>her</s> still to be found in England
          along which antiquarians say the  went to
          . <s>When</s> <sup>Yet</sup> the scholars tell us that
          so the scholars tell us <s>that</s> how
          <s>long before Chaucer,</s> how long before the <s>to</s>
          Christians came, the <s>sun was</s> fire <s>was a god</s> <sup>was worshipped</sup>
          or the sea was a god, &amp; how their
          ancient worship <s>was</s> <sup>went</sup> was beneath the
          other; &amp; <s>how the harvest was</s> &amp; they
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-7/300,72,2152,3360/full/0/default.tif">
          The man then who stood on the threshold of the great
          Elizabethan room was <s>separate from the chronicler</s>
          separate from , the <s>singer</s>, &amp; separate from
          the chronicler. <s>He was</s> separate from his
          audience. <s>He had emerged;</s> <s>But</s> <s>Directly</s>
          the creative instinct, <s>the desire to</s> had singled out
          chosen words for its medium. <s>And</s> The <s>pre</s> press which
          had given <s>him</s> those words a separate existence;
          <s>the reader had been</s> had <s>called into ex</s>
          <s>created a reader: &amp;</s> <s>the reader, the individual</s>
          an <s>un</s> public, a reading public, <s>to</s> And with the
          <s>existence of a public </s> began to exert its
          presentce. But it was a small public, an aristocratic public. <s>And then, when we</s>
          <s>find Spenser, standing at the door, we</s>
          <s>can</s> And so, <s>with Spenser perhaps</s>
          we come for the <s>first time</s> <s>into the</s>
          <s>presence of</s> <sup>to</sup> the book which is <s>influenced</s>
          <s>not anonymous, not spontaneous, not</s>
          is influenced; <s>not</s> in which we can <s>still</s>
          detect <s>other</s> the <s>beginning of</s> <s>all it</s>
          <s>all those tugs, plays</s> additions, influences,
          <s>of</s> <s>apart from the original and pure</s>
          <s>interior.</s> playing on the original instinct &amp;
          giving it that alloy <sup>[illeg.]</sup> <s>when</s> which
          as time goes on, become so innumerable
          <s>that</s> so distracting: the <s>presence</s> <sup>effect</sup> of the
          audience – <s>could we</s> <s>the curiousness</s>
          who will read this; what will be to
          their liking, what will offend them
          What book will find favour with Lady
          Ann? What will please 
          what will flatter the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-9/212,107,110,96/full/0/default.tif">
          2
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-9/331,48,2093,3448/full/0/default.tif">
          the group of nobles, after hunting? what will prove that
          Edmund Spenser, for example, deserves a post, a pension?
          <s>Thes</s> These are the outer influences that stamp
          themselves upon the pure desire. <s>Thus</s> <s>This is the</s>
          <s>atmosphere which draws out, finds, at some times</s>
          <s>is favourable, at others checks &amp; [illeg.]</s>
          <s>But</s> <s>Further, there are</s> Further there are the other
          influences; the <s>del</s> <s>pressure</s> <s>of wealth, rank. &amp; leisure</s>
          education, &amp; class, wealth &amp; poverty always
          at their work, tugging, obscuring distorting.
          Some are visible only to the writer himself;
          others only to the reader. More &amp; more
          complex do they become, as the book with the
          author's name on it goes out to a
          larger public, to a more complex public, to a
          public that has emerged sufficiently from
          the silence of the middle ages to be
          educated, partly educated, to desire
          humour, story, amusement, instruction,
          or [illeg.] something to make them forget <s>what</s>
          the private life which is so drab.
          When Spenser <s>wrote</s> When the book is thus
          covered over, <s>An</s> the song, the thing that the
          writer set out to say, begomes increasingly
          disguised. It is only to be discovered in a
          flash of recognition; some say they feel it
          when their beards bristle; others that a
          thrill runs down the nerves of the thigh.
          To disengage the <s>sur</s> song from the
          influence of the audience becomes a
          task for the critic –– an official who
          scarcely exists when Spenser emerged from
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-11/422,133,76,126/full/0/default.tif">
          3
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-11/479,152,1887,272/full/0/default.tif">
          depths of silence, writing that <s>was</s> <s>long</s> vast poem
          the 
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-11/411,376,1917,2392/full/0/default.tif">
          The artist however had chosen his medium. The
          great English art was not to be <s>l</s> music, or painting:
          it was to be the art of words. And if we call
          <sup>we call</sup> Spenser the first artist, it is because we <s>can</s>
          <s>are aware of his</s> <s>of his</s> <sup>he was</sup> awareness of his medium
          He was conscious not only of his public, not only
          of his own need, a poor man, of patronage &amp;
          support, but of the <s>limitations of the</s> fact that
          the language was truly an [incitement?]
          <s>It</s> "Let us be Kings of our language...
          <s>Let</s> In order <s>to be an artist, must one</s>
          The writer, like the chronicler, in order to see his
          medium cautiously, must be aware of the past
          <s>There</s> There must be a golden age behind him; &amp;
          <s>y</s> the present must be fallen, degenerate.
          But which <s>we</s> the modern writer, who has a
          long tradition behind him, <s>who</s> naturally
          attacks the <s>old</s> generation which has just
          past, thus giving himself a person to
          revolt against, the writer in Spenser's time,
          had no definite past. This is a more general
          reaction. This <s>rather</s> a sense of the
          [delicacy? debauchery?] the decay the language of its
          that he has to correct, rather than
          his actual predecessors.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-11/561,2720,1771,696/full/0/default.tif">
          Thus Spenser, on the threshold of his
          work as a poet, did not demolish his
          predecessors; he complained of the
          debasement of English speech: <s>&amp; the</s>
          He <s>used</s> the old <s>Chaucerian</s> language
          recovered the old words, <s>the</s> 
          words. <s>He</s> Curious perhaps of his own
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-13/578,70,104,142/full/0/default.tif">
          2.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-13/531,204,2111,3176/full/0/default.tif">
          The writer then, came to birth with difficulty in England:
          for so long as familiar letters are written in biblical
          <s>prose, he must remain</s> be <s>only</s> <s>confined</s> there are
          limits <s>to his</s> –– <s>something that remains unfitting</s>
          <s>a</s> to his freedom; a barrier between the sayable &amp;
          the unsayable. He is writing, for the printing press has
          given him a name; but <s>as yet suppressed in the</s>
          <s>submerged; it</s> <s>oppressed, by</s> <s>what</s> the
          <s>
            contorted <s>at many</s> by <s>wh</s> <s>in</s> the inadequacy <s>in</s> <sup>of</sup> his
            instrument; <s>its</s> which, <s>when it</s> <s>if</s> it seems must
            take <s>evade</s> dumb, unable, that is,
            <s>it cannot</s> but <sup>he</sup> still <s>submerged;</s> <s>partly by</s>
          </s>
          unspecialised, undifferentiated. <s>There is a passage in</s>
          <s>The eye was</s> <s>For one</s> <s>He was, seeing;</s> The artist
          is not wholly writer, wholly musician, or wholly
          painter. It seems possible that the great English art
          may not be the art of words. His
          eye <s>was</s> <sup>is</sup> stimulated <s>in that empty world</s>, by the
          colours <sup>of the</sup> of the clothing. His ear <s>was</s>
          <s>stimulated</s> by the sound of <sup>music</sup> words. "Pritchard" said
           read aloud <s>They</s> The Faery Queen..."
          England was given substance &amp; sharpness of the
          speaking voice. And <s>the</s> music gave lilt &amp;
          rhythm, melody to the spoken word.
          "Hardly one lighter or boat in three that had the
          goods of a home in it <s>"</s> but there was a
          pair of virginals in it"  observed, in 1666,
          when the people of London were loading their
          goods onto boats in the great fire. His
          world then was full of undifferentiated words:
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns=""> 
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-15/487,146,143,92/full/0/default.tif">
          3.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-15/487,172,2059,428/full/0/default.tif">
          old words &amp; new words; French &amp; Latin. No grammar
          held them tightly together. They were elastic, they
          could be danced to &amp; sung to. But they could
          not follow the sound of the speaking voice.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-15/443,576,2007,2872/full/0/default.tif">
           then in the  seems like a
          half articulate monster, rising from the depths of
          silence, <s>with</s> hung with the weeds &amp; pearls of <s>that</s>
          the deep sea in which the writer had been
          submerged. <s>The Faery Queen</s>: <s>is</s> we cannot read it: <sup>the 
            Fr Q. (Faerie Queene)</sup>
          we cannot leave it unread. <s>This</s> is a poem without a plot;
          the metre, casting its regular fling, but somehow
          comes to ground too [wholy?]. Unlike  who
          goes ahead, simply, directly, <s>It</s> The Knights, the
          ladies, <s>become</s> <s>loo</s> are <s>see</s> disembodied:
          <s>what</s> &amp; <s>the</s> But <s>we cannot leave</s> it unread:
          it has <s>the vitality of the</s> we see it: the
          <s>compound</s> in groups, like <s>[illeg.]</s> the great
          caravans, painted, brought together into <s>the</s>
          the [illeg.] comes together on the [finial?]
          from the ground. Sometimes the comment is
          perfectly free, expressive <s>of some</s> still of
          some emotion; &amp; then the [warbly]
          becomes sound merely, the [illeg.] merely,
          an incantation; &amp; it passes
          away like a cloud; sleep, indifference,
          [illeg.], along the ear, – still
          we must return to it, because of the
          language – partly for that love of the
          old they seem: it is the thing itself: not 
           or : <s>it is</s> &amp; [pearly?]
          a [illeg.] such a poem as an exile might
          write by way of refuge from the
          damp <s>of</s> &amp; the savagery of the Irish
          country
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-17/418,122,1992,624/full/0/default.tif">
          voluptuous, his love of sound, <s>his</s> <s>addiction</s> the sweetness of the
          his private vocabulary, he tried to harden &amp; <s>ground</s>
          stiffen his poem with the ruder speech which 
          used. For there was nothing, in the years that
          came between the  and the 
          for him to destroy; or to abolish.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-17/508,722,640,108/full/0/default.tif">
          <s>Then again</s>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-17/458,792,1768,1564/full/0/default.tif">
          He stands then, at the threshold of the great hall,
          – "a little man with short hair, a small hand &amp;
          cuffs'– looking back at ; &amp; <s>He</s>
          This public is a reading aloud public of nobles;
          &amp; he has, <s>perhaps</s> <sup>the</sup> disturbing [anticipation?]
          of a language to whuch anything may happen.
          His desire to fasten to to the old English of
          Chaucer arose perhaps from <s>his</s> a
          sense <s>that we cannot</s> sense long lost to us -–
          a sense of the future. <s>Suppose that he</s>
          Why <s>look back to Chaucer, why graft his</s>
          what was going to happen to this new
          [attendantly?] growing speech which he must
          with his sensibility to words he must have
          felt – everywhere – in talk, in songs –
          <s>it</s>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-17/560,2300,1488,788/full/0/default.tif">
          And <s>so we reach the force wh.</s>
          <s>The future</s> <s><s>This is a sense that only comes</s></s>
          The sense of the future is almost extinct, now.
          But then, the writer must have been
          aware, with the agitation of 
          that <s>something</s> it was all to come.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-19/159,92,2262,1024/full/0/default.tif">
          The  were applied to her, how she had sailed
          in a [sieve?] singing, how she had raised a storm in the
          north sea &amp; sunk the kings ships. The great house was not
          silent then. In <s>the</s> <s>tries</s> There were [birds? bodies?] in the trees,
          a deep murmur of old forgotten things humming in the
          mind. And down the roads came the wandering singer,
          lewd, impudent; but to  ear: but <s>he had seen,</s>
          who had seen, at the Green players acting his already
          past before .
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-21/664,64,1872,1256/full/0/default.tif">
          to the shelves of college libraries were the Greek &amp;
          Roman classics. The learned read them; &amp; the nobles.
          <sup>"</sup>...our ancient ladies of the court" when they
          <s>did the</s> were to be found reading the holy
          scriptiores or they did their needlework; &amp;
          histories; ,   made no
          show against these august ancients
          There they sit, in the palace, embroidering, reading,
          playing their musical instrument; &amp;
          the background of the mind is in Italy, in France, in
          Greece; <s>but in the foreground is England,</s>
          <s>the background of the</s> <s>b</s> <s>eye is</s> eye is
          <s>when he looks back, into the physical eye,</s>
          <s>he s</s>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m47/m47-21/700,1248,1896,1920/full/0/default.tif">
          <s>It</s>     – they are in
          the background they are the ancestors <s>to</s> <sup>with</sup> whom the
          learned Elizabethan classes [Kindness?]; but in the
          foreground there is the <s>pla</s> <s>Palace</s> house, <s>with its</s>
          <s>now built of stone</s>, no longer a hut made of branches,
          no longer <s>a</s> <s>ma</s> <s>of</s> a <s>cold</s> <s>smoky</s> <s>home</s>
          thick with smoke, <s>no</s> with a log for a pillow:
          <s>It is now</s> It is now almost too luxurious
          for an old clergyman; with pillows, &amp;
          silver, &amp; glass windows; and the
          Queen has a [barge?] &amp; <s>the</s> London is a 
          city; &amp; there, 
            tho (though) he cannot see
          himself
          is , a [illeg.] yet
          kindly man, using language,
          
            wh. (which) 
            wd (would) have shocked his ancestors,
            adding a patron, , in
          flowing [prose?] that 
            wd (would) have shocked
          his ancestors, &amp; owning a mastiff.
          <s>The</s> The age of anonymity is over.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>