<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-1/845,149,161,137/full/0/default.tif">
          29
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-1/844,292,1812,1732/full/0/default.tif">
          Anonymity was a great possession. It gave the early<br/>
          plays <sup>writing</sup> a general nature.
            It (t) gave us the 
            ballads (ballds); it gave<br/>
           us the 
            songs (somgs). It allowed us to know nothing of the mans<br/>
          name.  had great privileges. He is not responsible.<br/>
          He is not self conscious. He can borrow. He can repeat.<br/>
          He can say what everyone feels. No one asks that he shall<br/>
          stamp his own name on his work. He keeps at a distance from<br/>
          the present moment. Anon the lyric writer 
            repeats (repeat) over and<br/>
          
            over (ove) again that flowers fade; that death is the end.<br/>
          He is never tired of 
            celebrating (clebrating) red roses and the white<br/>
          
            breast (bresast) of his mistress. The anonymous dxmxmxmxmxmx<br/>
          playwright has like the singer this 
            nameless (namless) vitality.<br/>
          something drawn from the crowd in the penny seats. and not<br/>
          yet dead in 
            ourselves (ouslves). For we too have become 
            anonymous (aninymous), and<br/>
          forget something that we have learnt, in reading the plays<br/>
          that no one troubled to set a name to.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-1/824,2044,1812,1204/full/0/default.tif">
          Later when the audience becomes critical, when the<br/>
          emotion in the audience becomes self 
            conscious (oncsious), when<br/>
          the country squire can say without quoting  what<br/>
          is in his mind, we lose this general quality to gain---<br/>
          everything it 
            seems (seemes). For until the  shut the 
            theatre (thea)<br/>
          the 
            curtain (curayin) rises 
            incessantly (incesaantly). It goes on rising until<br/>
          finally it rises on the . But by then the stage has<br/>
          become too small for the play. It has outgrown the uncovered<br/>
          theatre where 
            the (eh) sun beats and the rain pours. And the<br/>
          reader is born. He acts the play in the theatre of his own<br/>
          brain. Perhaps after centuries the play is born again,
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-3/957,59,195,169/full/0/default.tif">
          30
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-3/958,196,1762,804/full/0/default.tif">
          revealed, is often a 
            suspended (supended) derelict irrelevant beauty.<br/>
          There is no sequence. It does not connect; axxxx the<br/>
          rxmxmxmxmxf the parts are u 
            severed (sevred), and  something runs to<br/>
          waste. For the anonuymous playwright is 
            irresponsible (irrepsonsible).<br/>
          He flouts 
            truth (trith) at the bidding of the audience. he cares 
            only (ony)<br/>
          for the plot. We are left in the end without an end. The<br/>
          emotion is wasted.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-3/934,980,1778,2068/full/0/default.tif">
          But gradually the audience is mastered by the 
            playwright (playwrgiht).<br/>
          The mist withdraws. So many 
            dramatists (darmatists) are 
            exploring (explroing)<br/>
          tunnels that lead at last to some common 
            discovery (disocvery).<br/>
          So many private people are pressing their weight of<br/>
          
            unexpressed (eunexpressed) emotion upon the writers 
            consciousness (consciouness).<br/>
          Country squires are 
            learning (earning) to speak what they feel without<br/>
          quoting Spenser. The curtain rises on play 
            after (afte) play.<br/>
          Each time it rises upon a more detached, a more matured<br/>
          drama. The 
            individual (indivisual) on the stage becomes more and more<br/>
          
            differentiated (diife entiated); and the whole group is more closely<br/>
          
            related (rleated) and less at the mercy of the lp plot. The curtain<br/>
          rises upon Hxmxmmxmx ; and ;<br/>
          upon  and  and upon .<br/>
          Finally it rises upon the Tempest. But the play has outgrown<br/>
          the uncovered theatre where the 
            sun (s n) beats and the rain<br/>
          pours. That 
            theatre (thetare) must be replaced by the<br/>
          
            theatre (thestre) of the brain. The playwright is replaced by the man<br/>
          who writes a book. The audience is replaced by the reader.<br/>
          Anon is dead.
        </p> 
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-5/929,58,155,161/full/0/default.tif">
          31
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-5/981,226,553,163/full/0/default.tif">
          The RxxxxReader.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m111-2/m111-2-5/860,380,1836,3060/full/0/default.tif">
          The audience at the 
            Elizabethan (Elizabetahn) play was not an 
             (audiejce)<br/>
          of readers. They had to draw 
            in (int) the play through their ears, through their eyes<br/>
          They could not deepen the impression and renew<br/>
          it at a table in a private room. This perhaps explains<br/>
          the scarcity of Elizabethan criticism; and the general nature<br/>
          of what criticism there is. Both  and <br/>
          deal with the general rules of poetry; not with the 
            particular (particuar)<br/>
          play or poem. The lack of a book of the words accounts too<br/>
          for the long pause, between  death<br/>
          and the eighteenth century, 
            when (whe) the plays of 
            Shakespeare (Shakepere)<br/>
          even hang suspended, 
            unrealised (unrea ised). They had to wait until the<br/>
          printed book was in many hands before they received<br/>
          the life that the reader 
            confers (co fers) Much that was lost<br/>
          in the playhouse was 
            discovered (disocvered) in the private room.<br/>
          But 
            much (mu h) was lost for ever when the playhouse shut.<br/>
          Txmxmmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxm We have lost the sound of the<br/>
          spoken word; all that the sight of the actors bodies<br/>
          suggests to the mind through the eye. We have lost the<br/>
          sense of being part of the audience. We miss a 
            thousand (th usnd)<br/>
          suggestions that the dramatist conveyed by the inflection<br/>
          of voice, by gesture, by the placing of the actors bodies.<br/>
          This can still be proved by comparing our impression<br/>
          
            after (aft) seeing the play acted with our impression after reading<br/>
          the play alone. But as the actor 
            imports (ipmports) much that is of<br/>
          his own day, and 
            [foreign?] (foreing) to the past, so that there is t<br/>
          still something in every Elizabethan play sunk beyond recall.
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          30
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          Presumably the earlier plays, in which the playwright<br/>
          and the audience were mxxxx in closer cooperation, are the<br/>
          more damaged by reading them. The reader 
            instinctively (instinctivly) tries<br/>
          to be there in person. He tries to supply the trumpets<br/>
          and the flags; the citizens and the apprentices. He<br/>
          nourishes the 
            inadequate (inadeuate) emotion with a dip into ,<br/>
          with a dip into . He labours to supply the sunk<br/>
          part of the play. He is 
            perpetually (perpetaully) rebuffed. He is apt<br/>
          to become not a reader but a student; a 
            careful (crafeul) collector of<br/>
          old scattered bones. At some point however in Elizabethan<br/>
          drama the readerr is born. When the dramatist 
            becomes (beceomes) consi<br/>
          of the play as a work of art; when he is able to unite the<br/>
          play by something in himself--his personality, his<br/>
          conception-- it is then that, he brings the reader into 
            being (beig)
        </p>
        <p facs="">
          We can be sure then that the reader has been<br/>
          in existence for round about four hundred years. But his<br/>
          life history is an obscure one. At some point his ear must<br/>
          have lost 
            its (i s) 
            acuteness (acutness); then his 
            eyes (eyees) became dulled.<br/>
          Later he became more conscious of the suggestions and echoes<br/>
          in words. He imported much into the 
            written (w itten) word that was<br/>
          unintended xxxxxxx by the writer. A word given in its<br/>
          Elizabethan spelling brings in suggestions that give it<br/>
          almost another meaning. The words suggest other manners,<br/>
          other clothes. They accent the contrast between one society<br/>
          and another. And as the habit of reading becomes universal,<br/>
          many 
            varieties (varities) of reader are created. There are the<br/>
          
            specialised (s ecialised) readers whose power of 
            drawing (darwing) out the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>