<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M109 [The Reader: At what point in Elizabethan drama...]. Typescript, fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 9p.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m109</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M109 [The Reader: But under the ceiling, on the seats, there were gentlemen...]. Typescript, fragment, with the author's ms. corrections, unsigned and undated. 9p.</p>
            <p>Numbered 26-27, 31, 34-35. Page 30 filed as p. 178 verso in her Between the Acts, later typescript with ms. fragment.</p>
            <p>On fol. 1 verso: [The moment and other essays. Mrs Thrale] typescript</p>
            <p>On verso of p. 26-27: [Between the Acts] manuscript fragment</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-1/107,108,1466,1628/full/0/default.tif">
          At what point in 
            Elizabethan (E) drama<br/>
          <s>a</s> is the reader born?<br/>
          at what point does one<br/>
          come to be aware of their<br/>
          [shape?] in the play: of the<br/>
          presence of the audience: of the<br/>
          that of paper drawing up<br/>
          the past; &amp; become<br/>
          in a room reading alone?<br/>
          With 
             of course. <s>He</s> It was<br/>
          
            Shakespeare (Sh) who created the reader.<br/>
          And <s>changed</s> <s>liter</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-2/83,708,2205,2636/full/0/default.tif">
        It was her (h  ) marriage however that brought about her<br/>
        peculiar relationship with . Had she been happy,<br/>
        she would never have known him as she did. It was through<br/>
        him that she got what  denied -- stimulus, society,<br/>
        an outlet for her irrepressible curiosity and ambition.<br/>
        But the friendship (freindship) between the old man and the young wife<br/>
        went far deeper (depper) than  allowed the world to guess.<br/>
        Johnson was not merely a distinguished (distingusihed) guest at the dinner<br/>
        table. He had the run of the (th) house. He knew the  (th) dark passages<br/>
        and the cupboards with their skeletons. Mrs Thrale told him<br/>
        all her troubles. She turned to him when Queeney snubbed her;<br/>
        when Mr Txxxxxx <sup>Thrale</sup> took another mistress; when ruin threatened (threatned)<br/>
        them; when one after another the children fell ill, and<br/>
        died. "What shall I do? What can I do? has th flattery<br/>
        of my mxmxmxmxmmxmmmxxxmmx friends (freinds) made me too proud of my own
      </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-3/976,42,154,186/full/0/default.tif">
          26
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-3/895,192,1818,748/full/0/default.tif">
          But under the ceiling (celing), on the seats, there were gentlemen,<br/>
        and noblemen, men versed in Latin and Greek; scholars,<br/>
        courtiers, statesmen. Their silence was equally profound.<br/>
        But their influence was also effective. ThxmxBaconsxxmxmx<br/>
         and  found what suited them too<br/>
        in the 
          playhouse (plyhouse)
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs=""/>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-5/950,36,186,202/full/0/default.tif">
          27
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-5/896,216,1812,3220/full/0/default.tif">
          for ever weaving nets and threading mazes 
            must (mist) relax them<br/>
          
            themselves (slves). The  must have players to divert her.<br/>
          With all his craft and caution he himself 
            embodies (emdoies) 
            substantiates (substantias)<br/>
          his meditations, gives them a body, a name a shape.<br/>
          
            "Nay, retire men cannot, when they would: 
              neither (neihter) will they<br/>
            when it were Reason: But are impatient of privateness<br/>
            even in Age and Sicknesse, which require the 
              [Shadow?] (Sa dow):<br/>
            Like old 
              Townsmen (Townemen) that will still be sitting at their strete<br/>
            d or door, those who thereby they offer 
              Age (Agge) to Scorn."
          
          Even the <sup>[crowd?]</sup> pressure of great 
            thoughts (tho ts) issue in a concrete shape.<br/>
          These short meditations were 
            themselves (themslves) making it possible<br/>
          for the dramatist to <sup>[illeg.]</sup> impart them where they seemed<br/>
          
            inappropriate (i appropitae). <sup>For</sup> Everything when times are 
            absorbent (abobrent) yields<br/>
          some savour to the stew. The 
            irresponsible (i responsible) 
            mountebanks (mountbanks),<br/>
          clothed in their 
            invisible (invisble) garment of anonymity were<br/>
          Gos spies, in the streets, also at Court.<br/>
          If at  or at , one of them caught sight<br/>
          of that grave 
            inscrutable (inscrutbale) figure, he could 
            quickly (uickly) add<br/>
          him to 
            the (t) list of characters. And hyperbole, though the<br/>
          
            groundlings (gr ndl gs) lusted 
            for (fot) it, required correction. Bacon<br/>
          
            despising (despsing) 
            the (th) 
            theatre (thetre) for its hyperbole was 
            held (hel) contempt for the stage 
            was (w) medicinal. He was teaching them<br/>
          to speak slowly, closely, subtly: to stiffen their<br/>
          poetry with prose: A great age is like youth in 
            the (th)<br/>
          individual. Any hint is heard. Any voice takes 
            effect (effcet).<br/>
          Criticism, a grave 
            man (an) 
            frowning (frwoning) in his corner of the royal<br/>
          box is <sup>drawn into</sup> affecting the current. And so, as 
            the (th) seasons pass,<br/>
          the aristocratic contempt 
            severs (sevres) to restrain; The 
            crabbed (cabbbed)<br/>
          prose of Bacon is seized and 
            transformed (transfomred). The plays are
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-7/832,88,145,151/full/0/default.tif">
          31
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-7/796,228,1796,3188/full/0/default.tif">
          The great house that  
            deplored (delpored) becomes solid and<br/>
          entire in the pages of Lady  diary.<br/>
          <sup>From the first she is aware of her rights of a noble.</sup> She is aware from her first youth of her rights as a<br/>
          land owner. She has a profound sense of the<br/>
          the rights of the 
            possessor (possesor). The body is visible to her.<br/>
          <sup>what she [illeg.], the [illeg.]</sup>She is for ever rebuilding castles,<br/>
          acquiring land, asserting her rights to property,<br/>
          claiming diamond buttons, making 
            inventories (inventroies) of her 
            possessions (possesin)<br/>
          as if to 
            solidify (soldify) them further. <sup>Family love is in part the desire to maintain her [honour?]</sup> She has asense of the<br/>
          family who will 
            inherit (imherit) her possessions.<br/>
          She sends for her 
            grandchildren (grandcholdren) in order that 
            they (ghey) may<br/>
          taste the delight of 
            possession (posseson) and so refresh her own satis<br/>
          faction. The living body is robed in black and yellow<br/>
          taffeta. Clothes are so 
            important (imp rtant) that they become things<br/>
          to be handed on. The living body is robed in<br/>
          black and yellow taffeta. The dead body is sealed in lead<br/>
          to preserve its flesh from 
            decay (d cay). The The sense of the<br/>
          body permeates her pages; <s>whether alive or dead.</s><br/>
          The human soul seems to become more expressive when its<br/>
          
            carcass (carcase) flashed in the public eye. All movements of the human<br/>
          body, from place to place, are attended with great effort;<br/>
          and become 
            spectacular (specatacular). Six bay horses drag the coach;<br/>
          
            The (Th) coach is lined with green cloth, and laced<br/>
          with green and black silk lace. 
            Crowds (Crwods) 
            attend (attned) her.<br/>
          She is for ever asserting her identity,<br/>
          with 
            initials (inittails) carved in stone even over 
            farmhouse (farm hous) walls.<br/>
          This is her property; this land is hers by right.<br/>
          Fxmxmxmxmxmmxmx 
            Certain (Certian) flesh and blood--txmxmmxmxmxmx
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-7/206,302,646,618/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            of what was<br/>
            due to her <br/>
            birth ––<br/>
            then, as she grows older,<br/>
            she fights, even in the<br/>
            Kings presence, for her<br/>
            land
          </sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-9/885,113,175,147/full/0/default.tif">
          34
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-9/795,268,1859,2052/full/0/default.tif">
          much sharper. As these faculties became atrophied,<br/>
          he became more conscious of the suggestions and<br/>
          associations of words. Txxxs One word written in 
            Elizabethan (Elizabathn)<br/>
          spelling bxmxmxmxmx xxxx has suggestions that give it<br/>
          almost another meaning. It suggests other manners, other<br/>
          clothes; the difference between one society and another.<br/>
          Then as reading becomes a universal habit, readers split<br/>
          off into many varieties. There are the specialised readers,<br/>
          whose power of 
            drawing (darwing) out the meaning of words is<br/>
          tremendously developed; so that they remain attached to 
            certain (certn)<br/>
          aspects of the printed wxxdxx page--the scholars, the<br/>
          students. At the opposite end of the scale, there is the<br/>
          very large class of perfectly literate people whose eyes<br/>
          travel over miles of print yearly, yet never read a word.<br/>
          <sup>Some <s>way</s> <sup>where</sup> between the two,</sup> The reader at the present moment exxxxxsx is placed somewhere<br/>
          between these two extremes. And his faculty is a very<br/>
          
            curious (curous) one. He has the power to make houses and<br/>
          places, men and women and their thoughts and emotions<br/>
          
            visible (isible) to him, from marks on a piece of paper.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-9/743,2344,1835,1124/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Somewhere (Somehwere) between the two comes the reader. His faculty is a<br/>
          very curious one. He has the power to make houses and places<br/>
          visible from marks on a 
            piece (ipiece) of paper; to draw 
            emotions (emitons)<br/>
          of 
            every (very) kind; and also some quality that is independent<br/>
          of emotion; form; unity. He is capable of all the<br/>
          impulses of a writer; but lacks the power of creation.<br/>
          His 
            influence (influnece) upon what is 
            written (wr tten) at any time is<br/>
          immense; In times of public stress, for instance, the writer<br/>
          is 
            incapable (uincapable) of 
            writing (swriting); in part at least because<br/>
          he has no audience. The life of a reader is thus
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-11/856,90,158,138/full/0/default.tif">
          35
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-11/848,188,1692,276/full/0/default.tif">
          Thus the life of a reader is bound<br/>
          up in the life of the book. <sup>a xxxx constantly merging</sup> is to some extent the life of <sup>the book.</sup>
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m109/m109-11/780,432,1852,1108/full/0/default.tif">
          It was to satisfy this unshaled blind infant,<br/>
          
            stretching (s retching) out his hands and covering his eyes in the Eliza<br/>
          bethan playhouse that the 
            owe (oew) the Elizabethans novels.<br/>
          or that very curious book <br/>
          a half born book; a book that is still amorphous<br/>
          
            neither (neother) one thing nor the 
            other (othet); a book that cannot walk;<br/>
          and yet now and then like an 
            unwieldy (unwildy) child gambols and<br/>
          breaks the 
            ornaments (ornmanets). But while  lived,<br/>
          the novel was always turning into the play. The reader<br/>
          was too weak to make his influence felt.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>