<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M54, 2 of 11. [Anon: The historians work from the outer to the inner...]. Typescript fragment, 5 fols.</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m54-2</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M54, 2 of 11. [The historians work from the outer to the inner...]. Typescript fragment, 2 fols.</p>
            <p>N.B.: This is one of eleven sub-fragments identified the Berg Collection's M54. [Anon: The printing press brought the past into existence...]. Typescript fragments, unsigned and undated, 35 fols. I have determined pagination and sequencing based on subject matter. M54 as curated by the Berg Collection is available as part of 'The Digital Anon' and can be found at [LINK].</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-1/805,48,173,182/full/0/default.tif">
          8
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-1/819,212,1781,1534/full/0/default.tif">
          The historians work from the outer to the inner; from the
          house they infer the 
            teant (tenant) of the house. It is the house 
            thy (they)
          dwell upon; the chairs and the furniture of the house.
          It is as if we were told 
            nbideen (bidden) to infer from
          a tweed suit, and six hats, and a fox terrier, and a
          
            waljing (walking) stick and a c kitchen with a 
            col (coal) fire and a
          servant pcalled perhaps Joan <sup>the life and 
            woks (works) of a novelist call 
            </sup> that  wrote the 
          and  Save for  and 
          and the voice of Anon singing at the back door the English
          might be a dumb race, who suffered 
            nad (and) ennjoyed in 
            silnce (silence);
          a race of 
            me rhcnats (merchants), soldiers and 
            preists (priests) <sup>builders</sup> who left behind 
            thm (them)
          stone houses, cultivated fields and vast cathedrals. but
          not <sup>no</sup> words. The great house is silent; Only the furniture
          
            mains (remains), stiff and ornate, 
            fanastic (fantastic) and uncushioned.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-1/815,1758,1781,1534/full/0/default.tif">
          At  for instance  sat at her table
          writing <sup>letters</sup>. <s>But</s> <sup>H</sup>er letters to  are letter written <sup>[illeg.]</sup>
          from the pulpit; as intricate involved and formal as state
          papers or legal documents or 
            dyin depositons (dying depositions). She admonishes and preaches;
          she expresses the violence of her temper and the<sup>her 
            violene (violence) and her 
            suspiions (suspicions);</sup>
          suspicions of her soul. She is a counsellor admonishing a
          subordinate. She is <sup>aware</sup> expressive only of 
            th (the) wickedness of
          men, the dangers and deceits of the world; and the
          
            awfu;ness (awfulness) of her God. Greek and Latin come to her pen
          as easily as English. If she has to 
            decend (descend) to the actual 
            objec (object)
          a basket of 
            starwberries (strawberries)-- it is with 
            coircomlocution (circumlocution) and
          dark threats. "I have sent them by 
            th (the) boy of my kitchen,
          a shrewd witted boy and prettily cachetized, but yet an
          untoward crafty boy..." She writes 
            onlt (only) to
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-3/817,75,153,139/full/0/default.tif">
          9
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-3/851,196,1773,1318/full/0/default.tif">
          exhort "God keep us sound in the faith and send us health
          and a care to please God above all" Or to admonish---
          
            "Be not speedy of speech, nor talk suddenly, but where
            discretion requireth, and that soberly then....
            Let not Lawson, that fox, be 
              acqaunited (acquainted) with my letters..."
          
          Fear of man, fear of God surround them as h as with the 
            wallsof (walls of)
          a dungeon. There is no gaiety, no freedom, no 
            familairity (familiarity)
          
            ni (in) the 
            hose (house) she lives in. The sound of the Bible is in her
          
            wars (words). Her prose takes its 
            slolemn (solemn) strain. And the prose
          of the bible will not adapt itself to the 
            eaxy (easy), the 
            co  oqu (colloquial)
          It is a garment to be put on when the mind is erect and
          dignified, on state 
            oaccions (occasions).
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-3/785,1496,1873,1766/full/0/default.tif">
          It is because they use of the prose of the bible when
          they write prose that the Elizabethans are unknown to us.
          It They can say nothing 
            simle (simple), nothing intimate.
          They are 
            nevr (never) subtle; they are never shaded. Bright 
            contrastd (contrasted)
          colours meet on their faces. Carnation and 
            sanow (snow);
          ebony and gold. When we look at them we see them
          in their 
            farthibgales (farthingales) and 
            ru ffs (ruffs);
          young 
            men s (men's) bodies
          are stiffly sewn into 
            dohblets (doublets) and school boys faces
          are raised above starched collars; 
            yong (young) women serve only to s
          display heavy quilted 
            dresse (dresses) stuck about with huge pearls.
          The writer, 
            to  rds (towards) the end of the 
            sicteenth cnyury (sixteenth century),
          was separate from his 
            arudience (audience); but he was still closely
          connected with it. He was himself unspecialised, 
            un ifferent (undifferentiated)
          ated. His eye was stimulated by the crimsons and gold and
          greens of the clothing. His ear was stimulated by the
          sound of words For 
              ac  (each) word was given substance and sharpness
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-5/889,131,115,155/full/0/default.tif">
          10
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-5/825,244,1797,1706/full/0/default.tif">
          by the speaking voice. And the 
            l tes (lutes) and the 
            cithersn (citherns)
          
            have (gave) lilt and 
            rhym (rhythm) and melody to the spoken word.
          His mind was full of half sung half 
            spoekn (spoken) words;
          full of undifferentiated words; 
            ol (old) words, new words; French words
          Latin words. No grammar bound them tightly together.
          They were elastic. They could stretch to any 
            lgneth (length). They 
            cd (could)
          could 
            refelct (reflect) many colours; they could 
            fol ow (follow) many tunes,
          they could be danced to, and sung to. But they could not
          follow the words of the speaking voice. For a moment then
          there is a pause on the threshold of the 
            gre t (great) 
            lizabethan (Elizabethan)
          room. The artist is not wholly writer, wholly musician, or
          wholly 
            paineter (painter). xmxsxmxsmssxmxsxmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxsxmxmxmxmxmxmmx
          xmxmxmxmmxmxmxmxmxmxmmxmxmxm.  may be 
          ; 
            Soenser (Spenser) may be . It seems possible that the
          great English art may not be the art of poetry.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-7/899,80,137,153/full/0/default.tif">
          10
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-7/1035,217,239,113/full/0/default.tif">
          ......
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-7/783,316,1897,2732/full/0/default.tif">
          The writer then came to birth with difficulty in
          England; for so long as familiar letters are written in
          Biblical prose there are limits to his freedom; a barrier
          between the sayable and the unsayable. He is in being;
          for the printing press has given him a name; but still
          unspecialised, undifferentiated. The artist is not wholly
          
            write (writer), wholly musician, or wholly painter. It seems
          possible that the great English art may not be the art of
          words. His eye is stimulated by the colour of the
          of the 
            clotning (clothing), of the pageantry. his ear by the sound of
          words spoken aloud. <sup>For books were read aloud.</sup> "
            Prtitachrd (Pritchard)" wrote 
          "read aloud the ..... They read aloud 
          and the Faery Queen." Every word was given sharpness and
          substance by the speaking voice. And the lute, the cithern,
          the old full bodied instrument that still stands on a
          
            ches (chest), 
            hgave (gave) lilt, rhythm, melody to the word.
          
            "Hardly one lighter or boat in 
              hree (three) that had the goods
            of a house in it , but there was a pair of virginals in
          
          it"  observed in 1666 when the people of London were
          loading their goods onto boats to escape from the fire of
          London. His mind the was full of undifferentiated words, 
            ole (old)
          words and new words; French and Latin. No grammar bound them
          tightly together. They were elastic; they could be danced to
          and sung to. But they could not follow the pace of the
          
            spea ing (speaking) voice.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-7/805,3040,1893,382/full/0/default.tif">
           then in the  is like a
          half articulate monster rising from the depths of 
            silnce (silence)
          hung with the weeds and pearls of the deep sea in
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-9/1027,70,181,169/full/0/default.tif">
          11
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-9/983,208,1747,1892/full/0/default.tif">
          he the writer has been so long submerged. We cannot read
          the 
            ; nor leave it 
            undread (unread). It is a poem
          without a plot; the metre, casting its regular fling of
          sound, comes to ground 
            to (too) evenly, too solidly, unlike
           who goes on, simply, directly, at an even pace.
          Great groups, composed, arranged, come together with the
          
            orest (forest) for 
            back rg und (background).  must have seen Italian
          pictures; or was it natural then to make compositions even
          in words? The 
            Knihgyts (knights) the 
            ldaies (ladies) and the ogres
          pass away amble their way through the glades and become
          one with the clouds. Like a 
            lcliund ([cloud?]) the words move up and
          down; 
            furst (first) lulling the ear then cloying the ear.
          It has the sweetness of a dream; something cut adrift from
          the rough 
            rish (Irish) land which lay outside; it has freshness,
          it has 
            csharpness (sharpness). It is the thing itself;
          it is the original design, from which  and 
          
            mad (made) their copies.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-10/479,64,1909,1758/full/0/default.tif">
          Latimer heard them. He raged.
          His is the voice of the new
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-10/457,1774,1557,350/full/0/default.tif"/>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-10/559,2048,2033,596/full/0/default.tif"/>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m54-2/m54-2-10/515,2528,2153,828/full/0/default.tif"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>