<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>M51. Anon. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. correction on p. 3, unsigned and undated. 9p. Wanting p. 1. Paginated 2-10</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name>Joshua Phillips</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>The Leverhulme Trust: Grant ECF-2022-602</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Estate of Virginia Woolf, administered by the Society of Authors</authority>
        <availability>
          <p>© Estate of Virginia Woolf 2022</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
            <repository>Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature</repository>
            <idno>m51</idno>
          </msIdentifier>        
          <physDesc>
            <p>M51. Anon. Typescript fragment, with the author's ms. correction on p. 3, unsigned and undated. 9p. Wanting p. 1. Paginated 2-10</p>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="ms" scribe="vwoo" script="handwritten">
          <p>Holograph writing by the documents' main hand, Virginia Woolf</p>
        </handNote>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="markup">
          <p>Apparent errors have been explicitly corrected in sic / corr tags, wrapped in a choice element.</p>
        </correction>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Names and references to places and literary works have been wrapped in rs tags which link to annotations and secondary material.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text encoded as part of 'The Digital "Anon": A Digital Genetic Edition of Virginia Woolf's Final Essays'. This project, funded by Leverhulme Grant ECF-2022-602, seeks to construct a TEI-XML based digital edition of the drafts of 'Anon' and 'The Reader', among the final documents Woolf wrote before her death.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/950,26,264,256/full/0/default.tif">
          2<br/>
          Anon.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/992,236,1736,444/full/0/default.tif">
          common voice singing out of doors. he has no house. He lives<br/>
          a roaming life, crossing the fields, 
            mounting (moutning) the hills,<br/>
          and lying down by the hawthown to listen to 
            the (te) nightingale.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/906,624,1804,884/full/0/default.tif">
          Still, by shutting out a 
            chimney (chimey) or a bungalow<br/>
          we can see what  saw-- the bird haunted reed whispering<br/>
          fen, the down, and the green scar never healed along which<br/>
          he came when he made his journeys. He was a 
            simple (simp le) singer,<br/>
          lifting a song or a story from other peoples lips, and 
            letting (lettig)<br/>
          the 
            audience (auience) join in the 
            chorus (chours). Sometimes he made a few<br/>  
          lines that exactly 
            matched his (matchedhis) 
            emotion (emtoin)--he was an 
            artist (arist).
        </p>
        <p facs="">
           <br/>
           <br/>
           <br/>
           <br/>
           
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/868,1708,1364,120/full/0/default.tif">
          But there is no name to that song.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/930,1826,1784,352/full/0/default.tif">
          When at last the house was built, he 
            sung (song) only at  the<br/>
          back door.  Upstairs they spoke French; his song was sung<br/>
          in English; and the words were so uncouth
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/1262,2156,852,180/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Icham for woing al forwake<br/>
            Wery no water in wore
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/928,2308,1036,144/full/0/default.tif">
          that they 
            need (n ed) a 
            dictionary (ditioc nary) now.]
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/1276,2426,852,180/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Icham for woing al forwake<br/>
            Wery no water in wore
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-1/872,2600,1840,812/full/0/default.tif">
          
            But (Bu ) to the listener then, to  for 
            example ( xample) in his<br/>
          
            parsonage (pasronage), they were not only difficult. They were painful.<br/>
          They reminded him of his lack of intellectual [illeg.]<br/>
          His intellectual pedigree reached 
            back (vack) only to <br/>
          , , a bare 
            hundred (hundre) and fifty years.<br/>
          To have 
            ancestors (anscestors) he must 
            cross (ross) the . His ancestors<br/>
          by way of the mind are Greeks and 
            Romans (Rla ns). His page is
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-3/891,52,156,180/full/0/default.tif">
          3
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-3/888,194,1748,468/full/0/default.tif">
          
            burdened (bu dened) with 
            protestations (protesttaions) of (og) good breeding-- 
            <br/>
          ;  , ; --xxxxxxx<br/>
            ixx quotes them to prove his good breeding as we to prove<br/>
            ours quote the 
              Elizabethans (Elizabthans).
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-3/779,612,1966,2832/full/0/default.tif">
           was not a 
            respectable (respecable) ancestor. He was nameless<br/>
          because he was 
            disreputable (disrputable). Even the Kings and Queens must<br/>
          have their 
            singers (sin ers), their 
            minstrels (mistrels), their xxxxxxx actors.<br/>
          But he was despised. Did he not feeling himself an outcast,<br/>
          use the outsiders privilege of 
            irresponsible (irreponsible) mockery?<br/>
          Hewas tolerated, as we tolerate those who say out loud<br/>
          what we think, but will not admit. So he sang, danced<br/>
          
            juggled ( uggled) and led his bears to the back 
            door (doot). He sings to<br/>
          serving men and maids. He tells them what they have heard<br/>
          
            already (aldready)--old stories in 
            in those ( inm hose) choruses they can join.<br/>
          When the great Elizabethan house was built, he was still<br/>
          nameless, 
            disreputable (disreptuable),  the 
            parson (prason) of <br/>
          in  instead of setting down those 
            songs (ongs), digs up<br/>
          coins. He already 
            sees (s  s) the present against the past.<br/>
          The past has become so settled that 
            the (yhe) present looks<br/>
          
            ungainly ( ngainly) and 
            degenerate (d g n rate) against it. There is too much<br/>
          comfort, too many 
            pillows (pi  ows), too many chimneys. The young<br/>
           and  are not the men their fathers were.<br/>
          The 
            smoke (msmoke) drawn up by the 
            chimneys (chimeys) no 
            longer (lo ger) hardens them.<br/>
          They are tender and subject to rheumatism. They dress<br/>
          
            fantastically (fantatically) compared with their 
            ancestors. (ancestor.s) It does not<br/>
          occur to him to set down the songs that were being sung, to<br/>
          describe the 
            pageants, (pagentatns ,) the 
            mumming (mu ming), the plays that the<br/>
          wandering 
            minstrels (mistrels) enacted. The English past served only to<br/>
          show the material change-- the change 
            that (tha) had come over
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-3/495,1644,439,496/full/0/default.tif">
          <sup>
            Latimer,<br/>
            <s>Go[wer],</s><br/>
            Langland
          </sup>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-5/898,60,160,176/full/0/default.tif">
          4
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-5/850,202,1856,332/full/0/default.tif">
          houses, 
            furniture (furinture)
            clothing (clothing½) There was no English literature<br/>
          to show up the change in the mind. There were no English<br/>
          
            books (boo s) to show up the decline of English writing.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-5/828,520,1864,2912/full/0/default.tif">
          Up stairs in the great room, as 
            Harrison (Ha ison) tells us,<br/>
          "...our ancient ladies of the 
            court (co rt)" 
            were (we e) to be found reading<br/>
          the 
            Greeks (Gekks) and Latins as they sat at their 
            needlework (needlwork).<br/>
          xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx Greek and Latin<br/>
          came as easily to their pens as English. At <br/>
          
            instance (isnatnec)  sat writing to her son. Her letters<br/>
          might have been sermons from the pulpit. Shxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx<br/>
          xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx She 
            exhorted (exhorst); she 
            admonished (admonsihed).<br/>
          Fear of God, 
            suspicion (suspcion) of man surround her with the walls<br/>
          of a dungeon. There is no gaiety, no familiarity, no intimacy<br/>
          in this world. 
            She ( hw) 
            drapes (draoes) herself in the 
            language (langauge) of the 
            Bible (B  le)<br/>
          when she writes; and it is a garment only to fit a certain<br/>
          attitude. Save for  and  and the voice of<br/>
           singing at the back door, making his 
            irreverent (irrevent) mockeries<br/>
          xmxmxmxmxmx the English might be a dumb race; a race of<br/>
          merchants 
            soldiers (soliders) priests, who left 
            behind ( ehind) them stone houses<br/>
          cultivated fields and many churches, but no words. The<br/>
          great house is 
            silent (sielnt). We can see it still, 
            standing (satnding) in its<br/>
          green island of park, 
            separated (seaparated) often from the high road,<br/>
          only by a dip in the ground and a low red wall. It is out<br/>
          of 
            proportion (porpotion) now; 
            either (iether) it is too large or the<br/>
          village with its 
            bungalows (bungalwos) and shops is too small. The 
            furniture (furn)<br/>
          is in 
            existence (exsitnce) too. Inside all is kept as if the Queen were<br/>
          expected. The up right Elizabethan chairs stand round the<br/>
          walls. Their fringes and their 
            tapestry (tap st y) is not much faded<br/>
          The oak tables are heavy and polished. The floor is 
            strewn (str wn)
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-7/898,142,124,136/full/0/default.tif">
          5
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-7/902,236,1740,596/full/0/default.tif">
          The oak tables are heavy and polished. The floor is<br/>
          laid with rugs; cut glass 
            chandeliers (chand liers) hang down from the<br/>
          decorated plaster work of the 
            ceiling (celing). 
            Knick knacks (Kick kncaks) have 
            survived (survid)<br/>
          an inlaid work box, an old doublet; and the pear shaped<br/>
          lute that the  once played.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-7/808,796,1856,2584/full/0/default.tif">
          But 
            if (of) the great 
            Elizabethan (Elizabethna) house looks to us out of<br/>
          proportion, a derelict among the bungalows, it is 
            because (b cause)<br/>
          the connection between it and the village is lost. If we<br/>
          could see the great house as it was in  time we<br/>
          should see tracks raying out from the great house across the<br/>
          fields to the cottage, to the farm, even to the hovel.<br/>
          Paths were worn by the fighters; and the ploughers.<br/>
          They must be armed against other men. They must<br/>
          plough and sow together if they were not to starve in winter<br/>
          This connection 
            between (isbetween) master and man is 
            painfully (pa nfully)<br/>
          
            minutely recorded (minutelt recoredc) in the medieval letters. 
            It is (I Its is) the 
            staple (stape)<br/>
          of 
            the (th) whole correspondence between  <sup>of </sup> and the <br/>
          and the  of . But there was also the other<br/>
          less 
            visible (visibl) connection--the common belief. That<br/>
          bond between the houses has been 
            grown (gorwn) over, 
            lies (li e) the track<br/>
          along which the  rode to .<br/>
          Nobody rides there now. But when  made 
            his (is)<br/> 
           that track led from house to house. It led to the<br/>
          village green; it led to the tree; to the 
            well (welll). In the<br/>
          spring they danced round the maypole; in at midsummer they<br/>
          
            lit (llit) the bon fire on the hill. At christmas the mummers<br/>
          acted their dumb shows; and the boys came 
            wassailing (wassiling).<br/>
          The road led to the old Kings graces, to the stones
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-9/909,97,80,88/full/0/default.tif">
          6
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-9/823,200,1903,768/full/0/default.tif">
          where the old pagan English had done sacrifice.<br/>
          The peasants still went that way by instinct, in spring<br/>
          and summer and winer. The old Gods lay 
            hidden (hideen) beneath the<br/>
          new. If they were nameless now, it was to them, not to the<br/>
          Christian God, that the 
            peasants (peants) did homage; wearing their<br/>
          green leaves to 
            propagate (propittte) the earth Goddess; dancing through<br/>
          the houses; killing the old; reviving the new.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-9/853,960,1815,2336/full/0/default.tif">
          It is in the twenty one books of the <br/>
          that we tap into the deep 
            reservoir (resev ir) of common belief that<br/>
          sunk , in the minds of the nobles and peasants.<br/>
          It is in  pages that we hear the voice of <br/>
          
            murmuring (murmurinf) still. Kings and Queens, nobles and 
            peasants (peasnts)<br/>
          remembered how the old King and his knights went<br/>
          their ways through the wild woods seeking adventure. When<br/>
           himself doubted if any such man had ever been,<br/>
          the gentlemen of England were positive. They said that you<br/>
          could see  skull at ; and the <br/>
          at ; and "in otherplaces  sword and many<br/>
          other things." Txxxxxxxxxxxxxx In <br/>
          time a 
            silver (silv r) horse shoe had been found at . The book<br/>
          comes to at the very moment when the old stories were<br/>
          fading. It xxxxxxxxx is half fable, half fact.<br/>
          There is ; and  and ; there is the<br/>
           and . But the roads lead<br/>
          past London to cast s where Knights lie enchanted;<br/>
          down the roads ride for Queens on white mules; <br/>
           turns herself suddenly to stone; and a hand rises from<br/>
          a lake holding . 
            It is (Itis) a childs story, in the
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-11/936,84,150,122/full/0/default.tif">
          7
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-11/893,194,1831,764/full/0/default.tif">
          simplicity of its belief. It is a 
            child's (chi  s) story in its<br/>
          particularity. Beauty is stated, not suggested. So he went
          
            in and searched from chamber to chamber, and found his bed,<br/>
            but she was 
              not (ot) here; then Balin looked into a little garden,<br/>
            and under a laurel tree 
              he saw (e sae) her lie upon a quilt of green<br/>
            samite and a knght with her, and under their heads<br/>
            
              grass (grasa) and herbs."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-11/951,940,1751,1216/full/0/default.tif">
          But, save that self 
            consciousness (oncsiousnes) has not yet raised<br/>
          its mirror, it is not a childs world. The men and women are<br/>
          corrupt already in this fresh world. They have evil dreams.<br/>
           is doomed. 
            Great kings ( reat ki gs) are undone by their own vices.<br/>
          The 
            Queens (Quuens) are lustful. Still we can 
            revisit (revsit) their world.<br/>
          But of the 
            writer (wr ter) nothing is known.  is not distinct<br/>
          from his book. It is still the voice of , speaking to<br/>
          the voice of anon. The dream is still dreamt. "...folks<br/>
          do say" a 
            peasant (peasnt) at  said in the 
            nineteenth (ninenenth) century,<br/>
          "that on the night of the full moon King Arthur and his men<br/>
          ride round the hill, and their horses are shod with silver..."
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-11/953,2156,1751,1216/full/0/default.tif">
          , printing the  at the 
            solicitation (solitictaion)<br/>
          of the nobles and the gentry, had his doubts. Anon wxxxx<br/>
          still 
            existed (existsed) but a shade has fallen 
            upon (upo) him. The printed<br/>
          book with its writers name attached to was destined to kill<br/>
          him. After that, the audience became separate from<br/>
          the singer. And the 
            audience (audeince) no longer took part in the song<br/>
          
            supplied (supp ied) the story, filled in the pauses, and added sometimes<br/>
          a nonsensical chorus. The printed book 
            separated (seapareted) from the<br/>
          voice and was read by those who could afford to buy them.<br/>
          The great read them in the great rooms. "I spent most of
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-13/940,89,124,136/full/0/default.tif">
          8
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-13/909,200,1763,464/full/0/default.tif">
          my time" wrote  playing at Clecko
          
            and hearing  read the ...  used to<br/>
            
              read (r ad) to me in   and Moll Neville in the<br/>
            ."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-13/859,660,1827,2304/full/0/default.tif">
          The book must find its way into the hall, into the<br/>
          great room where 
            nobles (novles) and 
            gentry (genrty) have 
            leisure (liesure) to read<br/>
          after the 
            business (busniess) and the sport of the day is over.<br/>  
          And with the printed book, the writer at last comes into<br/>
          existence--the writer wxxxxx who, 
            unlike (unl e) the 
            minstrel (mistrel),<br/>
          has a name; whose words are printed. He is in being after<br/>
          1477 but he 
            is still undifferentiated (stillundiffrentiated), limited. For when familiar<br/>
          letters are written in Biblical prose, only in emergency<br/>
          there must be a barrier between the sayable and the unsayable<br/>
          a limit to what can be put into words. The artist-- who<br/>
          stands outside, by some impulse desiring to observe and to<br/>
          state rather than to take part, is not wholly writer,<br/>
          wholly musician or wholly painter. It seems possible that the<br/>
          great English art may not 
            be (b ) the art of letters. 
            Every (   ry) word<br/>
          is read aloud; every word is given weight and edge by the<br/>
          speaking voice. And then the lute, the virginals 
            they (the)<br/>
          gave lilt, 
            rhythm (rhymn) and melody ot the written word.<br/>
          When in 1666 the london was burning and the citizens<br/>
          were loading their goods into boats  noted that "hardly
          
            one lighter or boat in 
              three (threee) that had the goods of a<br/>
              house in it, but there was a pair of virginals in it."
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-13/897,2938,1807,352/full/0/default.tif">
          Music, and the speaking voice lay beneath the words;<br/>
          and the words themselves were elastic. No grammar bound them<br/>
          tightly together. They could be danced to and sung to. 
            Nevertheless (Neverh)
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-15/965,123,112,142/full/0/default.tif">
          9
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-15/908,264,1748,312/full/0/default.tif">
          
            Nevertheless (theless), they could not follow the speaking voice, that<br/>
          voice that talks briefly, colloquially. The audience is<br/>
          speechless.
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-15/959,608,1694,2728/full/0/default.tif">
           
            then (the n), standing on the threshold of the<br/>
          great room at --"a little man with short<br/>
          hair, a small band and cuffs"--- was separate from Anon the<br/>
          
            minstrel (misntrel); separate from 
            Holinshed (Holingshed) the 
            chronicler (chorniclaer); and<br/>
          separate, in that he saw the scene with detachment and wished<br/>
          to record it, 
            from (fro ) his 
            audience (audie ce). But the book which had<br/>
          given his word a separate 
            existence (exsience), had brought into being<br/>
          a little group of readers. That influence, unknown to Anon,<br/>
          began at once to exert its pressure. What is 
            the (he) poem that<br/>
          will please ? What is the theme that will<br/>
          flatter the ? What will so flatter the audience that<br/>
          they will procure for the poet a place, a pension?<br/>
          From this 
            time (tiem) onward these are to be among the influences<br/>
          that tug, that distort, that 
            thwart (twart); as also they<br/>
          stimulate, and draw out. There are some among them<br/>
          that the writer only 
            realises (reaslies); others that the readers<br/>
          in time to come discover. More and more complex do 
            they (t ey)<br/>
          grow, as 
            the (t e) book with the authors name on it<br/>
          
            reaches (r aches) a more various a more divided 
            audience (audi ce). The the<br/>
          public insists; it wants, according to its 
            wealth (welah) and its<br/>
          
            poverty (poeverty), its education or 
            ignorance (irgnoarnce,), now 
            history (hist ry)<br/>
          now 
            melodrama (meloframa), now 
            poetry (powtry), now whatever will make it forget<br/>
          its drab and dismal existence. As the book becomes more and<br/>
          more aware of these 
            influences (infl unces) the thing that the writer
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
      <div xmlns="">
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-17/854,104,120,120/full/0/default.tif">
          
          10 (LO)
          
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-17/837,218,1743,984/full/0/default.tif">
          More and more deflected by these 
            influences (infleunces), the thing that<br/>
          the writer has to say becomes increasingly cumbered. It is<br/>
          only to be 
            discovered (dsicover d) in flash 
            intuition (intuiton). Thus some say<br/>
          that their beards bristle when they come upon it; others<br/>
          that a thrill runs down the nerves of the thigh. To 
            disengage (disengag)<br/>
          the song from its encumbrances becomes as time goes on<br/>
          a task for the critic--that 
            specially (sp cially) equipped taster<br/>
          who was not in existence when  stood on the threshold<br/>
          of the great room at .
        </p>
        <p facs="https://llkn576nqxepo6yucgfh2nl2ea0kkigc.lambda-url.eu-west-2.on.aws/iiif/2/m51/m51-17/1053,1216,1152,90/full/0/default.tif">
          It was still connected with the village.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div xmlns=""/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>